[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "What is the length of a motif, in terms of amino acids residue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30- 60",
            "b) 10- 20",
            "c) 70- 90",
            "d) 1- 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A typical motif is 10-20 amino acids long. For e.g. Zn-finger motif. Hence it is also referred to as super secondary structure. This motif is seen in transcription factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "On average, what is the length of a typical domain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) About 100 residues",
            "b) About 300 residues",
            "c) About 500 residues",
            "d) About 900 residues"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The predicted optimal number of residues, which corresponds to the maximum free energy of unfolding, is 100. This is in agreement with a statistical analysis derived from their experimental structures of motifs. For too short chain, change in enthalpy of internal interactions is not favorable enough for folding because of the limited number of inter-residue contacts. And a long chain is also unfavorable for a single domain."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Which of the following is false about the ‘loop’ structure in proteins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They connect helices and sheets",
            "b) They are more tolerant of mutations",
            "c) They are more flexible and can adopt multiple conformations",
            "d) They are never the components of active sites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Loops are frequently components of active sites as they are flexible in nature and as they are situated on the surface of the structure. Besides, they vary in length and 3-D configurations which give even more chances to be component of active sites."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Which of the common structural motifs are described wrongly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) β-hairpin – adjacent antiparallel strands",
            "b) Greek key – 4 adjacent antiparallel strand",
            "c) β-α-β – 2 parallel strands connected by helix",
            "d) β-α-β – 2 antiparallel strands connected by helix"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In motif, two adjacent β  parallel strands are connected by an α helix from the C-terminus of strand 1 to the N-terminus of strand. Most protein structures that contain parallel beta-sheets are built up from combinations of such β-α-βmotifs."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "Which of the following least describes Long Loop β-hairpins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are Often referred to as a ‘random coil’ conformation",
            "b) Generally they are referred to as the β-meander supersecondary structure",
            "c) Loop looks similar to the Greek Letter Ω",
            "d) Wide-range of conformations with very specific sequence preferences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: They are wide-range of conformations with no particular sequence preferences. As the name suggests ‘meander’ the conformation they possess is also quite unspecified. Addition to that Long loop β-hairpins are special case of Ω loops, that explains a lot about their structural preferences."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Motifs that can form α/β horseshoes conformation are rich with which protein residue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proline",
            "b) Arginine",
            "c) Valine",
            "d) Leucine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Specific pattern of Leucine residues, strands form a curved sheet with helices on the outside. Leucine-rich repeats (LRRs) are 20-29-residue sequence motifs present in a number of proteins with diverse functions. The primary function of these motifs appears to be to provide a versatile structural framework for the formation of protein-protein interactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "Which of the following wrongly describes protein domains?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are made up of one secondary structure",
            "b) Defined as independently foldable units",
            "c) They are stable structures as compared to motifs",
            "d) They are separated by linker regions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Protein domains are made up of two or more motifs i.e. the secondary structure to form stable and folded 3-D structures. They are conserved part of the protein sequence and can evolve, function, and exist independently of the rest of the protein chain."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "The protein structural motif domain- helix loop helix are contained by all of the following except ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scleraxis",
            "b) Neurogenins",
            "c) Transcription Factor 4",
            "d) Leucine zipper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Leucine zipper is associated with gene regulation and contains alpha helix with leucine at every 7th amino acid. While rest of them are under one of the largest families of dimerizing transcription factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the function of Short Linear Motifs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Irreversible cleavage of the peptide at the SLiM",
            "b) Reversible cleavage of the peptide at the SLiM",
            "c) Moiety addition at targeted sites on SLiM",
            "d) Structural modifications of the peptide backbone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Short Linear Motifs are short stretches of protein sequence that mediate protein-protein interaction. SLiMs can act as recognition sites of endo-peptidases resulting in the irreversible cleavage of the peptide at the SLiM."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "In the zinc finger, which residues in this sequence motif form ligands to a zinc ion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cysteine and histidine",
            "b) Cysteine and arginine",
            "c) Histidine and proline",
            "d) Histidine and arginine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the zinc finger, which is found in a widely varying family of DNA-binding proteins, cysteine and histidine residues in this sequence motif form ligands to a zinc ion whose coordination is essential to stabilize the tertiary structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "While scanning for similarities in motifs, how regular expressions’ techniques work?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It represents a sequence family by a string of characters and further compares them",
            "b) An algorithm similar to dynamic programming is used",
            "c) Dot matrix analysis is used in this type of sequence analysis",
            "d) Matrix analysis methods are used in this type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In regular expressions’ techniques Pattern matching is defined as true or false in answer or outcome. In other words, if the pattern described in regex is found in a string of letters, the answer is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "Which of the following best defines regular expressions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are made up of terms, operators and modifiers",
            "b) They describe string or set of strings to find matching patterns",
            "c) They are strictly restricted to alignment and corresponding score",
            "d) They consist of set of rules for the connotations of various amino acid residues"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Regular expressions are powerful notable algebra that describe string or set of strings to find matching patterns. Pattern matching is defined as true or false in answer or outcome. And it is true that they are made up of terms, operators and modifiers but they are terminologies further used in matching process."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "In regular expressions, which of the following pair of pattern is wrongly matched with its significance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) [ ] – Or",
            "b) { } – Not",
            "c) ( ) – Repeats",
            "d) Z – Any"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Regular Expression Symbols have their own significances in regular expressions system  means [GA] .g.e rFo ‘G or A’, {V,P} means not P or V, x(4) means (xxxx). Likewise, X denotes any character."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "In terminologies related to regular expressions which of the following is false about terms and operators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Terms are strings or substrings",
            "b) Operators combine terms and expressions",
            "c) Operators do not have precedence",
            "d) Operators have precedence like arithmetic operators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For harmonious, efficient and error-free functioning of the matching preocess, operators have precedence in order to set the priority of the operations to be carried out during the alignment."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "In regular expressions, which of the following pair of pattern is wrongly matched with its significance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ‘-’ – separator",
            "b) <  – N-terminal",
            "c) >  – C-terminal",
            "d) ‘>>’ – end"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Regular Expression Symbols have their own significances in regular expressions’ system. For e.g. x(2,3) means x-x or x-x-x. Similarly, ‘.’ means end."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Emotif uses which databases for alignment of sequences?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BLOCKS and PRINTS databases",
            "b) PROSITE",
            "c) BLOCKS",
            "d) PRINTS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Emotif is a motif database that uses multiple sequence alignments from both the BLOCKS and PRINTS databases with an alignment collection much larger than PROSITE. It identifies patterns by allowing fuzzy matching of regular expressions. Therefore, it produces fewer false negatives than PROSITE."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "While analysing motif sequences, what is the major disadvantageous feature of PROSITE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The database constructs profiles to complement some of the sequence patterns",
            "b) The functional information of these patterns is primarily based on published literature",
            "c) Some of the sequence patterns are too short to be specific",
            "d) Lack of specificity about probability and variation and relation between them"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The major pitfall with the PROSITE patterns is that some of the sequence patterns are too short to be specific. Rest of the options are advantages. The problem with these short sequence patterns is that the resulting match is very likely to be a result of random events. Overall, PROSITE has a greater than 20% error rate. Thus, either a match or non-match in PROSITE should be treated with caution."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": " Which of the following is not a characteristic of Fuzzy or approximate matches in regular expression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This method is able to include more variant forms of a motif with a conserved function",
            "b) the rule of matching is based on observations, not actual assumptions",
            "c) with the more relaxed matching, there is increase of the noise level and false positives",
            "d) the rule of matching is based on assumptions not actual observations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rule of matching is based on assumptions not actual observations in Fuzzy or approximate matches in regular expression. This provides more permissive matching by allowing more flexible matching of residues of similar biochemical properties. For example, if an original alignment only contains phenylalanine at a particular position, fuzzy matching allows other aromatic residues (including unobserved tyrosine and tryptophan) in a sequence to match with the expression."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of exact matches in regular expression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) There must be a strict match of sequence patterns",
            "b) Any variations in the query sequence from the predefined patterns are not allowed",
            "c) Provide more permissive matching by allowing more flexible matching of residues of similar biochemical properties",
            "d) Searching a motif database using this approach results in either a match or non-match"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In this type of matching, there has to be a strict match of sequence patterns. This way of searching has a good chance of missing truly relevant motifs that have slight variations, thus generating false-negative results. As new sequences of motif are being accumulated, the rigid regular expression tends to become obsolete if not updated regularly to reflect the changes."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "What does this representation mean- R.L.[EQD]?",
        "Options": [
            "a) An arginine- Amino acid- Leucine- Amino acid- Either Apartic acid, glutamic acid or glutamine",
            "b) An arginine- Leucine- Either Apartic acid, glutamic acid or glutamine",
            "c) An arginine- Leucine- Amino acid- Either Apartic acid, glutamic acid or glutamine",
            "d) An arginine- Leucine- Apartic acid and glutamic acid and glutamine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is an example of pexel motif. Here, the ‘.’ represents the ‘end’ i.e. the amino acid as mentioned in the answer and the [ ] means ‘or’ i.e. either of the mentioned residue is present in the given position. "
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of Statistical models’ methods in analyzing protein motifs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sequence information is preserved from a multiple sequence alignment and expresses it with probabilistic models",
            "b) Statistical models allow partial matches and compensate for unobserved sequence patterns using pseudo-counts",
            "c) Statistical models have stronger predictive power than the regular expression based approach, even when they are derived from a limited set of sequences",
            "d) The comparative flexibility is less in case of these methods when compared to regular expressions methods"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The major limitation of regular expressions is that this method does not take into account sequence probability information about the multiple alignment from which it is modeled making them less flexible. If a regular expression is derived from an incomplete sequence set, it has less predictive power because many more sequences with the same type of motifs are not represented. Unlike regular expressions, position-specific scoring matrices (PSSMs), profiles, and HMMs preserve the sequence information from a multiple sequence alignment and express it with probabilistic models."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "For motif scanning which of the following programs or databases is for regulated sites curated from scientific literature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ENSEMBL",
            "b) ORegAnno",
            "c) MAST",
            "d) Clover"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Clover identifies overrepresented motifs in protein sequences whereas; MAST allows users to scan different databases for matches to motifs. ENSEMBL is another online genomic sequence repository which also includes online tools for data mining as well as BLAST searches."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantageous feature or algorithm of the database PRINTS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This program breaks down a motif into even smaller non-overlapping units called ‘fingerprints’, which are represented by unweighted PSSMs",
            "b) To define a motif, at least a majority of fingerprints are required to match with a query sequence",
            "c) A query that has simultaneous high-scoring matches to a majority of fingerprints belonging to a motif is a good indication of containing the functional motif",
            "d) The difficulty to recognize short motifs when they reach the size of single fingerprints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PRINTS is a protein fingerprint database containing ungapped, manually curated alignments corresponding to the most conserved regions among related sequences. The drawbacks of PRINTS are–the difficulty to recognize short motifs when they reach the size of single fingerprints and a relatively small database, which restricts detection of many motifs."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "In which of the following multipurpose packages Gibbs sampling algorithm is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Consensus",
            "b) BEST",
            "c) AlignACE",
            "d) PhyloCon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Gibbs sampling algorithm can identify multiple motifs in a sequence in a sequence set using iterative masking procedure. It is used in AlignACE whereas BEST is a suite of four motif discovery tools integrated in a graphical user interface. Also, Consensus program finds motifs in a set of unaligned sequences and PhyloCon builds on this framework by modeling conservation across orthologous genes from multiple species."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue in case of the database BLOCKS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The alignments are automatically generated using the same data sets used for deriving the BLOSUM matrices",
            "b) The derived ungapped alignments are called ‘blocks’, which are usually longer than motifs, are subsequently converted to PSSMs",
            "c) A weighting scheme and pseudo counts are subsequently applied to the PSSMs to account for underrepresented and unobserved residues in alignments",
            "d) The functional annotation of blocks is not consistent with that for the motifs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: BLOCKS is a database that uses multiple alignments derived from the most conserved, ungapped regions of homologous protein sequences. Because blocks often encompass motifs, the functional annotation of blocks is thus consistent with that for the motifs. A query sequence can be used to align with pre-computed profiles in the database to select the highest scored matches. Because of the use of the weighting scheme, the signal-to-noise ratio is improved relative to PRINTS."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "Which of the following is false in case of the database Pfam and its algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Each motif or domain is represented by an HMM profile generated from the seed alignment of a number of conserved homologous proteins",
            "b) Since the probability scoring mechanism is more complex in HMM than in a profile-based approach the use of HMM yields further increases in sensitivity of the database matches",
            "c) Pfam-B only contains sequence families not covered in Pfam",
            "d) The functional annotation of motifs in Pfam-A is often related to that in UNIPROT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pfam is a database with protein domain alignments derived from sequences in SWISSPROT and TrEMBL. The Pfam database is composed of two parts, Pfam-A and Pfam-B. Pfam-A involves manual alignments and Pfam-B, automatic alignment in a way similar to ProDom. The functional annotation of motifs in Pfam-A is often related to that in PROSITE. Because of the automatic nature, Pfam-B has a much larger coverage but is also more error prone because some HMMs are generated from unrelated sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Which of the following is false in case of the database SMART and its algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contains HMM profiles constructed from manually refined protein domain alignments",
            "b) Alignments in the database are built based on tertiary structures whenever available or based on PSI-BLAST profiles",
            "c) Alignments are further checked but not refined by human annotators before HMM profile construction",
            "d) SMART stands for Simple Modular Architecture Research Tool"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Alignments are further checked and refined by human annotators before HMM profile construction. Protein functions are also manually curated. Thus, the database may be of better quality than Pfam with more extensive functional annotations. Compared to Pfam,\nThe SMART database contains an independent collection of HMMs, with emphasis on signaling, extracellular, and chromatin-associated motifs and domains. Sequence searching in this database produces a graphical output of domains with well-annotated information with respect to cellular localization, functional sites, super-family, and tertiary structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Which of the following is false in case of the database InterPro and its algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) InterPro is an integrated pattern database designed to unify multiple databases for protein domains and functional sites",
            "b) This database integrates information from PROSITE, Pfam, PRINTS, ProDom, and SMART databases",
            "c) Only overlapping motifs and domains in a protein sequence derived by all five databases are included",
            "d) All the motifs and domains in a protein sequence derived by all five databases are included"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The only overlapping motifs and domains in a protein sequence derived by all five databases are included in the database. The InterPro entries use a combination of regular expressions, fingerprints, profiles, and HMMs in pattern matching. However, an InterPro search does not obviate the need to search other databases because of its unique criteria of motif inclusion and thus may have lower sensitivity than exhaustive searches in individual databases. A popular feature of this database is a graphical output that summarizes motif matches and has links to more detailed information."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Which of the following is false in case of the CDART and its algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CDART is a domain search program that combines the results from RPS-BLAST, SMART, and Pfam",
            "b) The program is now an integral part of the regular BLAST search function",
            "c) CDART is a substitute for individual database searches",
            "d) It stands for Conserved Domain Architecture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: CDART is a domain search program that combines the results from various database searches. As with InterPro, CDART is not a substitute for individual database searches because it often misses certain features that can be found in SMART and Pfam."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Point out the wrong or irrelevant mathematical method in motif analysis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enumeration",
            "b) Probabilistic Optimization",
            "c) Deterministic Optimization",
            "d) Literature mining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the rest of the options are indeed valid and proven mathematical methods that contain efficient algorithms in finding motifs in protein sequences. Literature mining is not a mathematical algorithm or tool as such to be used in identifying motifs. But it is definitely a part of research when it comes to find a function of various protein sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements about COG is incorrect regarding its features?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Currently, there are 4,873 clusters in the COG databases derived from unicellular organisms",
            "b) It is constructed by comparing protein sequences encoded in forty-three completely sequenced genomes, which are mainly from prokaryotes, representing thirty major phylogenetic lineages",
            "c) The interface for sequence searching in the COG database is the COGnitor program, which is based on gapped BLAST",
            "d) It is a protein family database based on structural classification"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: COG which stands for Cluster of Orthologous Groups, is a protein family database based on phylogenetic classification. Because orthologous proteins shared by three or more lineages are considered to have descended through a vertical evolutionary scenario, if the function of one of the members is known, functionality of other members can be assigned."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements about InterPro is incorrect regarding its features?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protein relatedness is defined by the P-values from the BLAST alignments",
            "b) The most closely related sequences are grouped into the lowest level clusters",
            "c) More distant protein groups are merged into higher levels of clusters",
            "d) The outcome of this cluster merging is a tree-like structure of functional categories"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: InterPro is a database of clusters of homologous proteins similar to COG. Protein relatedness is defined by the E-values from the BLAST alignments. The database further provides gene ontology information for protein cluster at each level as well as keywords from InterPro domains for functional prediction."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Pfam is available at four locations around the world. Which of the following is not one of them?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UK",
            "b) Sweden",
            "c) US",
            "d) Japan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pfam is available at four locations around the world each providing a core set of functionality for accessing each family. They are US, UK, Sweden and France. Documentation on the content and use of Pfam is available via the web."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a member database of InterPro?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SCOP",
            "b) HAMAP",
            "c) PANTHER",
            "d) Pfam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The signatures from InterPro come from 11 member databases viz. CATH-Gene3D, HAMAP, PANTHER, Pfam, PIRSF, PRINTS, ProDom, PROSITE, SMART, SUPERFAMILY, TIGRFAMs."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements about SCOP is incorrect regarding its features?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proteins with the same shapes but having little sequence or functional similarity are placed in different super families, and are assumed to have only a very distant common ancestor",
            "b) Proteins having the same shape and some similarity of sequence and/or function are placed in ‘families’, and are assumed to have a closer common ancestor",
            "c) SCOP was created in 1994 in the Centre of Protein Engineering and the University College London",
            "d) It aims to determine the evolutionary relationship between proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: SCOP, Structural Classification of Proteins, was created in 1994 in the Centre of Protein Engineering and the Laboratory of Molecular Biology. It was maintained by Alexey G. Murzin and his colleagues in the Centre for Protein Engineering until its closure in 2010 and subsequently at the Laboratory of Molecular Biology in Cambridge, England."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "What is the source of protein structures in SCOP and CATH?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uniprot",
            "b) Protein Data Bank",
            "c) Ensemble",
            "d) InterPro"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The source of protein structures in SCOP is PDB (Protein Data Bank). PDB is a secondary database which means it has protein structures derived from primary databases that have the protein sequences. UNIPROT is a primary database."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements about SUPERFAMILY database is incorrect regarding its features?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sequences can be submitted raw or FASTA format",
            "b) Sequences must be submitted in FASTA format only",
            "c) It searches the database using a superfamily, family, or species name plus a sequence, SCOP, PDB or HMM ID’s",
            "d) It has generated GO annotations for evolutionarily closed domains and distant domains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: SUPERFAMILY is a database of structural and functional annotation for all proteins and genomes. It classifies amino acid sequences into known structural domains, especially into SCOP super families. Sequences can be amino acids, a fixed frame nucleotide sequence, or all frames of a submitted nucleotide sequence. Up to 1000 sequences can be run at a time."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements about PRINTS and ProDom databases is incorrect regarding its features?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PRINTS is a compendium of protein fingerprints",
            "b) Usually the motifs do not overlap, but are separated along a sequence, though they may be contiguous in 3D-space",
            "c) Current versions of ProDom are built using a novel procedure based on recursive BLAST searches",
            "d) ProDom domain database consists of an automatic compilation of homologous domains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Current versions of ProDom are built using a novel procedure based on recursive PSI-BLAST searches and not just BLAST searches. And PRINTS is indeed a compendium of protein fingerprints. A fingerprint is a group of conserved motifs used to characterise a protein family; its diagnostic power is refined by iterative scanning of UniProt."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements about CATH-Gene3D and HAMAP databases is incorrect regarding its features?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CATH-Gene3D describes protein families and domain architectures in complete genomes",
            "b) In CATH-Gene3D the functional annotation is provided to proteins from single resource",
            "c) HAMAP profiles are manually created by expert curators they identify proteins that are part of well-conserved bacterial, archaeal and plastid-encoded proteins families or subfamilies.",
            "d) HAMAP stands for High-quality Automated and Manual Annotation of microbial Proteomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In CATH-Gene3D Protein families are formed using a Markov clustering algorithm, followed by multi-linkage clustering according to sequence identity. Mapping of predicted structure and sequence domains is undertaken using hidden Markov models libraries representing CATH and Pfam domains. Functional annotation is provided to proteins from multiple resources. Functional prediction and analysis of domain architectures is available at the website."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements about PANTHER and TIGRFAMs databases is incorrect regarding its features?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TIGRFAMs provides a tool for identifying functionally related proteins based on sequence homology",
            "b) TIGRFAMs is a collection of protein families, featuring curated multiple sequence alignments, hidden Markov models (HMMs) and annotation",
            "c) Hidden Markov models (HMMs) are not used in PANTHER",
            "d) PANTHER is a large collection of protein families that have been subdivided into functionally related subfamilies, using human expertise"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In PANTHER the subfamilies model the divergence of specific functions within protein families, allowing more accurate association with function (human-curated molecular function and biological process classifications and pathway diagrams), as well as inference of amino acids important for functional specificity. Hidden Markov models (HMMs) are built for each family and subfamily for classifying additional protein sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "When did Needleman-Wunsch first describe the algorithm for global alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1899",
            "b) 1970",
            "c) 1930",
            "d) 1950"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Needleman and Wunsch were among the first to describe dynamic programming algorithm for global sequence. In global sequence alignment, an attempt to align the entirety of two different sequences is made, up to and including the ends of sequences. "
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not describe dynamic programming?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The approach compares every pair of characters in the two sequences and generates an alignment, which is the best or optimal",
            "b) Global alignment algorithm is based on this method",
            "c) Local alignment algorithm is based on this method",
            "d) The method can be useful in aligning protein sequences to protein sequences only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The method can be useful in aligning nucleotide to protein sequences as well. These programs first perform pair-wise alignment on each pair of sequences. Then, they perform local re-arrangements on these results, in order to optimize overlaps between multiple sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of Needleman-Wunsch algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) New algorithmic improvements as well as increasing computer capacity make it possible to align a query sequence against a large DB in a few minutes",
            "b) Similar sequence region is of same order and orientation",
            "c) This does not help in determining evolutionary relationship",
            "d) If you have 2 genes that are already understood as closely related, then this type of algorithm can be used to understand them in further details"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Needleman-Wunsch algorithm is used when 2 genes that are already understood as closely related and can be used to understand them in further details. This is quite helpful in finding orthologs, paralogs and homologs in evolutionary studies."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a disadvantage of Needleman-Wunsch algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This method is comparatively slow",
            "b) There is a need of intensive memory",
            "c) This cannot be applied on genome sized sequences",
            "d) This method can be applied to even large sized sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: This method cannot be applied on genome sized sequences. But this is indeed useful in determining similarities and evolutionary relationships."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not describe global alignment algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In initialization step, the first row and first column are subject to gap penalty",
            "b) Score can be negative",
            "c) In trace back step, beginning is with the cell at the lower right of the matrix and it ends at top left cell",
            "d) First row and first column are set to zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Initialization and scoring system of the Smith–Waterman algorithm and Needleman-Wunsch algorithm is quite different. In global alignment first row and first column are subject to gap penalty and are not set to 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not describe PAM matrices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) These matrices are used in optimal alignment scoring",
            "b) It stands for Point Altered Mutations",
            "c) It stands for Point Accepted Mutations",
            "d) It was first developed by Margaret Dayhoff"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PAM stands for Point Accepted Mutations. PAM matrices are calculated by observing the differences in closely related proteins. One PAM unit (PAM1) specifies one accepted point mutation per 100 amino acid residues, i.e. 1% change and 99% remains as such."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the scoring system used in dynamic programming?",
        "Options": [
            "a) If the residues are same in both the sequences the match score is assumed as +5 which is added to the diagonally positioned cell of the current cell",
            "b) If the residues are not same, the mismatch score is assumed as -3",
            "c) If the residues are not same, the mismatch score is assumed as 3",
            "d) The score should be added to the diagonally positioned cell of the current cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the residues are not same, the mismatch score is assumed as -3 and it has to be negative. However, these scores are not unique, they can be user defined also, but the mismatch and gap penalty should be the negative values."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not describe global alignment algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Score can be negative in this method",
            "b) It is based on dynamic programming technique",
            "c) For two sequences of length m and n, the matrix to be defined should be of dimensions m+1 and n+1",
            "d) For two sequences of length m and n, the matrix to be defined should be of dimensions m and n"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For two sequences of length m and n, the matrix to be defined should be of dimensions m+1 and n+1so that there is margin for addition of the score along the diagonal. Also, corresponding score is further calculated at the end cumulatively."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not describe global alignment algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It attempts to align every residue in every sequence",
            "b) It is most useful when the aligning sequences are similar and of roughly the same size",
            "c) It is useful when the aligning sequences are dissimilar",
            "d) It can use Needleman-Wunsch algorithm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Performing global alignment is most useful when the aligning sequences are similar and of roughly the same size. This is most useful to find the similarities among the organisms that are roughly connected on the timeline."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong in case of substitution matrices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They determine likelihood of homology between two sequences",
            "b) They use system where substitutions that are more likely should get a higher score",
            "c) They use system where substitutions that are less likely should get a lower score",
            "d) BLOSUM-X type uses logarithmic identity to find similarity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: BLOSUM-X type identifies sequences that are X% similar to the query sequence i. e. score 54 corresponds to 54% similarity hence reducing the complexity of the output and giving the similarity in percentage. Also, these matrices are popular in bioinformatics due to their speed and accuracy."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "When did Smith–Waterman first describe the algorithm for local alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1950",
            "b) 1970",
            "c) 1981",
            "d) 1925"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The algorithm was first proposed by Temple F. Smith and Michael S. Waterman in 1981. The Smith–Waterman algorithm performs local sequence alignment; that is, for determining similar regions between two strings of nucleic acid sequences or protein sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not describe local alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A local alignment aligns a substring of the query sequence to a substring of the target sequence",
            "b) A local alignment is defined by maximizing the alignment score, so that deleting a column from either end would reduce the score, and adding further columns at either end would also reduce the score",
            "c) Local alignments have terminal gaps",
            "d) The substrings to be examined may be all of one or both sequences; if all of both are included then the local alignment is also global"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Local alignments never have terminal gaps, because a higher score could be obtained by deleting the gaps (which always have negative scores, i.e. penalties). In case of global alignment there are terminal gaps while analyzing."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not describe local alignment algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Score can be negative",
            "b) Negative score is set to 0",
            "c) First row and first column are set to 0 in initialization step",
            "d) In traceback step, beginning is with the highest score, it ends when 0 is encountered"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Score can be negative. When any element has a score lower than zero, it means that the sequences up to this position have no similarities; this element will then be set to zero to eliminate influence from previous alignment. In this way, calculation can continue to find alignment in any position afterward."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Local alignments are more used when _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) There are totally similar and equal length sequences",
            "b) Dissimilar sequences are suspected to contain regions of similarity",
            "c) Similar sequence motif with larger sequence context",
            "d) Partially similar, different length and conserved region containing sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given description is suitable for global alignment. It attempts to align maximum of the entire sequence unlike local alignment where the partially similar sequences are analyzed."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not describe BLOSUM matrices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for BLOcks SUbstitution Matrix",
            "b) It was developed by Henikoff and Henikoff",
            "c) The year it was developed was 1992",
            "d) These matrices are logarithmic identity values"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These matrices are actual percentage identity values. Or simply, they depend on similarity. Blosum 62 means there is 62 % similarity."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the gap penalty used in dynamic programming?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gap penalty is subtracted for each gap that has been introduced",
            "b) Gap penalty is added for each gap that has been introduced",
            "c) The gap score defines a penalty given to alignment when we have insertion or deletion",
            "d) Gap open and gap extension has been introduced when there are continuous gaps (five or more)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dynamic programming algorithms use gap penalties to maximize the biological meaning. The open penalty is always applied at the start of the gap, and then the other gaps following it is given with a gap extension penalty which will be less compared to the open penalty. Typical values are –12 for gap opening, and –4 for gap extension."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "Among the following which one is not the approach to the local alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smith-Waterman algorithm",
            "b) K-tuple method",
            "c) Words method",
            "d) Needleman-Wunsch algorithm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Local alignment can be distinguished on two broad approaches, Smith-Waterman algorithm and word methods, also known as k-tuple methods and they are implemented in the well-known families of programs FASTA and BLAST."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not describe k-tuple methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) k-tuple methods are best known for their implementation in the database search tools FASTA and the BLAST family",
            "b) They are also known as words methods",
            "c) They are basically heuristic methods to find local alignment",
            "d) They are useful in small scale databases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: k-tuple or word methods are especially useful in large-scale database searches where a large proportion of stored sequences will have essentially no significant match with the query sequence. They are heuristic methods that are not guaranteed to find an optimal alignment solution but are significantly more efficient than Smith-Waterman algorithm."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not describe BLAST?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for Basic Local Alignment Search Tool",
            "b) It uses word matching like FASTA",
            "c) It is one of the tools of the NCBI",
            "d) Even if no words are similar, there is an alignment to be considered"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If no words are similar, there is no alignment i. e. it will not find matches for very short sequences. But it is considerably accurate as compared to other tools and hence is quite popular."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding BLAST and FASTA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FASTA is faster than BLAST",
            "b) FASTA is the most accurate",
            "c) BLAST has limited choices of databases",
            "d) FASTA is more sensitive for DNA-DNA comparisons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: BLAST is faster than FASTA and most other tools. The speed and relatively good accuracy of BLAST is the key why the tool is the most popular bioinformatics search tool. "
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "For what type of sequences Gibbs sampling is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Closely related sequences",
            "b) Distinctly related sequences",
            "c) Distinctly related sequences that share common motifs",
            "d) Closely related sequences that share common motifs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Often, distantly related sequences that share common motifs cannot be readily aligned. For example, the sequences for the helix-turn-helix motif in transcription factors can be subtly different enough that traditional multiple sequence alignment approaches fail to generate a satisfactory answer. For detecting such subtle motifs, more sophisticated algorithms such as expectation maximization (EM) and Gibbs sampling are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Expectation Maximization (EM) method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is used to find hidden motifs",
            "b) The method works by first making a random or guessed alignment of the sequences to generate a trial PSSM",
            "c) The trial PSSM is used to compare with each sequence individually",
            "d) The log odds scores of the PSSM are modified at the end of the process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The log odds scores of the PSSM are modified in each iteration to maximize the alignment of the matrix to each sequence. During the iterations, the sequence pattern for the conserved motifs is gradually “recruited” to the PSSM."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about Expectation Maximization (EM) method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The log odds scores of the PSSM are modified at the end of the process",
            "b) The procedure stops prematurely if the scores reach convergence",
            "c) The final result is not sensitive to the initial alignment",
            "d) Local optimum is an advantage of EM method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The final result is sensitive to the initial alignment. The Local optimum is actually a drawback of EM method. It is same as the fact that the procedure stops prematurely if the scores reach convergence."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "MEME stands for _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multiple Expectation Maximization for Motif Elicitation",
            "b) Multiple Expectation Maximization for Motif Extraction",
            "c) Mega Expectation Maximization for Motif Elicitation",
            "d) Micro Expectation Maximization for Motif Extraction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Multiple Expectation Maximization for Motif Elicitation is a web-based program that uses the EM algorithm to find motifs either for DNA or protein sequences. It uses amodified EM algorithm to avoid the local minimum problem."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "In the web-based program MEME, the computation is a _____ step procedure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) one",
            "b) two",
            "c) three",
            "d) four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In constructing a probability matrix, it allows multiple starting alignments and does not assume that there are motifs in every sequence. Also, the computation is a two-step procedure that includes generation of sequence motif and finding highest score."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Gibbs is a web-based program that uses the Gibbs sampling approach to look for _____ gap-free segments for either DNA or protein sequences.",
        "Options": [
            "a) short, partially conserved",
            "b) long, partially conserved",
            "c) long, conserved",
            "d) short, not conserved"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gibbs sampling approach to look for short, partially conserved gap-free segments for either DNA or protein sequences. To ensure accuracy, more than twenty sequences of the exact same length should be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "A multiple sequence alignment or a motif is often represented by a graphic representation called a ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) logo",
            "b) motto",
            "c) algorithm",
            "d) algo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a logo, each position consists of stacked letters representing the residues appearing in a particular column of a multiple alignment. This graphic representation called a logo."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "The overall height of a logo position reflects how conserved the position is, and the _____ of each letter in a position reflects the _______ of the residue in the alignment.",
        "Options": [
            "a) height, relative frequency",
            "b) width, relative frequency",
            "c) height, amplitude",
            "d) width, amplitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The height expresses the data about the extent of the conservation of the position and each letter shows the frequency of that particular residue. The amplitude, here in this case, is irrelevant option."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Conserved positions have _____ residues and bigger symbols.",
        "Options": [
            "a) fewer",
            "b) more",
            "c) maximum",
            "d) minimum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The options maximum and minimum are comparatively obsolete as there involves the studies of alignment. Conserved positions have fewer residues and bigger symbols; whereas less conserved positions have a more heterogeneous mixture of smaller symbols stacked together. In general, a sequence logo provides a clearer description of a consensus sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "_______ is an interactive program for generating sequence logos.",
        "Options": [
            "a) EMBOSS",
            "b) WebLogo",
            "c) LOGOLY",
            "d) BLAST"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In WebLogo, a user needs to enter the sequence alignment in FASTA format to allow the program to compute the logos. A graphic file is returned to the user as a result. "
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a software for dot plot analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SIMMI",
            "b) DOTLET",
            "c) DOTMATCHER",
            "d) LALIGN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the purpose of dot plot interpretation there are various softwares currently present. Among these SIM is used for these kinds of alignments through dot-plot method that is wrongly abbreviated."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "The softwares for dot plot analysis perform several tasks. Which one of them is not performed by them?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gap open penalty",
            "b) Gap extend penalty",
            "c) Expectation threshold",
            "d) Change or mutate residues"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The gap penalties mentioned above are for the determination of score of the aligning sequences. The change in residue barely takes place as there are number of other softwares for that purpose and also the main objective is to find the score of the alignment."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "For palindromic sequences, what is the structure of the dot plot?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 intersecting diagonal lines at the midpoint",
            "b) One diagonal",
            "c) Two parallel diagonals",
            "d) No diagonal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For perfectly aligned sequences there is a diagonal formation of dot plot. For palindromic sequences i. e. for sequences that are symmetrical from the midpoint of the sequence, there exist 2 intersecting diagonals on the plot."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "For significantly aligning sequences what is the resulting structure on the plot?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intercrossing lines",
            "b) Crosses everywhere",
            "c) Vertical lines",
            "d) A diagonal and lines parallel to diagonal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If there is alignment of sequences there is a significantly bold diagonal visible on the plot. And if the is a bit imperfect, the diagonal is shattered too to an extent and forms small parallel lines to it."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "When was this method, first described?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1959",
            "b) 1966",
            "c) 1970",
            "d) 1982"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This method was first described in 1970. Briefly, this method involves constructing a matrix with one of the sequences to be compared running horizontally across the bottom, and the other running vertically along the left-hand side."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Who were the inventors of this method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smith-Waterman",
            "b) Margaret Preston",
            "c) Gibbs and McIntyre",
            "d) Needleman-Wunsch"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first computer aided sequence comparison is called “dot-matrix analysis” or simply dot-plot. The first published account of this method is by Gibbs and McIntyre (1970 The diagram, a method for comparing sequences. Eur. J. Biochem 16: 1-11)."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for EMBOSS Dottup?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Allows you to specify threshold",
            "b) Doesn’t allow you to specify threshold",
            "c) Doesn’t allow you to specify window size",
            "d) If all cells in the window are identity, it colors in some specific cells in the window"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The EMBOSS Dottup doesn’t allow you to specify threshold but allows you to specify window size. Also, if all cells in the window are identity, it colors in all the cells in the window."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "Vertical frame shifts show ______ while the horizontal ones show _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) insertion, insertion",
            "b) insertion, deletion",
            "c) deletion, deletion",
            "d) deletion, insertion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Those isolated dots represent random matches. The dots on the diagonal represent the perfect alignment and the dots with vertical and horizontal shifts show insertions and deletions."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "The matrices PAM250 and BLOSUM62 contain _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) positive and negative values",
            "b) positive values only",
            "c) negative values only",
            "d) neither positive nor negative values, just the percentage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Once those parameters have been set, the resulting alignment for two sequences should always be the same. Hence, the use of the dynamic programming method requires a scoring system for the comparison of symbol pairs (nucleotides for DNA sequences and amino acids for protein sequences), and a scheme for insertion/deletion (GAP) penalties. "
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "The higher is the score in the alignment _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the more significant is the alignment",
            "b) or the less it resembles alignments in related proteins",
            "c) the less significant is the alignment",
            "d) the less it aligns with the related protein sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: After the derivation, the outputs of the dynamic programming are the ratios are called odd scores. The ratios are transformed to logarithms of odds scores, called log odds scores, so that scores of sequential pairs may be added to reflect the overall odds of a real to chance alignment of an alignment. This happens in Dayhoff PAM250 and BLOSUM62."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "Gaps are added to the alignment because it ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases the matching of identical amino acids at subsequent portions in the alignment",
            "b) increases the matching of or dissimilar amino acids at subsequent portions in the alignment",
            "c) reduces the overall score",
            "d) enhances the area of the sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: These matrices contain positive and negative values, reflecting the likelihood of each amino acid substitution in related proteins. Using these tables, an alignment of a sequential set of amino acid pairs with no gaps receives an overall score that is the sum of the positive and negative log odds scores for each individual amino acid pair in the alignment."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a description of dynamic programming algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A method of sequence alignment",
            "b) A method that can take gaps into account",
            "c) A method that requires a manageable number of comparisons",
            "d) This method doesn’t provide an optimal (highest scoring) alignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the scoring system, the higher this score, the more significant is the alignment, or the more it resembles alignments in related proteins. Also, the score given for gaps in aligned sequences is negative, because such misaligned regions should be uncommon in sequences of related proteins. Such a score will reduce the score obtained from an adjacent, matching region upstream in the sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a site on internet for alignment of sequence pairs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BLASTX",
            "b) BLASTN",
            "c) SIM",
            "d) BCM Search Launcher"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the alignment process, gaps are added to the alignment in a manner that increases the matching of identical or similar amino acids at subsequent portions in the alignment. Ideally, when two similar protein sequences are aligned, the alignment should have long regions of identical or related amino acid pairs and very few gaps. As the sequences become more distant, more mismatched amino acid pairs and gaps should appear."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding dynamic programming algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The method compares every pair of characters in the two sequences and generates an alignment",
            "b) The output alignment will include matched and mismatched characters and gaps in the two sequences that are positioned so that the number of matches between identical or related characters is the maximum possible",
            "c) The dynamic programming algorithm provides a reliable computational method for aligning DNA and protein sequences",
            "d) This doesn’t allow making evolutionary predictions on the basis of sequence alignments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The method of sequence alignment by dynamic programming provides an optimal (highest scoring) alignment as an output. The quality of the alignment between two sequences is calculated using a scoring system that favors the matching of related or identical amino acids and penalizes for poorly matched amino acids and gaps."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "Which of the following doesn’t describe PAM matrices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This family of matrices lists the likelihood of change from one amino acid to another in homologous protein sequences during evolution",
            "b) There is presently no other type of scoring matrix that is based on such sound evolutionary principles as are these matrices",
            "c) Even though they were originally based on a relatively small data set, the PAM matrices remain a useful tool for sequence alignment",
            "d) It stands for Percent Altered Mutation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The odds scores are converted to log odds scores so that the values for amino acid pairs in an alignment may be summed to obtain the log odds score of the alignment. In this case, the logarithms are calculated to the base 2 and multiplied by 2 to give values designated as half-bits (a bit is the unit of an odds score that has been converted to a logarithm to the base 2). The value of 4 indicates that the 4 amino acid alignment is 2(4/2) = 4 four-fold more likely than expected by chance."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about the modification of PAM matrices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) At one time, the PAM250 scoring matrix was modified in an attempt to improve the alignment obtained",
            "b) All scores for matching a particular amino acid were normalized to the same mean and standard deviation, and all amino acid identities were given the same score to provide an equal contribution for each amino acid in a sequence alignment",
            "c) This took place in 1976",
            "d) These modifications were included as the default matrices for the GCG sequence alignment programs in versions 8 and earlier and are optional in later versions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PAM stands for Percent Accepted Mutation. In this, each matrix gives the changes expected for a given period of evolutionary time, evidenced by decreased sequence similarity as genes encoding the same protein diverge with increased evolutionary time."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true regarding the assumptions in the method of constructing the Dayhoff scoring matrix?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it is assumed that each amino acid position is equally mutable",
            "b) it is assumed that each amino acid position is not equally mutable",
            "c) it is assumed that each amino acid position is not mutable at all",
            "d) sites do not vary in their degree of mutability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The BLOSUM matrices are based on scoring substitutions found over a range of evolutionary periods and reveal that substitutions are not always as predicted by the PAM model. The purpose of assumption in this evolutionary model is to make predictions."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "A gap opening penalty for any gap (g) and a gap extension penalty for each element in the gap (r) are most often used, to give a total gap score wx, according to the equation ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) wx – rx = -g",
            "b) wx = g – rx",
            "c) wx = g + rx",
            "d) wx + g + rx = 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This event took place in 1986 by Gribskov and Burgess. However, they are not recommended because they will not give an optimal alignment that is in accordance with the evolutionary model."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "In the GCG and FASTA program suites, the scoring matrix itself is formatted in a way that includes default ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) gap additions",
            "b) alignment scores",
            "c) score penalties",
            "d) gap penalties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Dayhoff Model of Protein Evolution as Used in PAM Matrices is a Markov process. In Analysis of the Dayhoff Model, each amino acid site in a protein can change at any time to any of the other 20 amino acids with probabilities given by the PAM table, and the changes that occur at each site are independent of the amino acids found at other sites in the protein and depend only on the current amino acid at the site."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "On analysis of the alignment scores of random sequences will reveal that the scores follow a different distribution than the normal distribution called the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gumbel equal value distribution",
            "b) Gumbel extreme value distribution",
            "c) Gumbel end value distribution",
            "d) Gumbel distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Originally, the significance of sequence alignment scores was evaluated on the basis of the assumption that alignment scores followed a normal statistical distribution. If sequences are randomly generated in a computer by a Monte Carlo or sequence shuffling method, as in generating a sequence by picking marbles representing four bases or 20 amino acids out of a bag, the distribution may look normal at first glance. But on further analysis the above result was obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "The statistical analysis of alignment scores is much better understood for ________ than for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) global alignments, local alignments",
            "b) local alignments, global alignments",
            "c) global alignments, any other alignment method",
            "d) Needleman-Wunsch alignment, Smith-Waterman alignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Smith-Waterman alignment algorithm and the scoring system used to produce a local alignment are designed to reveal regions of closely matching sequence with a positive alignment score. In random or unrelated sequence alignments, these regions are rarely found. Hence, their presence in real sequence alignments is significant, and the probability of their occurring by chance alignment of unrelated sequences can be readily calculated."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "When random or unrelated sequences are compared using a global alignment method, they can have ____________ reflecting the tendency of the global algorithm to match as many characters as possible.",
        "Options": [
            "a) very low scores",
            "b) very high scores",
            "c) moderate scores",
            "d) low scores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The significance of the scores of global alignments, is more difficult to determine. Using the Needleman-Wunsch algorithm and a suitable scoring system, there are many ways to produce a global alignment between any pair of sequences, and the scores of many different alignments may be quite similar hence the scores obtained might be unusually high."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "Which of the following are not related to Needleman-Wunsch alignment algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Global alignment programs use this algorithm",
            "b) The output is a positive number",
            "c) Small changes in the scoring system can produce a different alignment",
            "d) Changes in the scoring system can produce the same alignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In general, global alignment programs use the Needleman-Wunsch alignment algorithm and a scoring system that scores the average match of an aligned nucleotide or amino acid pair as a positive number. Hence, the score of the alignment of random or unrelated sequences grows proportionally to the length of the sequences. In addition, there are many possible different global alignments depending on the scoring system chosen, and small changes in the scoring system can produce a different alignment. "
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "Waterman, in1989, provided a set of means and standard deviations of global alignment scores between random DNA sequences, using mismatch and gap penalties that produce a linear increase in score with _______ a distinguishing feature of global alignments.",
        "Options": [
            "a) alignment score",
            "b) sequence score",
            "c) sequence length",
            "d) scoring system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the algorithm provided by Waterman, the score of the alignment of random or unrelated sequences grows proportionally to the length of the sequences. However, these values are of limited use because they are based on a simple gap scoring system."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "Who suggested that the global alignment scores between unrelated protein sequences followed the extreme value distribution, similar to local alignment scores? And when?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abagyan and Batalov, in 1981",
            "b) Chvátal and Lipman, in 1984",
            "c) Abagyan and Batalov, in 1997",
            "d) Chvátal and Sankoff, in 1995"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Abagyan and Batalov, in 1997, suggested the above observation. However, since the scoring system that they used favored local alignments, these alignments they produced may not be global but local. Unfortunately, there is no equivalent theory on which to base an analysis of global alignment scores as there is for local alignment scores."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "_______ analyzed the distribution of scores among 100 vertebrate nucleic acid sequences and compared these scores with randomized sequences prepared in different ways.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lipman, in 1984",
            "b) Batalov, in 1964",
            "c) Waterman, in 1987",
            "d) Lipman, in 1967"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the randomized sequences were prepared by shuffling the sequence to conserve base composition, as was done by Dayhoff and others, the standard deviation was approximately one-third less than the distribution of scores of the natural sequences. Thus, natural sequences are more variable than randomized ones, and using such randomized sequences for a significance test may lead to an overestimation of the significance."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "If the random sequences were prepared in a way that maintained the local base composition by producing them from overlapping fragments of sequence, the distribution of scores has a _______ standard deviation that is closer to the distribution of the natural sequences.",
        "Options": [
            "a) lowest",
            "b) higher",
            "c) lower",
            "d) moderate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The conclusion from the above is that the presence of conserved local patterns can influence the score in statistical tests such that an alignment can appear to be more significant than it actually is. Although this study was done using the Smith-Waterman algorithm with nucleic acids, the same cautionary note applies for other types of alignments."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Dayhoff, 1978- 1983, devised a second method for testing the relatedness of two protein sequences that can accommodate some local variation. Where this method is useful?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For finding repeated regions within a sequence",
            "b) For finding similar regions that are in a different order in two sequences",
            "c) For finding small conserved region such as an active site",
            "d) For finding huge regions within sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the new similarity scores are significantly smaller than the real alignment score, the alignment is considered significant. This analysis is only useful for providing a rough approximation of the significance of an alignment score and can easily be misleading."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "By whom and when were the Bayesian methods applied first?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smith-Waterman, 1981",
            "b) Agarwal and States, 1996",
            "c) Smith-Waterman, 1996",
            "d) Agarwal and States, 1981"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Agarwal and States, in1996, have applied Bayesian methods to provide the best estimate of the evolutionary distance between two DNA sequences. For example, sequences of the same length that have a certain level of mismatches."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "If the purpose is to calculate the probability of one event AND a second event, the odds scores for the events are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) added",
            "b) multiplied",
            "c) multiplied and added",
            "d) subtracted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sequences of this type originated from gene duplication events in the yeast and Caenorhabditis elegans genomes. When there are multiple mismatches between such repeated sequences, it is difficult to determine the most likely length of the repeats. Here the methods can be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "In a type of probability, analysis is to calculate the odds score for one event OR a second event, or of a series of events. In this case, the odds scores are _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) multiplied",
            "b) subtracted",
            "c) added and multiplied",
            "d) added"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An example is the calculation of the odds of an alignment of two sequences from the alignment scores for each of the matched pairs of bases or amino acids in the alignment. The odds scores for the pairs are multiplied. Usually, the log odds score for the first pair is added to that for the second, etc., until the scores for every pair have been added."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "A length and distance that gives the highest overall probability may then be determined. Such alignments are initially found using ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) a particular scoring matrix only",
            "b) an alignment algorithm only",
            "c) an alignment algorithm and a particular scoring matrix",
            "d) dot method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An example is the calculation of the odds score for a given sequence alignment using a series of alternative PAM scoring matrices. The alignment scores are calculated in log odds units and then converted into odds scores. "
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "Which of the following feature of Bayesian methods is the disadvantage of it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A length and distance that gives the highest overall probability may be determined",
            "b) They are used to calculate evolutionary distance",
            "c) Computationally Bayesian methods are better",
            "d) A specific mutational model is required"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The assumption mentioned above (the molecular clock hypothesis) is made to reduce the complications. Such problems may be solved by scoring different portions of a sequence with a different scoring matrix, and then using the above Bayesian methods to calculate the best evolutionary distance."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "Zhu (1998) have devised a computer program called the Bayes block aligner which in effect slides ____ sequences along each other to find the ______ ungapped regions or blocks.",
        "Options": [
            "a) two, least scoring",
            "b) two, highest scoring",
            "c) multiple, highest scoring",
            "d) multiple, least scoring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In genomes, the presence of repeats may be revealed by long regions of matched sequence positions dispersed among regions of sequence positions that do not match. However, as the frequency of mismatches is increased, it becomes difficult to determine the extent of the repeated region."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Unlike the commonly used methods for aligning a pair of sequences, the Bayesian method _______ using a particular scoring matrix or designated gap penalties.",
        "Options": [
            "a) does not depend on",
            "b) depends on",
            "c) is based on",
            "d) involves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Analysis of the yeast and C. elegans genomes for such repeats has underscored the importance of using a range of DNA scoring matrices such as PAM1 to\nPAM120 if most repeats are to be found. The application of the above Bayesian analysis allows a determination of the probability distributions as a function of both length of the repeated region and evolutionary distance."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding pair wise sequence alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The most fundamental process in this type of comparison is sequence alignment",
            "b) It is an important first step toward structural and functional analysis of newly determined sequences",
            "c) This is the process by which sequences are compared by searching for common character patterns and establishing residue-residue correspondence among related sequences",
            "d) It is the process of aligning multiple sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pair wise sequence alignment is the process of aligning two sequences and is the basis of database similarity searching and multiple sequence alignment. As new biological sequences are being generated at exponential rates, sequence comparison is becoming increasingly important to draw functional and evolutionary inference of a new protein with proteins already existing in the database."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about evolution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The macromolecules can be considered molecular fossils that encode the history of millions of years of evolution",
            "b) The building blocks of these biological macromolecules, nucleotide bases, and amino acids form linear sequences that determine the primary structure of the molecules",
            "c) DNA and proteins are products of evolution",
            "d) The molecular sequences barely undergo changes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: During this time period, the molecular sequences undergo random changes, some of which are selected during the process of evolution. As the selected sequences gradually accumulate mutations and diverge over time, traces of evolution may still remain in certain portions of the sequences to allow identification of the common ancestry."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "If the two sequences share significant similarity, it is extremely ______ that the extensive similarity between the two sequences has been acquired randomly, meaning that the two sequences must have derived from a common evolutionary origin.",
        "Options": [
            "a) unlikely",
            "b) possible",
            "c) likely",
            "d) relevant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The residues that perform key functional and structural roles tend to be preserved by natural selection. For example, active site residues of an enzyme family tend to be conserved because they are responsible for catalytic functions. Therefore, by comparing sequences through alignment, patterns of conservation and variation can be identified."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding sequence homology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two sequences can homologous relationship even if have do not have common origin",
            "b) It is an important concept in sequence analysis",
            "c) When two sequences are descended from a common evolutionary origin, they are said to have a homologous relationship",
            "d) When two sequences are descended from a common evolutionary origin, they are said to share homology"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The degree of sequence conservation in the alignment reveals evolutionary relatedness of different sequences, whereas the variation between sequences reflects the changes that have occurred during evolution in the form of substitutions, insertions, and deletions. Identifying the evolutionary relationships between sequences helps to characterize the function of unknown sequences. When a sequence alignment reveals significant similarity among a group of sequences, they can be considered as belonging to the same family."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Sequence similarity can be quantified using ________ homology is a ______ statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) percentages, quantitative",
            "b) percentages, qualitative",
            "c) ratios, qualitative",
            "d) ratios, quantitative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sequence alignment provides inference for the relatedness of two sequences under study. Regions that are aligned but not identical represent residue substitutions; regions which residues from one sequence correspond to nothing in the other represent insertions or deletions that have taken place on one of the sequences during evolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "In a dot matrix, two sequences to be compared are written in the _____________ of the matrix.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal and vertical axes",
            "b) 2 parallel horizontal axes",
            "c) 2 parallel vertical axes",
            "d) horizontal axis (one preceding another)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The goal of pair wise sequence alignment is to find the best pairing and to achieve this goal; one sequence needs to be shifted relative to the other to find the position where maximum matches are found. There are two different alignment strategies that are often used: global alignment and local alignment. "
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "When the two sequences have substantial regions of similarity, many dots line up to form contiguous _______ lines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) crossings on",
            "b) horizontal",
            "c) diagonal",
            "d) vertical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The two sequences to be aligned can be of different lengths. This approach is more appropriate for aligning divergent biological sequences containing only modules that are similar, which are referred to as domains or motifs. This approach can be used for aligning more divergent sequences with the goal of searching for conserved patterns in DNA or protein sequences. "
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "A problem exists when comparing _____ sequences using the dot matrix method, namely, the _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) small, amplification",
            "b) large, amplification",
            "c) small, high noise level",
            "d) large, high noise level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Both types of algorithms can be based on one of the three methods: the dot matrix method, the dynamic programming method, and the word method. The word method is used in fast database similarity searching. "
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about dot plot method and its applications?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This method gives a direct visual statement of the relationship between two sequences",
            "b) One of its advantages is the identification of sequence repeat regions based on the presence of parallel diagonals of the same size vertically or horizontally in the matrix",
            "c) It is not useful in identifying chromosomal repeats",
            "d) The method can be used in identifying nucleic acid secondary structures through detecting self-complementarity of a sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The comparison is done by scanning each residue of one sequence for similarity with all residues in the other sequence. If a residue match is found, a dot is placed within the graph. Otherwise, the matrix positions are left blank. "
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "By calculating alignment scores of a large number of ______ sequence pairs, a distribution model of the ______ sequence scores can be derived.",
        "Options": [
            "a) related, randomized",
            "b) unrelated, randomized",
            "c) unrelated, unrandomized",
            "d) related, unrandomized"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When given a sequence alignment showing a certain degree of similarity, it is often important to determine whether the observed sequence alignment can occur by random chance or the alignment is indeed statistically sound. When a statistically significant sequence alignment is under consideration, it will be able to provide evidence of homology between the sequences involved."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Many studies have demonstrated that the distribution of similarity scores assumes a peculiar shape that resembles a highly skewed normal distribution with a long tail on one side. The distribution matches the _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gumble elective value distribution",
            "b) Gumble extreme void distribution",
            "c) Gumble end value distribution",
            "d) Gumble extreme value distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Solving the statistical significance problem requires a statistical test of the alignment scores of two unrelated sequences of the same length. From the distribution, a statistical test can be performed based on the number of standard deviations from the average score."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a part of the statistical test of sequences?",
        "Options": [
            "a) An optimal alignment between two chosen sequences is obtained at the end",
            "b) Unrelated sequences of the same length are then generated through a randomization process",
            "c) Unrelated sequences of the different length are then generated through a randomization process",
            "d) Related sequences of the same length are then generated through a randomization process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The mentioned Distribution pattern matches the Gumble extreme value distribution for which a mathematical expression is available. This means that, given a sequence similarity value, by using the mathematical formula for the extreme distribution, the statistical significance can be accurately estimated."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "What is used to generate parameters for the extreme distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The pool of alignment scores from the shuffled sequences",
            "b) A single score of a shuffled sequence",
            "c) The pool of alignment scores from the unshuffled sequences",
            "d) The basic optimal score computed at the beginning of the test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Unrelated sequences of the same length are then generated through a randomization process in which one of the two sequences is randomly shuffled. And the next step is that a new alignment score is computed for the shuffled sequence pair."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "If the score is located in the extreme margin of the distribution, that means that the alignment between the two sequences is ______ due to random chance and is thus considered ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) unlikely, significant",
            "b) unlikely, insignificant",
            "c) unlikely, insignificant",
            "d) very likely, significant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: After the mentioned step, computation for the alignment score for the shuffled sequence pair is done. Further, More such scores are similarly obtained through repeated shuffling."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about the PRSS program?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for Probability of Random Shuffles",
            "b) It is a web-based program that can be used to evaluate the statistical significance of DNA or protein sequence alignment",
            "c) It first aligns two sequences using the Needleman-Wunsch algorithm and calculates the score",
            "d) It holds one sequence in its original form and randomizes the order of residues in the other sequence."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum scores are obtained through repeated shuffling. Then the pool of alignment scores from the shuffled sequences is used to generate parameters for the extreme distribution. The original alignment score is then compared against the distribution of random alignments to determine whether the score is beyond random chance."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot be related to multiple sequence alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Many conserved and functionally critical amino acid residues can be identified in a protein multiple alignment",
            "b) Multiple sequence alignment is also an essential prerequisite to carrying out phylogenetic analysis of sequence families and prediction of protein secondary and tertiary structures",
            "c) Multiple sequence alignment also has applications in designing degenerate polymerase chain reaction (PCR) primers based on multiple related sequences",
            "d) This method does not contribute much to degenerate polymerase chain reaction (PCR) primers creation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A natural extension of pair wise alignment is multiple sequence alignment, which is to align multiple related sequences to achieve optimal matching of the sequences. Related sequences are identified through the database similarity searching. As the process generates multiple matching sequence pairs, it is often necessary to convert the numerous pair wise alignments into a single alignment, which arranges sequences in such a way that evolutionarily equivalent positions across all sequences are matched."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "Which of the following scores are not considered while calculating the SP scores?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All possible pair wise matches",
            "b) All possible mismatches",
            "c) All possible gap costs",
            "d) Number of gap penalties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is truly an advantage of multiple sequence alignment. For example, it allows the identification of conserved sequence patterns and motifs in the whole sequence family, which are not obvious to detect by comparing only two sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about DCA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for Divide-and-Conquer Alignment",
            "b) It works by breaking each of the sequences into two smaller sections",
            "c) The breaking points during the process are determined based on regional similarity of the sequences",
            "d) If the sections are not short enough, further divisions are restricted as well"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In practice, heuristic approaches are most often used. Multiple sequence alignment has applications in designing degenerate (PCR) primers based on multiple related sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the Progressive Alignment Method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Progressive alignment depends on the stepwise assembly of multiple alignments and is heuristic in nature",
            "b) It speeds up the alignment of multiple sequences through a multistep process",
            "c) It first conducts pair wise alignments for each possible pair of sequences using the Needleman–Wunsch global alignment method and records these similarity scores from the pair wise comparisons",
            "d) Its drawback is it slows down the alignment of multiple sequences through a single step process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Progressive alignment speeds up the alignment of multiple sequences through a multistep process further, the scores can either be percent identity or similarity scores based on a particular substitution matrix. Both scores correlate with the evolutionary distances between sequences. "
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the progressive alignment method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The program also applies a weighting scheme to increase the reliability of aligning divergent sequences (sequences with less than 25% identity)",
            "b) The progress is done by down weighting redundant and closely related groups of sequences in the alignment by a certain factor",
            "c) This scheme is useful in enhancing similar sequences from dominating the alignment",
            "d) This scheme is useful in enhancing similar sequences from dominating the alignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Probably the most well-known progressive alignment program is Clustal. The stand-alone program, which runs on UNIX and Macintosh, has two variants, Clustal W and Clustal X. The W version provides a simple text-based interface and the X version provides a more user-friendly graphical interface."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a drawback of the progressive alignment method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The progressive alignment method is not suitable for comparing sequences of different lengths because it is a global alignment–based method",
            "b) In this method the use of affine gap penalties, long gaps are not allowed, and, in some cases, this may limit the accuracy of the method",
            "c) In this method the use of affine gap penalties, long gaps is allowed, and, in some cases, this may limit the accuracy of the method",
            "d) The final alignment result is also influenced by the order of sequence addition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This scheme is useful in enhancing similar sequences from dominating the alignment. Further, the weight factor for each sequence is determined by its branch length on the guide tree. The branch lengths are normalized by how many times sequences share a basal branch from the root of the tree."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding T-Coffee?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for Tree-based Consistency Objective Function for alignment Evaluation",
            "b) It performs progressive sequence alignments as in Clustal.",
            "c) The global pair wise alignment is not performed using the Clustal program.",
            "d) The local pair wise alignment is generated by the Lalign program, from which the top ten scored alignments are selected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Another major limitation is the “greedy” nature of the algorithm: it depends on initial pair wise alignment. Once gaps introduced in the early steps of alignment, they are fixed. The final alignment could be far from optimal. The problem can be more glaring when dealing with divergent sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about iterative approach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The iterative approach is based on the idea that an optimal solution can be found by repeatedly modifying existing suboptimal solutions",
            "b) Because the order of the sequences used for alignment is different in each iteration",
            "c) This method is also heuristic in nature and does not have guarantees for finding the optimal alignment",
            "d) This method is not based on heuristic methods"
        ],
        "Answer": ": c\nExplanation: The global pair wise alignment is performed using the Clustal program. The main difference is that, in processing a query, T-Coffee performs both global and local pair wise alignment for all possible pairs involved. The collection of local and global sequence alignments is pooled to form a library. The consistency of the alignments is evaluated."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about PRRN?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PRRN is a web-based program that uses a double nested iterative strategy for multiple alignment",
            "b) It performs multiple alignments through two sets of iterations: inner iteration and outer iteration",
            "c) In the outer iteration, an initial random alignment is generated that is used to derive a UPGMA tree",
            "d) In the inner iteration, the sequences are randomly divided into multiple groups"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: This method is based on heuristic methods. The procedure starts by producing a low-quality alignment and gradually improves it by iterative realignment through well-defined procedures until no more improvements in the alignment scores can be achieved."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about DIALIGN2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web based program designed to detect local similarities",
            "b) It is designed to detect global similarities",
            "c) It does not apply gap penalties and thus is not sensitive to long gaps",
            "d) The method breaks each of the sequences down to smaller segments and performs all possible pair wise alignments between the segments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the inner iteration, the sequences are randomly divided into two groups. Randomized alignment is used for each group in the initial cycle, after which the alignment positions in each group are fixed. The two groups, each treated as a single sequence, are then aligned to each other using global dynamic programming. The process is repeated through many cycles until the total SP score no longer increases. At this point, the resulting alignment is used to construct a new UPGMA tree."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the objective to perform sequence comparison?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To observe patterns of conservation",
            "b) To find the common motifs present in both sequences",
            "c) To study the physical properties of molecules",
            "d) To study evolutionary relationships"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To assess whether it is likely that two sequences evolved from the same sequence comparison is required. Also, to find out which sequences from the database are similar to the sequence at hand, sequence comparison is carried out."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Protein substitution matrices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are significantly more complex than DNA scoring matrices",
            "b) They have the N x N matrices of the amino acids",
            "c) Protein substitution matrices have quite important role in evolutionary studies",
            "d) They are significantly quite less complex than DNA scoring matrices"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sequence alignment is an exact and quantitative measure of similarity of alignments. It involves Construction of the best alignment between the sequences and assessment of the similarity from the alignment."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "The number of possible global alignments between two sequences of length N is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{2^N}{\\sqrt{πN}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{2^{2N}}{\\sqrt{πN}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{2^{(N-1)}}{\\sqrt{πN}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{2^{2N}}{\\sqrt{N}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The global sequence alignment is suitable when the two sequences are of similar length, with a significant degree of similarity throughout. It gives the best alignment over the entire length of two sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Needleman-Wunsch algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is an example of dynamic programming",
            "b) Basic idea here is to build up the best alignment by using optimal alignments of larger subsequences",
            "c) It was first used by Saul Needleman and Christian Wunsch",
            "d) It was first used in 1970"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Use of +1 as a reward for a match, -1 as the penalty for a mismatch, and ignoring gaps is the scoring scheme of this type of method. Hence, the alignment score is the sum of substitution scores and gap penalties in this type of algorithm."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Progenitor sequences represented by the ______ branches of the tree are derived by alignment of the _______ sequences.",
        "Options": [
            "a) outer, outermost",
            "b) inner, outermost",
            "c) inner, innermost",
            "d) outer, innermost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The progressive alignment methods use the dynamic programming method. Relationships among the sequences are modeled by an evolutionary tree in which the outer branches or leaves are the sequences. The tree is based on pair-wise comparisons of the sequences using one of the phylogenetic methods."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "CLUSTALW is a more recent version of CLUSTAL with the W standing for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) weakening",
            "b) winding",
            "c) weighting",
            "d) wiping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Progenitor sequences represented by the inner branches of the tree are derived by alignment of the outermost sequences. These inner branches will have uncertainties where positions in the outermost sequences are dissimilar. "
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about CLUSTAL program?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CLUSTAL performs a global-multiple sequence alignment by a different method than MSA (Multiple Sequence Alignment)",
            "b) The initial heuristic alignment obtained by MSA is calculated in a different way",
            "c) The initial step includes performing pair-wise alignments of all of the sequences",
            "d) The intermediate step includes use the alignment scores to produce a phylogenetic tree"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The W in CLUSTALW stands for ‘weighting’ to represent the ability of the program to provide weights to the sequence and program parameters. CLUSTAL has been around for more than 10 years and lots of improvements in the program have been made."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "The initial alignments used to produce the guide tree may be obtained by various methods. Which of the following is not one of them?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fast k-tuple",
            "b) pattern-finding approach similar",
            "c) FASTA",
            "d) Faster, full dynamic programming method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Two examples of programs that use progressive methods are CLUSTALW and the Genetics Computer Group program PILEUP. CLUSTALX provides a graphic interface.\nThese changes provide more realistic alignments that should reflect the evolutionary changes in the aligned sequences and the more appropriate distribution of gaps between conserved domains."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about PILEUP program?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the MSA program that is a part of the Genetics Computer Group package of sequence analysis programs",
            "b) It is owned since 1997 by Oxford Communications and is widely used due to the popularity and availability of this package",
            "c) It uses a method for MSA that is polar opposite to CLUSTALW",
            "d) The sequences are aligned pair-wise using the Needleman- Wunsch dynamic programming algorithm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The initial heuristic alignment obtained by MSA is calculated the same way, although it performs a global-multiple sequence alignment by a different method than MSA (Multiple Sequence Alignment). As the mentioned options are first two steps, the last is aligning the sequences sequentially, guided by the phylogenetic relationships indicated by the tree."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding PRRP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The program PRRP uses iterative methods to produce an alignment",
            "b) An initial pair-wise alignment is made to predict a tree",
            "c) Only one cycle is performed",
            "d) The whole process is repeated until there is no further increase in the alignment score"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Subgroups are aligned into a global alignment of all of the sequences. The objective is to improve the overall alignment score, such as a sum of pairs score. Selection of these groups may be based on the ordering of the sequences on a phylogenetic tree predicted in a manner similar to that of progressive alignment, separation of one or two of the sequences from the rest, or a random selection of the groups."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "In Genetic Algorithm, in the mutation process _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) sequence is changed",
            "b) gaps are not inserted",
            "c) sequence is not changed",
            "d) gaps are not rearranged"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As mentioned, an initial pair-wise alignment is made to predict a tree, the tree is used to produce weights for making alignments in the same manner as MSA except that the sequences are analyzed for the presence of aligned regions that include gaps rather than being globally aligned, and these regions are iteratively recalculated to improve the alignment score. The best scoring alignment is then used in a new cycle of calculations to predict a new tree, new weights, and new alignments."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about iterative methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Genetic Algorithm is method used for under this",
            "b) Hidden Markov Models are used for Multiple Sequence Alignment",
            "c) The objective is to improve the overall alignment score",
            "d) MultAlin recalculates global scores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The program DIALIGN finds an alignment by a different iterative method. Pairs of sequences are aligned to locate aligned regions that do not include gaps, much like continuous diagonals in a dot matrix plot. Diagonals of various lengths are identified. A consistent collection of weighted diagonals that provides an alignment which is a maximum sum of weights is then found."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not among the methods for finding localized sequence similarity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Profile Analysis",
            "b) Block Analysis",
            "c) Extraction of Blocks from a Global or Local MSA",
            "d) Pattern blocking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pattern Searching is the correct name of the method for finding localized sequence similarity. This type of analysis was performed on groups of related proteins, and the amino acid patterns that were located may be found in the Prosite catalog."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "Profiles are found by performing the _____ MSA of a group of sequences and then removing the _______ regions in the alignment into a smaller MSA.",
        "Options": [
            "a) local, more highly conserved",
            "b) global, low conserved",
            "c) global, more highly conserved",
            "d) local, low conserved"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Profiles are found by performing the global MSA of a group of sequences and then removing the more highly conserved regions in the alignment into a smaller MSA. A scoring matrix for the MSA, called a profile, is then made. The profile is composed of columns much like a mini-MSA and may include matches, mismatches, insertions, and deletions."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the block analysis method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blocks represent a conserved region in the MSA",
            "b) Blocks differ from profiles in lacking insert and delete positions in the sequences",
            "c) Every column includes only matches and mismatches",
            "d) Blocks may be made by searching for a section of an MSA alignment that is low conserved"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A version of the Profilesearch program, which performs a database search for matches to a profile, is available at the University of Pittsburgh Supercomputer Center. A special grant application may be needed to use this facility. Profile-generating programs are available by FTP and are included in the Genetics Computer Group suite of programs."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true regarding the BLOCKS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blocks of width 10–55 are extracted from a protein MSA",
            "b) The protein MSA is up to 400 sequences",
            "c) The program doesn’t accept manually reformatted MSAs",
            "d) The program accepts FASTA format"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Like profiles, blocks may be made by searching for a section of an MSA alignment that is highly conserved. However, aligned regions may also be found by searching each sequence in turn for similar patterns of the same length. These patterns may include a region with one or a few matching characters followed by a short spacer region of unmatched characters and then by another set of a few matching characters, and so on, until the sequences start to be different."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true regarding the BLOCKS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The BLOCKS server can extract a conserved, ungapped region from a MSA to produce a sequence block",
            "b) The server can also find blocks in a set of unaligned, input sequences and maintains a large database of blocks based on an analysis of proteins in the Prosite catalog",
            "c) Blocks are found by the Protomat program",
            "d) The program MOTIF doesn’t locate spaced patterns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: These methods do not use substitution matrices such as the PAM and BLOSUM matrices to score matches. Rather, they are based on finding exact matches that have the same spacing in at least some of the input sequences, and that may be repeated in a given sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding Expectation Maximization algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) An initial guess is made as to the location and size of the site of interest in each of the sequences, and these parts of the sequence are aligned",
            "b) The alignment provides an estimate of the base or amino acid composition of each column in the site",
            "c) The column-by-column composition of the site already available is used to estimate the probability of finding the site at any position in each of the sequences",
            "d) The row-by-column composition of the site already available is used to estimate the probability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This algorithm has been used to identify both conserved domains in unaligned proteins and protein-binding sites in unaligned DNA sequences (Lawrence and Reilly 1990), including sites that may include gaps (Cardon and Stormo 1992). Given are a set of sequences that are expected to have a common sequence pattern and may not be easily recognizable by eye."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "Out of the two repeated steps in EM algorithm, the step 2 is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the maximization step",
            "b) the minimization step",
            "c) the optimization step",
            "d) the normalization step"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The EM algorithm then consists of two steps, which are repeated consecutively. In step 1, the expectation step, the column-by-column composition of the site already available is used to estimate the probability of finding the site at any position in each of the sequences. These probabilities are used in turn to provide new information as to the expected base or amino acid distribution for each column in the site. "
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "In EM algorithm, as an example, suppose that there are 10 DNA sequences having very little similarity with each other, each about 100 nucleotides long and thought to contain a binding site near the middle 20 residues, based on biochemical and genetic evidence. the following steps would be used by the EM algorithm to find the most probable location of the binding sites in each of the ______ sequences.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 25",
            "d) 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In step 2, the maximization step, the new counts of bases or amino acids for each position in the site found in step 1 are substituted for the previous set. Step 1 is then repeated using these new counts. The cycle is repeated until the algorithm converges on a solution and does not change with further cycles. At that time, the best location of the site in each sequence and the best estimate of the residue composition of each column in the site will be available."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "For the 10-residue DNA sequence example, there are _______ possible starting sites for a 20-residue-long site.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 21",
            "c) 81",
            "d) 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When examining the EM program MEME, the size and number of binding sites, the location in each sequence, and whether or not the site is present in each sequence do not necessarily have to be known. For the present example, the following steps would be used by the EM algorithm to find the most probable location of the binding sites in each of the 10 sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Which of the following about MEME is untrue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a Web resource for performing local MSAs (Multiple Sequence Alignment) by the above expectation maximization method is the program MEME",
            "b) It stands for Multiple EM for Motif Elicitation",
            "c) It was developed at developed at the University of California at San Diego Supercomputing Center",
            "d) The Web page has multiple versions for searching blocks by an EM algorithm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The base composition of each column in the aligned patterns is then determined. The composition of the flanking sequence on each side of the site provides the surrounding base or amino acid composition for comparison. Each sequence is assumed to be the same length and to be aligned by the ends."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "Which of the following about the Gibbs sampler is untrue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a statistical method for finding motifs in sequences",
            "b) It is dissimilar to the principle of the EM method",
            "c) It searches for the statistically most probable motifs",
            "d) It can find the optimal width and number of given motifs in each sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For example, that there are four Gs in the first column of the 10 sequences, then the frequency of G in the first column of the site, fSG = 4/10 = 0.4. This procedure is repeated for each base and each column."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "The quality and quantity of information provided by the PSSM also varies for ________ in the motif.",
        "Options": [
            "a) each row",
            "b) each column",
            "c) rows and columns",
            "d) neither the rows nor the columns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The analysis of MSAs (Multiple Sequence Alignment) for conserved blocks of sequence leads to production of the position-specific scoring matrix or PSSM. The PSSM may be used to search a sequence to obtain the most probable location or locations of the motif represented by the PSSM. Alternatively, the PSSM may be used to search an entire database to identify additional sequences that also have the same motif."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "Two considerations arise in trying to tune the PSSM so that it adequately represents the training sequences. Which of the following is not their description?",
        "Options": [
            "a) If a given column in 20 sequences has only isoleucine, it is not very likely that different amino acid will be found in other sequences with that motif because the residue is probably important for function",
            "b) If a given column in 20 sequences has only isoleucine, it is very likely that different amino acid will be found in other sequences with that motif because the residue is probably important for function",
            "c) If the number of sequences with the found motif is large and reasonably diverse, the sequences represent a good statistical sampling of all sequences that are ever likely to be found with that same motif",
            "d) Another column in the motif from the 20 sequences may have several amino acids, and some amino acids may not be represented at all"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The quality and quantity of information provided by the PSSM also varies for each column in the motif, and this variation profoundly influences the matches found with sequences. This situation can be accurately described by information theory, and the results can be displayed by a colored graph called a sequence logo."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "If a good sampling of sequences is _______ the number of sequences is _________ and the motif structure is ________ it should, in principle, be possible to obtain frequencies highly representative of the same motif in other sequences also.",
        "Options": [
            "a) available, sufficiently large, not too complex",
            "b) unavailable, sufficiently large, not too complex",
            "c) unavailable, sufficiently small, not too complex",
            "d) available, sufficiently large, too complex"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The PSSM is constructed by a simple logarithmic transformation of a matrix giving the frequency of each amino acid in the motif. Even more variation may be expected at that position in other sequences, although the more abundant amino acids already found in that column would probably be favored."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "If the data set is _______ then unless the motif has __________ amino acids in each column, the column frequencies in the motif may not be highly representative of all other occurrences of the motif.",
        "Options": [
            "a) small, distinct",
            "b) small, almost identical",
            "c) large, almost identical",
            "d) large, distinct"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The more abundant amino acids already found in that column would probably be favored. Thus, if a good sampling of sequences is available, the number of sequences is sufficiently large, and the motif structure is not too complex, it should, in principle, be possible to obtain frequencies highly representative of the same motif in other sequences also (Henikoff and Henikoff 1996)."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a feature of editors and formatters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) provision for displaying the sequence on a color monitor with residue colors to aid in a clear visual representation of the alignment",
            "b) recognition of the multiple sequence format that was output by the MSA (Multiple Sequence Alignment)  program",
            "c) maintenance of the alignment in a suitable format when the editing is completed",
            "d) disallowing shading conserved residues in the alignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The number of sequences for producing the motif may be small, highly diverse, or complex, giving rise to a second level of consideration. If the data set is small, then unless the motif has almost identical amino acids in each column, the column frequencies in the motif may not be highly representative of all other occurrences of the motif. In such cases, it is desirable to improve the estimates of the amino acid frequencies by adding extra amino acid counts, called pseudocounts, to obtain a more reasonable distribution of amino acid frequencies in the column."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not one of the requirements for implementing algorithms for sequence database searching?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size of the dataset",
            "b) Sensitivity",
            "c) Specificity",
            "d) Speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This process involves submission of a query sequence and performing a pairwise comparison of the query sequence with all individual sequences in a database. Thus, database similarity searching is pairwise alignment on a large scale. This type of searching is one of the most effective ways to assign putative functions to newly determined sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "An increase in sensitivity is associated with _______ in selectivity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) no specific change",
            "b) increase",
            "c) decrease",
            "d) exponential increase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dynamic programming method is slow and impractical to use in most cases. Special search methods are needed to speed up the computational process of sequence comparison."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smith–Waterman algorithm is the fastest",
            "b) Smith–Waterman algorithm is comparatively slower method",
            "c) To speedup up comparison, heuristic methods are used",
            "d) Heuristic algorithms perform faster searches"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are unique requirements for implementing algorithms for sequence database searching out of which, the later three play an important role. However, speed can vary with the size of database. achieving all three at a time is nearly impossible."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect the ‘word’ method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both BLAST and FASTA use a heuristic word method",
            "b) Word method is used for fast pairwise sequence alignment in BLAST and FASTA",
            "c) The basic assumption is that two related sequences must have at least one word in common",
            "d) Two related sequences must have at zero word in common while assuming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Among the unique requirements for implementing algorithms for sequence database Searching, the first criterion is sensitivity, which refers to the ability to find as many correct hits as possible. It is measured by the extent of inclusion of correctly identified sequence members of the same family. These correct hits are considered ‘true positives’ in the database searching exercise."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "1.The BLAST program was developed in _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1992",
            "b) 1995",
            "c) 1990",
            "d) 1991"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The BLAST program was developed by Stephen Altschul of NCBI in 1990 and hassince become one of the most popular programs for sequence analysis. BLAST uses heuristics to align a query sequence with all sequences in a database."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "In sequence alignment by BLAST, each word from query sequence is typically _______ residues for protein sequences and _______ residues for DNA sequences.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ten, eleven",
            "b) three, three",
            "c) three, eleven",
            "d) three, ten"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first step is to create a list of words from the query sequence. Each word is typically three residues for protein sequences and eleven residues for DNA sequences. The list includes every possible word extracted from the query sequence. This step is also called seeding."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a variant of BLAST?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BLASTN",
            "b) BLASTP",
            "c) BLASTX",
            "d) TBLASTNX"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This step is to identify database sequences containing the matching words. The matching of the words is scored by a given substitution matrix. A word is considered a match if it is above a threshold."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct about BLAST?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The BLAST web server has been designed in such away as to simplify the task of program selection",
            "b) The programs are organized based on the type of query sequences",
            "c) The programs are organized based on the type of nucleotide sequences, or nucleotide sequence to be translated",
            "d) BLAST is not based on heuristic searching methods"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The extension continues until the score of the alignment drops below a threshold due to mismatches (the drop threshold is twenty-two for proteins and twenty for DNA). The resulting contiguous aligned segment pair without gaps is called high-scoring segment pair. In the original version of BLAST, the highest scored HSPs are presented as the final report. They are also called maximum scoring pairs."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct about FASTA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Its stands for FAST ALL",
            "b) It was in fact the first database similarity search tool developed, preceding the development of BLAST",
            "c) FASTA uses a ‘hashing’ strategy to find matches for a short stretch of identical residues with a length of k",
            "d) The string of residues is known as blocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The string of residues is known as ktuples or ktups, which are equivalent to words inBLAST, but are normally shorter than the words. Typically, a ktup is composed of two residues for protein sequences and six residues for DNA sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "The positional difference for each word between the two sequences is obtained by ________ the position of the ______ sequence from that of the _______ sequence and is expressed as the offset.",
        "Options": [
            "a) subtracting, second, first",
            "b) adding, second, first",
            "c) adding, first, second",
            "d) subtracting, first, second"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first step in FASTA alignment is to identify ktups between two sequences by using the hashing strategy. This strategy works by constructing a look up table that shows the position of each ktup for the two sequences under consideration. The mentioned method is similar to that of BLAST."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "In FASTA, For a Z-score > 15, the match can be considered extremely ______ with _____ of a homologous relationship.",
        "Options": [
            "a) insignificant, uncertainty",
            "b) significant, uncertainty",
            "c) significant, certainty",
            "d) insignificant, certainty"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If Z is in the range of 5 to 15, the sequence pair can be described as highly probable homologs. If Z<5, their relationship is described as less certain."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "BLAST uses a _______ to find matching words, whereas FASTA identifies identical matching words using the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) substitution matrix, hashing procedure",
            "b) substitution matrix, blocks",
            "c) hashing procedure, substitution matrix",
            "d) ktups, substitution matrix"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: BLAST and FASTA have been shown to perform almost equally well in regular database searching; However, there are some notable differences between the two approaches. The major difference is in the seeding step– BLAST uses a substitution matrix to find matching words, whereas FASTA identifies identical matching words using the hashing procedure."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a benefit or a factual of FASTA over BLAST?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FASTA scans smaller window sizes",
            "b) It gives more sensitive results",
            "c) It gives less sensitive results",
            "d) It gives results with a better coverage rate for homologs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: By default, FASTA scans smaller window sizes. Thus, it gives more sensitive results than BLAST, with a better coverage rate for homologs. However, it is usually slower than BLAST."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a benefit of BLAST?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Handling of gaps",
            "b) Speed",
            "c) More sensitive",
            "d) Statistical rigor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In addition to the given statement, BLAST sometimes gives multiple best-scoring alignments from the same sequence. FASTA returns only one final alignment."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "The initiation of FASTA format has ____ symbol.",
        "Options": [
            "a) >",
            "b) <",
            "c) /",
            "d) *"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In addition to this, user friendly UI of BLAST is also one of its benefits. However, it does not handle gaps well. In that case gapped BLAST is better."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "FASTA and BLAST are __________ but __________ for larger datasets.",
        "Options": [
            "a) faster, more sensitive",
            "b) faster, less sensitive",
            "c) slower, less sensitive",
            "d) slower, more sensitive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Heuristics such as BLAST and FASTA are developed for faster speed. However, the heuristic methods are limited in sensitivity and are not guaranteed to find the optimal alignment. They often fail to find alignment for distantly related sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "In Smith–Waterman algorithm, in initialization Step, the _________ row and ________ column are subject to gap penalty.",
        "Options": [
            "a) first, first",
            "b) first, second",
            "c) second, First",
            "d) first, last"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Empirical tests have indeed shown that the exhaustive method produces superior results over the heuristic methods like BLAST and FASTA. But heuristic methods are better and practical when it comes to assess larger datasets with comparatively low sensitivity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "In SW algorithm, to align two sequences of lengths of m and n _________ time is required.",
        "Options": [
            "a) O(mn)",
            "b) O(m2n)",
            "c) O(m2n3)",
            "d) O(mn2)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ScanPS (Scan Protein Sequence) is a web-based program that implements a modified version of the Smith–Waterman algorithm optimized for parallel processing. The major feature is that the program allows iterative searching similar to PSI-BLAST, which builds profiles from one round of search results and uses them for the second round of database searching. Full dynamic programming is used in each cycle for added sensitivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "The building blocks of proteins are ______ naturally occurring amino acids, small molecules that contain a free amino group (NH2) and a free carboxyl group (COOH).",
        "Options": [
            "a) ten",
            "b) twenty",
            "c) nine",
            "d) nineteen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Both of these groups are linked to a central carbon (Cα), which is attached to hydrogen and a side chain group (R). Amino acids differ only by the side chain R group. The chemical reactivities of the R groups determine the specific properties of the amino acids. Amino acids can be grouped into several categories based on the chemical and physical properties of the side chains, such as size and affinity for water."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "______ the smallest amino acid, has a hydrogen atom as the R group.",
        "Options": [
            "a) valine",
            "b) proline",
            "c) Glycine",
            "d) threonine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aliphatic side chains are linear hydrocarbon chains and aromatic side chains are cyclic rings. Within the hydrophilic set, amino acids can be subdivided into polar and charged. Charged amino acids can be either positively charged (basic) or negatively charged (acidic)."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "A linear polymer of more than fifty amino acid residues is referred to as a ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) dipeptide",
            "b) oligopeptide",
            "c) peptide",
            "d) polypeptide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Of particular interest within the twenty amino acids are glycine and proline. It can therefore adopt more flexible conformations that are not possible for other amino acids. Proline is on the other extreme of flexibility. Its side chain forms a bond with its own backbone amino group, causing it to be cyclic. The cyclic conformation makes it very rigid, unable to occupy many of the main chain conformations adopted by other amino acids."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct about the stabilizing Forces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protein structures from secondary to quaternary are maintained by noncovalent forces",
            "b) They include electrostatic interactions but not van der Waals forces, and hydrogen bonding",
            "c) Electrostatic interactions are a significant stabilizing force in a protein structure",
            "d) Electrostatic interactions occur when excess negative charges in one region are neutralized by positive charges in another region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This reaction is a condensation reaction involving removal of elements of water from the two molecules. The resulting product is called a dipeptide. The newly formed covalent bond connecting the two amino acids is called a peptide bond. Once an amino acid is incorporated into a peptide, it becomes an amino acid residue. Multiple amino acids can be joined together to form a longer chain of amino acid polymer."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct about the α-Helices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) An α-helix has a main chain backbone conformation that resembles a corkscrew",
            "b) Nearly all known α-helices are right handed, exhibiting a leftward spiral form",
            "c) Nearly all known α-helices are right handed, exhibiting a rightward spiral form",
            "d) In right handed helix, there are 3.6 amino acids per helical turn"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A polypeptide, also called a protein, has a well-defined three-dimensional arrangement. On the other hand, a polymer with fewer than fifty residues is usually called a peptide without a well-defined three-dimensional structure. The residues a peptide or polypeptide are numbered beginning with the residue containing the amino group, referred to as the N-terminus, and ending with the residue containing the carboxyl group, known as the C-terminus."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct about the β-sheet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A β-sheet is a fully extended configuration built up from several spatially adjacent regions of a polypeptide chain",
            "b) Each region involved in forming the β-sheet is a β-strand",
            "c) The β-strand conformation is pleated with main chain backbone zigzagging and side chains positioned on same sides of the sheet",
            "d) β-Strands are stabilized by hydrogen bonds between residues of adjacent strands"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rigid double bond structure forces atoms associated with the peptide bond to lie in the same plane, called the peptide plane. For a peptide unit, the atoms linked to the peptide bond can be moved to a certain extent by the rotation of two bonds flanking the peptide bond."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct about the Coils and Loops?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are regular structures",
            "b) They are irregular structures",
            "c) The loops are often characterized by sharp turns or hairpin-like structures",
            "d) If the connecting regions are completely irregular, they belong to random coils"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It includes electrostatic interactions, van der Waals forces, and hydrogen bonding. The result is the formation of salt bridges between oppositely charged residues. The electrostatic interactions can function within a relatively long range (15 Å). Hydrogen bonds are a particular type of electrostatic interactions similar to dipole–dipole interactions involving hydrogen from one residue and oxygen from another. Hydrogen bonds can occur between main chain atoms as well as side chain atoms."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct about the Integral Membrane Proteins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Membrane proteins exist in lipid bilayers of cell membranes",
            "b) The exterior of the proteins spanning the membrane must be very hydrophobic to be stable",
            "c) The exterior of the proteins spanning the membrane must be very hydrophilic to be stable",
            "d) Most typical transmembrane segments are α-helices"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The structure is stabilized by hydrogen bonds formed between the main chain atoms of residues i and i + 4. The hydrogen bonds are nearly parallel with the helical axis. The average φ and ψ angles are 60◦ and 45◦, respectively, and are distributed in a narrowly defined region in the lower left region of a Ramachandran plot."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct about the X-ray Crystallography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In x-ray protein crystallography, proteins need to be grown into large crystals in which their positions are fixed in a repeated, ordered fashion",
            "b) The protein crystals are illuminated with an intense x-ray beam",
            "c) The x-rays are deflected by the electron clouds surrounding the atoms in the crystal producing a regular pattern of diffraction",
            "d) The protein crystals are illuminated with an intense infrared beam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The β-strand conformation is pleated with main chain backbone zigzagging and side chains positioned alternately on opposite sides of the sheet. β-strands near the surface of the protein tend to show an alternating pattern of hydrophobic and hydrophilic regions, whereas strands buried at the core of a protein are nearly all hydrophobic. The β-strands can run in the same direction to form a parallel sheet or can run every other chain in reverse orientation to form an antiparallel sheet or a mixture of both."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct about the NMR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for Nuclear Magnetic Resonance",
            "b) NMR spectroscopy detects spinning patterns of atomic nuclei in a electric field",
            "c) NMR spectroscopy detects spinning patterns of atomic nuclei in a magnetic field",
            "d) Protein samples are labeled with radioisotopes such as 13C and 15N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Residues in the loop or coil regions tend to be charged and polar and located on the surface of the protein structure. They are often the evolutionarily variable regions where mutations, deletions, and insertions frequently occur. They can be functionally significant because these locations are often the active sites of proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong about Swiss-PDB Viewer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a structure viewer for multiple platforms",
            "b) It is a structure viewer for single platforms",
            "c) It is essentially a Swiss-Army knife for structure visualization and modeling",
            "d) It is capable of structure visualization, analysis, and homology modeling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At the touch of a mouse button, a user can move, rotate, and zoom an atomic model on a computer screen in real time, or examine any portion of the structure in great detail, as well as draw it in various forms in different colors. Further manipulations can include changing the conformation of a structure by protein modeling or matching a ligand to an enzyme active site through docking exercises."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an incorrect statement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) WebMol is a web-based program built based on a modified RasMol code and thus shares many similarities with RasMol",
            "b) WebMol is a web-based program that is totally different from RasMol",
            "c) Chime is a plug-in for web browsers",
            "d) Chime is not a standalone program and has to be invoked in a web browser"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Because a Protein Data Bank (PDB) data file for a protein structure contains only x, y, and z coordinates of atoms, the most basic requirement for a visualization program is to build connectivity between atoms to make a view of a molecule. The visualization program should also be able to produce molecular structures in different styles, which include wire frames, balls and sticks, space-filling spheres, and ribbons."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an incorrect statement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Molscript is a UNIX program capable of generating wire-frame",
            "b) Molscript is capable of generating space-filling",
            "c) Molscript is not capable of generating ball-and-stick styles",
            "d) In particular, secondary structure elements can be drawn with solid spirals and arrows representing α-helices and β-strands, respectively"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The wire frame is the simplest form of model representation. It is useful for localizing positions of specific residues in a protein structure, or for displaying a skeletal form of a structure when Cα atoms of each residue are connected."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about protein structure comparison?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The comparative approach is important in finding remote protein homologs",
            "b) Protein structures have a much higher degree of conservation than the sequences",
            "c) Protein structures have a much lesser degree of conservation than the sequences",
            "d) Proteins can share common structures even without sequence similarity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Structure comparison is one of the fundamental techniques in protein structure analysis. Structure comparison can often reveal distant evolutionary relationships between proteins, which is not feasible using the sequence-based alignment approach alone. In addition, protein structure comparison is a prerequisite for protein structural classification into different fold classes."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "The intermolecular approach is normally applied to relatively _____ structures.",
        "Options": [
            "a) distinctive",
            "b) dissimilar",
            "c) similar",
            "d) different"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The algorithmic approaches to comparing protein geometric properties can be divided into three categories: the first superposes protein structures by minimizing intermolecular distances; the second relies on measuring intramolecular distances of a structure; and the third includes algorithms that combine both intermolecular and intramolecular approaches."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about intermolecular approach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This procedure starts with identifying equivalent residues or atoms",
            "b) After residue–residue correspondence is established, one of the structures is moved laterally and vertically toward the other structure to allow the two structures to be in the same location",
            "c) The structures are rotated relative to each other around the three-dimensional axes",
            "d) The rotation doesn’t depend on the intermolecular distance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The rotation continues until the shortest intermolecular distance is reached. At this point, an optimal superimposition of the two structures is reached. After superimposition, equivalent residue pairs can be identified, which helps to quantitate the fitting between the two structures."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "The root mean square deviation (RMSD), without the size dependency correction is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\sum_{i=1}^N \\frac{D_i^2}{N}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\sum_{i=1}^N \\frac{D_i^2}{N + 1}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\sum_{i=1}^N \\frac{D_i^2}{N x N}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\sum_{i=1}^N \\frac{D_i^2}{N – 1}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An important measurement of the structure fit during superposition is the distance between equivalent positions on the protein structures. This requires using a least square-fitting function called root mean square deviation (RMSD), which is the square root of the averaged sum of the squared differences of the atomic distances. Here D is the distance between coordinate data points and N is the total number of corresponding residue pairs."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "The root mean square deviation (RMSD), with the size dependency correction is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{RMSD}{-1.3 + 0.5 ln⁡(N+1)}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{RMSD}{-1.3 + 0.5 ln⁡(N x N)}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{RMSD}{-1.3 + 0.5 ln⁡(N-1)}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{RMSD}{-1.3 + 0.5 ln⁡(N)}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In practice, only the distances between Cα carbons of corresponding residues are measured. The goal of structural comparison is to achieve a minimum RMSD. However, the problem with RMSD is that it depends on the size of the proteins being compared. For the same degree of sequence identity, large proteins tend to have higher RMSD values than small proteins when an optimal alignment is reached. Recently, a logarithmic factor has been proposed to correct this size-dependency problem. This new measure is called RMSD100."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about the intramolecular approach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The method works by generating a distance matrix between residues of the same protein",
            "b) It generates a string between residues of the same protein",
            "c) In comparing two protein structures, the distance matrices from the two structures are moved relative to each other to achieve maximum overlaps",
            "d) By overlaying two distance matrices, similar intramolecular distance patterns representing similar structure folding regions can be identified"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The intramolecular approach relies on structural internal statistics and therefore does not depend on sequence similarity between the proteins to be compared. In addition, this method does not generate a physical superposition of structures but instead provides a quantitative evaluation of the structural similarity between corresponding residue pairs."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about Multiple Structure Alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The alignment strategy is different than the Clustal sequence alignment using a progressive approach",
            "b) All structures are first compared in a pairwise fashion",
            "c) A distance matrix is developed based on structure similarity scores such as RMSD",
            "d) The aligned structures create a median structure that allows other structures to be progressively added for comparison based on the hierarchy described in the guide tree"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For the ease of comparison, each matrix is decomposed into smaller submatrices consisting of hexapeptide fragments. To maximize the similarity regions between two structures, a Monte Carlo procedure is used. By reducing three-dimensional information into two-dimensional information, this strategy identifies overall structural resemblances and common structure cores."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about SSAP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web server that uses an intramolecular distance–based method",
            "b) Matrices are built based on the Cβ distances of all residue pairs",
            "c) Dynamic programming approach is not used here",
            "d) Dynamic programming approach is used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In addition to pairwise alignment, a number of algorithms can also perform multiple structure alignment. The alignment strategy is similar to the Clustal sequence alignment using a progressive approach. When all the structures in the set are added, this eventually creates a multiple structure alignment."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about SCOP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a database for comparing and classifying protein structures",
            "b) It is constructed almost entirely based on manual examination of protein structures",
            "c) The proteins are grouped into hierarchies of classes, folds, superfamilies, and families",
            "d) The SCOP families consist of proteins having low sequence identity (>30%)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Due to the differences in classification criteria, one might expect that there would be huge differences in classification results. In fact, the classification results from both systems are quite similar. Exhaustive analysis has shown that the results from the two systems converge at about 80% of the time. In other words, only about 20% of the structure fold assignments are different."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "Members within the ____ fold ______ have evolutionary relationships.",
        "Options": [
            "a) same, always",
            "b) same, do not always",
            "c) one, always",
            "d) different, do not"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Among the tens of thousands of entries in PDB, the majority of the structures are redundant as they correspond to structures solved at different resolutions, or associated with different ligands or with single-residue mutations. The redundancy can be removed by selecting representatives through a sequence alignment–based approach."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "In CATH, Structural domain separation is carried by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) manual comparison only",
            "b) computer programs only",
            "c) human expertise only",
            "d) a combined effort of a human expert and computer programs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Because some proteins are composed of multiple domains, they must be subdivided before a sensible structural comparison can be carried out. This domain identification and separation can be done either manually or based on special algorithms for domain recognition."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about SCOP and CATH?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The definition for class in CATH is quite dissimilar to that in SCOP",
            "b) The definition for class in CATH is based on secondary structure content",
            "c) Architecture is a unique level in CATH, intermediate between fold and class",
            "d) The definition for class in CATH is similar to that in SCOP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Once multidomain proteins are split into separate domains, structure comparison can be conducted at the domain level, either through manual inspection, or automated structural alignment, or a combination of both. This step involves grouping proteins/domains of similar structures and clustering them based on different levels of resemblance in secondary structure composition and arrangement of the secondary structures in space."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "SCOP is _______ based on manual comparison of structures by human experts with no quantitative criteria to group proteins.",
        "Options": [
            "a) entirely",
            "b) almost entirely",
            "c) not",
            "d) partially"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The SCOP families consist of proteins having high sequence identity (>30%). Thus, the proteins within a family clearly share close evolutionary relationships and normally have the same functionality. The protein structures at this level are also extremely similar."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "The formation of _____ is determined by ______ interactions, whereas the formation of ____ is strongly influenced by ______ interactions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) α-helices, long-range, α-helices, short-range",
            "b) α-helices, long-range, β-strands, short-range",
            "c) α-helices, short-range, β-strands, long-range",
            "d) β-strands, short-range, β-strands, long-range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Protein secondary structure prediction with high accuracy is not a trivial ask. It remained a very difficult problem for decades. This is because protein secondary structure elements are context dependent. The formation of α-helices is determined by short-range interactions, whereas the formation of β-strands is strongly influenced by long-range interactions. Prediction for long-range interactions is theoretically difficult. After more than three decades of effort, prediction accuracies have only been improved from about 50% to about 75%."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding Ab Initio–Based Methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This type of method predicts the secondary structure based on a single query sequence",
            "b) This type of method predicts the secondary structure based on a multiple query sequence",
            "c) It measures the relative propensity of each amino acid belonging to a certain secondary structure element",
            "d) The propensity scores are derived from known crystal structures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ab initio methods, which belong to early generation methods, predict secondary structures based on statistical calculations of the residues of a single query sequence. The homology-based methods do not rely on statistics of residues of a single sequence, but on common secondary structural patterns conserved among multiple homologous sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding Chou–Fasman and GOR methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both are the first-generation methods",
            "b) They are developed in the 1970s,",
            "c) They suffer from the fact that the prediction rules are somewhat arbitrary",
            "d) They are based on single sequence statistics with clear relation to known protein-folding theories"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Examples of ab initio prediction are the Chou–Fasman and Garnier, Osguthorpe, Robson (GOR) methods. The ab initio methods were developed in the 1970s when protein structural data were very limited. The statistics derived from the limited data sets can therefore be rather inaccurate. However, the methods are simple enough that they are often used to illustrate the basics of secondary structure prediction."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding Homology-Based Methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The third generation of algorithms was developed in the late 1990s",
            "b) They were developed by making use of evolutionary information",
            "c) This type of method uses the ab initio secondary structure prediction of individual sequences only",
            "d) This type of method combines the ab initio secondary structure prediction of individual sequences and alignment information from multiple homologous sequences (>35% identity)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It determines the propensity or intrinsic tendency of each residue using observed frequencies found in protein crystal structures (conformational values for coils are not considered). For example, it is known that alanine, glutamic acid, and methionine are commonly found in α-helices, whereas glycine and proline are much less likely to be found in such structures."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding Prediction with Neural Networks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The third-generation prediction algorithms extensively apply sophisticated neural networks",
            "b) It is used to analyze substitution patterns in multiple sequence alignments",
            "c) It is not a machine learning process",
            "d) It requires a structure of multiple layers of interconnected variables or nodes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The GOR method is based on the “propensity” of each residue to be in one of the two conformational states, helix (H), strand(E), turn(T), and coil (C). However, instead of using the propensity value from a single residue to predict a conformational state, it takes short-range interactions of neighboring residues into account."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding Prediction with Neural Networks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It has to be first trained by sequences with known structures",
            "b) Between input and output are many connected hidden layers",
            "c) Between the connected hidden layers the machine learning takes place to adjust the mathematical weights of internal connections",
            "d) It doesn’t have to be first trained by sequences with known structures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: They are based on single sequence statistics without clear relation to known protein-folding theories. The predictions solely rely on local sequence information and fail to take into account long range interactions. A Chou-Fasman–based prediction does not even consider the short-range environmental information."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding Prediction with Neural Networks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When multiple sequence alignments and neural networks are combined, the result is further improved accuracy",
            "b) A neural network is trained by a single sequence",
            "c) A neural network is trained by a sequence profile derived from the multiple sequence alignment",
            "d) When the sufficiently trained network processes an unknown sequence, it applies the rules learned in training to recognize particular structural patterns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The idea behind this approach is that close protein homologs should adopt the same secondary and tertiary structure. When each individual sequence is predicted for secondary structure using a method similar to the GOR method, errors and variations may occur. However, evolutionary conservation dictates that there should be no major variations for their secondary structure elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding PHD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for Profile network from Heidelberg",
            "b) It is a web-based program that combines neural network only",
            "c) It first performs a BLASTP of the query sequence against a non redundant protein sequence database",
            "d) In initial steps it finds a set of homologous sequences, which are aligned with the MAXHOM program (a weighted dynamic programming algorithm performing global alignment)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By aligning multiple sequences, information of positional conservation is revealed. This homology based method has helped improve the prediction accuracy by another 10% over the second-generation methods."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the transmembrane proteins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constitute up to 30% of all cellular proteins",
            "b) They are responsible for performing a wide variety of important functions in a cell, such as signal transduction, cross-membrane transport, and energy conversion",
            "c) The membrane proteins are also of tremendous biomedical importance",
            "d) They are not drug targets or receptors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The membrane proteins are also of tremendous biomedical importance, as they often serve as drug targets for pharmaceutical development. There are two types of integral membrane proteins: α-helical type and β-barrel type. Most transmembrane proteins contain solely α-helices, which are found in the cytoplasmic membrane. A few membrane proteins consist of β-strands forming a β- barrel topology, a cylindrical structure composed of antiparallel β-sheets."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding Prediction of Helical Membrane Proteins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For membrane proteins consisting of transmembrane α–helices, these transmembrane helices are predominantly hydrophobic with a specific distribution of positively charged residues",
            "b) The α-helices generally run perpendicular to the membrane plane",
            "c) The α-helices generally run parallel to the membrane plane",
            "d) The α-helices have an average length between seventeen and twenty-five residues"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For this group of proteins, prediction of the transmembrane secondary structural elements and their organization is particularly important. Fortunately, the prediction process is somewhat easier because of the hydrophobic environment of the lipid bilayers, which restricts the transmembrane segments to be hydrophobic as well."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "The presence of ______ signal peptides can significantly compromise the prediction _______ because the programs tend to confuse hydrophobic signal peptides with membrane helices.",
        "Options": [
            "a) hydrophobic, accuracy",
            "b) hydrophobic, error",
            "c) hydrophilic, accuracy",
            "d) hydrophilic, error"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The hydrophobic helices are normally separated by hydrophilic loops with average lengths of fewer than sixty residues. The residues bordering the transmembrane spans are more positively charged. Another feature indicative of the presence of transmembrane segments is that residues at the cytosolic side near the hydrophobic anchor are more positively charged than those at the lumenal or periplasmic side. This is known as the positive-inside rule."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding TMHMM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web-based program based on an HMM algorithm",
            "b) It is trained to recognize transmembrane helical patterns",
            "c) It is not trained to recognize transmembrane helical patterns",
            "d) When a query sequence is scanned, the probability of having an α-helical domain is given"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A number of algorithms for identifying transmembrane helices have been developed where the early algorithms based their prediction on hydrophobicity scales. They typically scan a window of seventeen to twenty-five residues and assign membrane spans based on hydrophobicity scores. Some are also able to determine the orientation of the membrane helices based on the positive-inside rule."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding Phobius?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web-based program designed to overcome false positives caused by the presence of signal peptides",
            "b) The program incorporates distinct HMM models for signal peptides only",
            "c) The program incorporates distinct HMM models for signal peptides as well as transmembrane helices",
            "d) After distinguishing the putative signal peptides from the rest of the query sequence, prediction is made on the remainder of the sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Predictions solely based on hydrophobicity profiles have high error rates. As with the third-generation predictions for globular proteins, applying evolutionary information with the help of neural networks or HMMs can improve the prediction accuracy significantly."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true regarding Prediction of β-Barrel Membrane Proteins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For membrane proteins with β-strands only, the β-strands forming the transmembrane segment are amphipathic in nature",
            "b) For membrane proteins with β-strands only, the β-strands forming the transmembrane segment are only hydrophilic in nature",
            "c) For membrane proteins with β-strands only, the β-strands forming the transmembrane segment are only hydrophobic in nature",
            "d) They contain six to nine residues"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Predicting transmembrane helices is relatively easy. The accuracy of Some of the best predicting programs, such as TMHMM or HMMTOP, can exceed 70%. To minimize errors, the presence of signal peptides can be detected using a number of specialized programs and then manually excluded."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true regarding Coiled coil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They have an integral repeat of twenty residues",
            "b) They have an integral repeat of seven residues",
            "c) They have an integral repeat of thirty residues",
            "d) The sequence periodicity doesn’t contribute in designing algorithms to predict the structural domain."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The individual α-helices twist and wind around each other to form a coiled bundle structure. The coiled coil conformation is important in facilitating inter- or intra protein interactions. Proteins possessing these structural domains are often involved in transcription regulation or in the maintenance of cytoskeletal integrity."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding Coils?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web-based program that detects coiled coil regions in proteins",
            "b) It scans a window of fourteen, twenty-one, or twenty-eight residues",
            "c) It scans a window of fourteen or twenty-one residues only",
            "d) It compares the sequence to a probability matrix compiled from known parallel two-stranded coiled coils"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Coiled coils have an integral repeat of seven residues (heptads) which assume a side-chain packing geometry at facing residues. For every seven residues, the first and fourth are hydrophobic, facing the helical interface; the others are hydrophilic and exposed to the solvent. The sequence periodicity forms the basis for designing algorithms to predict this important structural domain."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding PSIPRED?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web-based program that predicts protein secondary structures",
            "b) It uses a combination of evolutionary information and neural networks",
            "c) It uses a combination of evolutionary information only",
            "d) The multiple sequence alignment is derived from a PSI-BLAST database search"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: By comparing the similarity scores, the program calculates the probability of the sequence to adopt a coiled coil conformation. The program is accurate for solvent-exposed, left-handed coiled coils, but less sensitive for other types of coiled coil structures, such as buried or right-handed coiled coils."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about homology modeling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homology modeling predicts protein structures based on sequence homology with known structures",
            "b) It is also known as comparative modeling",
            "c) The principle behind it is that if two proteins share a high enough sequence similarity, they are likely to have very similar three-dimensional structures",
            "d) It doesn’t involve the evolutionary distances anywhere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As the name suggests, homology modeling predicts protein structures based on sequence homology with known structures. Homology modeling produces an all-atom model based on alignment with template proteins. "
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about template Selection Step?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The first step in protein structural modeling is to select appropriate structural templates",
            "b) This forms the foundation for rest of the modeling process",
            "c) There is no use of heuristic alignment search programs",
            "d) The template selection involves searching the Protein Data Bank (PDB) for homologous proteins with determined structures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The search can be performed using a heuristic pair wise alignment search program such as BLAST or FASTA. However, the use of dynamic programming based search programs such as SEARCH or ScanPS can result in more sensitive search results. The relatively small size of the structural database means that the search time using the exhaustive method is still within reasonable limits, while giving a more sensitive result to ensure the best possible similarity hits."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Sequence Alignment Step?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Once the structure with the highest sequence similarity is identified as a template, the full-length sequences of the template and target proteins need to be realigned using refined alignment algorithms to obtain optimal alignment",
            "b) The realignment is the most critical step in homology modeling",
            "c) The realignment directly affects the quality of the final model",
            "d) Errors made in the alignment step can be corrected in the following modeling steps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Incorrect alignment at this stage leads to incorrect designation of homologous residues and therefore to incorrect structural models. Errors made in the alignment step cannot be corrected in the following modeling steps. Therefore, the best possible multiple alignment algorithms, such as Praline and T-Coffee should be used for this purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Backbone Model Building Step?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Once optimal alignment is achieved, residues in the aligned regions of the target protein can assume a similar structure as the template proteins",
            "b) Coordinates of the corresponding residues of the template proteins can be simply copied onto the target protein",
            "c) If the two residues differ, everything other than the backbone atoms can be copied",
            "d) If the two aligned residues are identical, coordinates of the side chain atoms are copied along with the main chain atoms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Option “Once optimal alignment is achieved, residues in the aligned regions of the target protein can assume a similar structure as the template proteins” and “Coordinates of the corresponding residues of the template proteins can be simply copied onto the target protein” mean the same. If the two residues differ, only the backbone atoms can be copied. The side chain atoms are rebuilt in a subsequent procedure.\nIn backbone modeling, it is simplest to use only one template structure. The structure with the best quality and highest resolution is normally chosen if multiple options are available."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Loop Modeling Step?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In the sequence alignment for modeling, there are often regions caused by insertions and deletions producing gaps in sequence alignment",
            "b) In the sequence alignment for modeling, there are no regions producing gaps in sequence alignment",
            "c) The gaps cannot be directly modeled",
            "d) Loop modeling is required for closing the gaps requires"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Closing the gaps requires loop modeling, which is a very difficult problem in homology modeling and is also a major source of error. Loop modeling can be considered a mini–protein modeling problem by itself. Unfortunately, there are no mature methods available that can model loops reliably. Currently, there are two main techniques used to approach the problem: the database searching method and the ab initio method."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about specialized programs for loop modeling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PETRA is a web server that models loops using the database approach",
            "b) FREAD is a web server that models loops using the database approach",
            "c) CODA is a web server that uses a consensus method based on the prediction results from FREAD and PETRA",
            "d) For loops of three to eight residues, CODA uses consensus conformation of both methods"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Usually, many different alternative segments that fit the endpoints of the stems are available. The best loop can be selected based on sequence similarity as well as minimal steric clashes with the neighboring parts of the structure. The conformation of the best matching fragments is then copied onto the anchoring points of the stems."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Ab initio prediction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The limited knowledge of protein folding forms the basis of ab initio prediction",
            "b) The ab initio prediction method attempts to produce all-atom protein models based on sequence information alone without the aid of known protein structures",
            "c) The ab initio prediction method attempts to produce all-atom protein models based on sequence information alone with some aid of known protein structures",
            "d) The perceived advantage of this method is that predictions are not restricted by known folds and that novel protein folds can be identified"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PETRA is a web server that uses the ab initio method to model loops. For nine to thirty residues, CODA uses FREAD prediction only."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "In Rosetta, The segments with assigned _______ structures are subsequently assembled into a ______ dimensional configuration.",
        "Options": [
            "a) primary, three",
            "b) secondary, three",
            "c) secondary, two",
            "d) primary, three"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: However, this approach is computationally prohibitive in most cases. In fact, most current side chain prediction programs use the concept of rotamers, which are favored side chain torsion angles extracted from known protein crystal structures. In prediction of side chain conformation, only the possible rotamers with the lowest interaction energy with nearby atoms are selected."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "In the pairwise energy based method, a protein sequence is searched for in a structural fold database to find the best matching structural fold using ______ criteria.",
        "Options": [
            "a) sequence-based",
            "b) structure-based",
            "c) energy-based",
            "d) residue-based"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are only small number of protein folds available (<1,000), compared to millions of protein sequences. This means that protein structures tend to be more conserved than protein sequences. Consequently, many proteins can share a similar fold even in the absence of sequence similarities. This allowed the development of computational methods to predict protein structures beyond sequence similarities. "
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about profile method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A profile is constructed for a group of related protein structures",
            "b) The propensity of amino acids in not in picture of this method",
            "c) Statistical information from these aligned residues is then used to construct a profile",
            "d) The structural profile is generated by the superimposition of the structures to expose corresponding residues"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: To determine whether a protein sequence adopts a known three-dimensional structure fold relies on threading and fold recognition methods. The comparison emphasizes matching of secondary structures, which are most evolutionarily conserved. Therefore, this approach can identify structurally similar proteins even without detectable sequence similarity."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "Because threading and fold recognition detect structural homologs ________ relying on sequence similarities, they have been shown to be _______ than PSI-BLAST in finding distant evolutionary relationships",
        "Options": [
            "a) without completely, far more sensitive",
            "b) completely, far more sensitive",
            "c) completely, less sensitive",
            "d) without completely, less sensitive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pairwise energy–based method was originally referred to as threading and the profile-based method was originally defined as fold recognition. However, the two terms are now often used interchangeably without distinction in the literature."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about threading and fold recognition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It assess the compatibility of an amino acid sequence with a known structure in a fold library",
            "b) If the protein fold to be predicted does not exist in the fold library, the method won’t necessarily fail",
            "c) If the protein fold to be predicted does not exist in the fold library, the method will fail",
            "d) Threading and fold recognition do not generate fully refined atomic models for the query sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The detailed procedure involves aligning the query sequence with each structural fold in a fold library. The alignment is performed essentially at the sequence profile level using dynamic programming or heuristic approaches. Local alignment is often adjusted to get lower energy and thus better fitting. The adjustment can be achieved using algorithms such as double-dynamic programming."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about 3D-PSSM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web-based program that employs the structural profile method to identify protein folds",
            "b) The profiles for each protein superfamily are constructed by combining multiple smaller profiles",
            "c) A protein structural superfamily doesn’t have sequence-based PSI-BLAST profile",
            "d) In initial steps, protein structures in a superfamily based on the SCOP classification are superimposed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: After the mentioned step, the last step is to calculate the energy terms of the raw model, which include pairwise residue interaction energy, solvation energy, and hydrophobic energy. Finally, the models are ranked based on the energy terms to find the lowest energy fold that corresponds to the structurally most compatible fold."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about Gen Threader?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web-based program that uses a hybrid of the profile and pairwise energy methods",
            "b) It is a web-based program that uses profile methods only",
            "c) It is a web-based program that uses pairwise energy methods only",
            "d) The initial step is quite dissimilar to 3D-PSSM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The profile contains scores that describe the propensity of each of the twenty amino acid residues to be at each profile position. The profile scores contain information for secondary structural types, the degree of solvent exposure, polarity, and hydrophobicity of the amino acids. To predict the structural fold of an unknown query sequence, the query sequence is first predicted for its secondary structure, solvent accessibility, and polarity."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "RNA structures can be experimentally determined using _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) X-ray crystallography techniques only",
            "b) NMR techniques only",
            "c) X-ray crystallography or NMR techniques",
            "d) Gel electrophoresis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: However, the two approaches are extremely time consuming and expensive. As a result, computational prediction has become an attractive alternative. Option Gel electrophoresis, here, becomes irrelevant as it comes to the structure of RNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a form of RNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) mRNA",
            "b) tRNA",
            "c) qRNA",
            "d) rRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is known that RNA is a carrier of genetic information and exists in three main forms. They are messenger RNA (mRNA), ribosomal RNA (rRNA), and transfer RNA (tRNA). Their main roles are as follows: mRNA is responsible for directing protein synthesis; rRNA provides structural scaffolding within ribosomes; and tRNA serves as a carrier of amino acids for polypeptide synthesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a base of RNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thymine (T)",
            "b) Adenine (A)",
            "c) Cytosine (C)",
            "d) Guanine (G)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RNA is single stranded, although an RNA molecule can self-hybridize at certain regions to form partial double-stranded structures. Generally, mRNA is more or less linear and non-structured, whereas rRNA and tRNA can only function by forming particular secondary and tertiary structures."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "In addition to the canonical base pairing, there often exists non-canonical base pairing such as _________ and ________ base paring.",
        "Options": [
            "a) G, U",
            "b) G, C",
            "c) U, C",
            "d) A, C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Knowledge of the structures of these molecules is particularly important for understanding their functions. Difficulties in experimental determination of RNA structures make theoretical prediction a very desirable approach. In fact, computational-based analysis is the main tool in RNA-based drug design in pharmaceutical industry. In addition, knowledge of the secondary structures of rRNA is key for RNA-based phylogenetic analysis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "The ______ refers to a structure with two ends of a single-stranded region (loop) connecting a base-paired region (stem).",
        "Options": [
            "a) helical junctions",
            "b) hairpin loop",
            "c) bulge loop",
            "d) interior loop"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RNA structures can be described at three levels as in proteins: primary, secondary, and tertiary. The primary structure is the linear sequence of RNA, consisting of four bases, adenine (A), cytosine (C), guanine (G), and uracil (U). "
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "The __________ refers to two single-stranded regions on opposite strands connecting two adjacent base-paired segments.",
        "Options": [
            "a) hairpin loop",
            "b) interior loop",
            "c) pseudoknot loop",
            "d) helical junctions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The secondary structure refers to the planar representation that contains base-paired regions among single-stranded regions. The base pairing is mainly composed of traditional Watson–Crick base pairing, which is A–U and G–C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Ab initio approach makes structural predictions based on ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) a single RNA sequence",
            "b) comparing RNA sequences",
            "c) evolutionary basis",
            "d) pure phylogenetics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: One is based on the calculation of the minimum free energy of the stable structure derived from a single RNA sequence. This can be considered an ab initio approach. The second is a comparative approach which infers structures based on an evolutionary comparison of multiple related RNA sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "In ab initio approach, generally, when a base pairing is formed, the energy of the molecule is _________ because of attractive interactions between the two strands.",
        "Options": [
            "a) lowered",
            "b) increased",
            "c) multiplied",
            "d) kept stable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rationale behind this method is that the structure of an RNA molecule is solely determined by its sequence. Thus, algorithms can be designed to search for a stable RNA structure with the lowest free energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "The attractive interactions lead to _________ energy.",
        "Options": [
            "a) increased",
            "b) higher",
            "c) lower",
            "d) no change in"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Here, the algorithms can be designed to search for a stable RNA structure with the lowest free energy. Thus, to search for a most stable structure, ab initio programs are designed to search for a structure with the maximum number of base pairs."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "If the base pair is adjacent to loops or bulges, the neighboring loops and bulges tend to ___________ the base-pair formation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) have no change on",
            "b) decrease the energy",
            "c) stabilize",
            "d) destabilize"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: G–C base pairs are more stable than A–U base pairs, which are more stable than G–U base pairs. It is also known that base-pair formation is not an independent event."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "In dot matrix in ab initio methods, the diagonals _____________ to the main diagonal represent regions that can self hybridize.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel",
            "b) cutting in random fashion",
            "c) perpendicular",
            "d) adjacent parallel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The diagonals perpendicular to the main diagonal represent regions that can self hybridize to form double-stranded structure with traditional A–U and G–C base pairs. In reality, the pattern detection in a dot matrix is often obscured by high noise levels."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "In dynamic programming, in ab initio methods, the use of a dot plot can be effective in finding a ____ secondary structure in a ________ molecule.",
        "Options": [
            "a) multiple, large",
            "b) single, large",
            "c) single, small",
            "d) multiple, small"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To reduce the noise in the matrix is to select an appropriate window size of a minimum number of contiguous base matches. Normally, only a window size of four consecutive base matches is used. If the dot plot reveals more than one feasible structure, the lowest energy one is chosen."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "In dynamic programming, in ab initio methods, Often ________ base pairing and energy terms of the base pairing _____ incorporated into the scoring process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) G-C, are",
            "b) G–U, are not",
            "c) G–U, are also",
            "d) G-C, are not"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mostly, The use of a dot plot can be effective in finding a single secondary structure in a small Molecule. However, if a large molecule contains multiple secondary structure segments, choosing a combination that is energetically most stable among a large number of possibilities can be a daunting task."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "The dynamic programming method produces ____ structure with _____ score.",
        "Options": [
            "a) one, single best",
            "b) multiple, single best",
            "c) multiple, multiple",
            "d) single, multiple"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this approach, an RNA sequence is compared with itself. A scoring scheme is applied to fill the matrix with match scores based on Watson–Crick base complementarity."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "The problem of dynamic programming to select one single structure can be complemented by adding a probability distribution function, known as the _________ which calculates a mathematical distribution of probable base pairs in thermodynamic equilibrium.",
        "Options": [
            "a) partition function",
            "b) division function",
            "c)  increment function",
            "d) fold function"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Although the traditional structure comprises of A–U and G–C base pairs, G-U base pairing is incorporated into the scoring process. A path with the maximal score within a scoring matrix after taking into account the entire sequence information represents the most probable secondary structure form. "
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct about MFOLD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It uses the dynamic programming only",
            "b) It uses the thermodynamic calculations only",
            "c) It uses the both dynamic programming and thermodynamic calculations as well",
            "d) It doesn’t take into account the themoststablility of the secondary structures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: However, this is potentially a drawback of this approach. In reality an RNA may exist in multiple alternative forms with near minimum energy but not necessarily the one with maximum base pairs."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Which of the following about the RNAFold is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It extends the sequence alignment to the vicinity of the optimal diagonals to calculate thermodynamic stability of alternative structures",
            "b) It incorporates a partition function",
            "c) It doesn’t necessarily use a partition function",
            "d) It aims to select a number of statistically most probable structures in one of its steps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This function helps to select a number of suboptimal structures within a certain energy range. The MFOLD and RNAFold are two well-known programs using the ab initio prediction method."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "___________ of covariation can be ___________ to the RNA structure and functions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Any lack, deleterious",
            "b) Any lack, benign",
            "c) Any abundance, deleterious",
            "d) Any inadequacy, advantageous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Because of the much larger number of secondary structures to be computed, a more simplified energy rule has to be used to increase computational speed. Thus, the prediction results are not always guaranteed to be better than those predicted by Mfold."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "An aspect of the comparative method is to select a __________ structure through consensus drawing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) relatively distinct",
            "b) remote",
            "c) common",
            "d) least abundant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The comparative approach uses multiple evolutionarily related RNA sequences to infer a consensus structure. This approach is based on the assumption that RNA sequences that deem to be homologous fold into the same secondary structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "The type of algorithm that requires predefined alignment, requires the user to provide _______ alignment as input.",
        "Options": [
            "a) not necessarily an alignment",
            "b) multiple only",
            "c) pairwise or multiple",
            "d) pair wise only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is known that RNA functional motifs are structurally conserved. To maintain the secondary structures while the homologous sequences evolve, a mutation occurring in one position that is responsible for base pairing should be compensated for by a mutation in the corresponding base-pairing position so to maintain base pairing and the stability of the secondary structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "The type of algorithm that _____ predefined alignment is ______ for reasonably conserved sequences.",
        "Options": [
            "a) doesn’t require, more successful",
            "b) requires, less successful",
            "c) doesn’t require, relatively successful",
            "d) requires, relatively successful"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Based on this rule, algorithms can be written to search for the covariation patterns after a set of homologous RNA sequences are properly aligned. The detected correlated substitutions help to determine conserved base pairing in a secondary structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "The predefined alignment requiring method also depends on the quality of the input alignment. If there ___ errors in the alignment, covariation signals ____ detected.",
        "Options": [
            "a) are, will be",
            "b) are, will not be",
            "c) are not, will not be",
            "d) are not, possibly will not be"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Predicting secondary structures for each individual sequence may produce errors, by comparing all predicted structures of a group of aligned RNA sequences and drawing a consensus. Hence, the commonly adopted structure can be selected; many other possible structures can be eliminated in the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about the RNAalifold?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic programming is not involved",
            "b) Minimum free energy method is not used",
            "c) Only minimum free energy is used",
            "d) Covariation information is taken into consideration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The comparative-based algorithms can be further divided as mentioned. One requires predefined alignment and the other does not."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "If prediction accuracy can be represented using a ______ the ______ programs score roughly 20% to 60% depending on the length of the sequences.",
        "Options": [
            "a) multiple parameter, ab initio–based",
            "b) single parameter, ab initio–based",
            "c) multiple parameter, comparative–based",
            "d) single parameter, comparative–based"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The availability of recently solved crystal structures of the entire ribosome provides a wealth of structural details relating to diverse types of RNA molecules. The high resolution structural information can then be used as a benchmark for evaluating state-of-the-art RNA structure prediction programs in all categories."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "For _________ RNA sequences, such as tRNA, some programs may be able to produce _________% accuracy.",
        "Options": [
            "a) small, 70",
            "b) small, 40",
            "c) large, 90",
            "d) large, 75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As mentioned, the scores depend on the length of the sequences. Generally speaking, the programs perform better for shorter RNA sequences than for longer ones."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "The pre-alignment independent programs fare __________ for predicting long sequences.",
        "Options": [
            "a) slight better",
            "b) much better",
            "c) a bit worse",
            "d) much worse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The number of the percentage may vary but the qualitative idea is that for small RNA sequences, some programs may produce better accuracy. The major limitation for performance gains of this category appears to be dependence on energy parameters alone, which may not be sufficient to distinguish different structural possibilities of the same molecule."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "In comparative approach to RNA structure prediction, Dynalign is a ________ program.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Windows based",
            "b) Fedora",
            "c) UNIX",
            "d) iOS based"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For small RNA sequences such as tRNA, both subtypes can achieve very high accuracy (up to 100%). This illustrates that the comparative approach is consistently more accurate than the ab initio one."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "In comparative approach to RNA structure prediction, in Dynalign program–by comparing _________ from each sequence, a ______ structure common to both sequences is selected that serves as the basis for sequence alignment.",
        "Options": [
            "a) multiple alternative structures, lowest energy",
            "b) single structure, lowest energy",
            "c) single structure, highest energy",
            "d) multiple alternative structures, highest energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The results depend on whether a program is pre-alignment dependent or not. Most of the superior performance comes from pre-alignment-dependent programs such as RNAalifold."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about the RNA structure prediction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Given the sequence, it provides an ab initio prediction of secondary structure",
            "b) From the many possible choices of complementary sequences that can potentially base-pair, the compatible sets that provide the highest energy molecules are chosen",
            "c) Structures with energies almost as stable as the most stable one may also be produced",
            "d) Regions whose predictions are the most reliable can be identified from such an analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Stable structures are the ones with least or relatively quite low energy. Sequence variations found in related sequences may also be used to predict which base pairs are likely to be found in each of the molecules. One variation of RNA structure prediction methods will predict a set of sequences that are able to form a particular structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "____ wobble pairs may be produced in these double-stranded regions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A/A",
            "b) A/U",
            "c) G/C",
            "d) G/U"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sequence positions that base-pair are found to vary at the same time during evolution of RNA molecules so that structural integrity is maintained. For example, if two positions G and C form a base pair in a given type of molecule, then sequences that have C and G reversed, or A and U or U and A at the corresponding positions, would be considered reasonable matches. "
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "In predicting RNA secondary structure, some simplifying assumptions are usually made, like the _____ structure is similar to the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) most likely, energetically most unstable structure",
            "b) most unlikely, energetically most stable structure",
            "c) most likely, energetically most stable structure",
            "d) least likely, energetically most stable structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RNA secondary structure is composed primarily of double-stranded RNA regions formed by folding the single-stranded molecule back on itself. To produce such double-stranded regions, a run of bases downstream in the RNA sequence must be complementary to another upstream run so that Watson–Crick base-pairing between the complementary nucleotides G/C and A/U (analogous to the G/C and A/T base pairs in DNA) can occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "The Second assumption in predicting RNA secondary structure is that the energy associated with any position in the structure is _____ influenced by local sequence and structure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) only",
            "b) not at all",
            "c) partially",
            "d) never"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As in DNA, the G/C base pairs contribute the greatest energetic stability to the molecule, with A/U base pairs contributing less stability than G/C, and G/U wobble base pairs contributing the least. From the RNA structures that have been solved, these base pairs and a number of additional ones have been identified."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "The third assumption in predicting RNA secondary structure is that the structure is assumed to be formed by _____ of the chain back on itself in a manner that ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) crossing, produces knots",
            "b) crossing, does not produce any knots",
            "c) folding, produces knots",
            "d) folding, does not produce any knots"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The assumption here is that the most predicted or likely structure has to be similar to the energetically most stable structure. The abundance is not taken into consideration in this."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "Martinez (1984) made a list of possible double-stranded regions, and these regions were then given weights in proportion to their equilibrium constants, calculated by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) the Boltzmann function [exp (-∆G/RT2)] ",
            "b) the Boltzmann function [exp (-∆G/RT)] ",
            "c) the Boltzmann function [exp (-∆G/RT -T)] ",
            "d) the Boltzmann function [exp (∆G/RT)]"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The energy associated with a particular base pair in a double-stranded region is assumed to be influenced only by the previous base pair and not by the base pairs farther down the double-stranded region or anywhere else in the structure. These energies can be reliably estimated by experimentation with small, synthetic RNA oligonucleotides recently improved to include sequence dependence."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about the prediction of RNA secondary structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Every base is first compared to every other base by a type of analysis very similar to the dot matrix analysis",
            "b) A row of matches in the RNA matrix indicates a succession of complementary nucleotides that can potentially form a double-stranded region",
            "c) A row of matches in the RNA matrix indicates a failure of complementary nucleotides that can potentially form a double-stranded region",
            "d) The sequence is listed across the top and down the side of the page, and G/C, A/U, and G/U base pairs are scored"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The energy of each predicted structure is estimated by the nearest- neighbor rule by summing the negative base-stacking energies for each pair of bases in double-stranded regions. By adding the estimated positive energies of destabilizing regions such as loops at the end of hairpins, bulges within hairpins, internal bulges, and other unpaired regions."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "______ regions in sequences, such as those in RNA that will form secondary structures, are an example of such context-free sequences.",
        "Options": [
            "a) non-interlocking",
            "b) non-Complementary",
            "c) complementary",
            "d) non-compatible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To evaluate all the different possible configurations and to find the most energetically favorable, several types of scoring matrices are used. The complementary regions are evaluated by a dynamic programming algorithm to predict the most energetically stable molecule. The method is similar to the dynamic programming method used for sequence alignment."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "Originally, the FOLD program of _____ predicted _____ having the minimum free energy.",
        "Options": [
            "a) M. Zuker, two structures",
            "b) M. Wunsch, two structures",
            "c) M. Zuker, only one",
            "d) M. Wunsch, only one"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: However, changes in a single nucleotide can result in drastic changes in the predicted structure. A later version, called MFOLD, has improved prediction of non-base paired interactions and predicts several structures having energies close to the minimum free energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "In the programs related to FOLD, the second region, the ________ region, is used to calculate the energy of the ________ structure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) included, most likely",
            "b) included, best",
            "c) excluded, least likely",
            "d) excluded, best"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It was so done to evaluate parts of a new scoring matrix in which the sequence is represented in two tandem copies on both the vertical and horizontal axes. The regions from i 1 to n and j 1 to n are used to calculate an energy V (i,j) for the best structure that includes an i, j base pair and is called the included region."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Three scores, Pnum (i), Hnum (i,j), and Ssum, have been derived to assist with a determination of the reliability of a secondary structure prediction for a particular base i or a base pair i,j. Which of the following is not a correct regarding Pnum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) is the total number of energy dots regardless of color in the i th row and i th column of the energy dot plot",
            "b) is the total number of energy dots considering the color in the ith row and ith column of the energy dot plot",
            "c) represents in an unfiltered dot plot",
            "d) represents the number of base pairs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A second region, the excluded region, is used to calculate the energy of the best structure that includes i, j but is not derived from the structure at i+1, j-1 After certain corrections are made, the difference between the included and excluded values is the most energetic structure that includes the base pair i, j."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Three scores, Pnum (i), Hnum (i,j), and Ssum, have been derived to assist with a determination of the reliability of a secondary structure prediction for a particular base i or a base pair i,j. Which of the following is not a correct regarding Hnum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) is the sum of Pnum(i) and Pnum(j) -1",
            "b) is the sum of Pnum(i) and Pnum(j) + 1",
            "c) is the total number of dots in the ith row and jth column",
            "d) represents the total number of base pairs with the ith or jth base in the predicted structures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All complementary base pairs can be sampled in a fashion to determine which are within a certain range of the optimal one. An energy dot plot is produced showing the locations of alternative base pairs that produce the most stable or suboptimally stable structures."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "Three scores, Pnum (i), Hnum (i,j), and Ssum, have been derived to assist with a determination of the reliability of a secondary structure prediction for a particular base i or a base pair i,j. Which of the following is not a correct regarding Ssum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) is also called as ss-count",
            "b) is the number of foldings in which base i is single-stranded divided by m, the number of folding",
            "c) is the number of foldings in which base i is single-stranded multiplied by m, the number of folding",
            "d) gives the probability that base i is single-stranded"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Parameter d provides a measure of similarity between two structures. When MFOLD is established on a suitable local host machine, the window is interactive, and clicking a part of the display will lead to program output of the corresponding structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "______ molecules can simply be identified based on their sequence similarity with already-known sequences.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Larger, less conserved",
            "b) Larger, highly conserved",
            "c) smaller, highly conserved",
            "d) shorter, highly conserved"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For smaller sequences with more sequence variation, this method does not work. A number of methods for finding small RNA genes have been described and are available on the Web. A major problem with these methods in searches of large genomes is that a small false positive rate becomes quite unacceptable because there are so many false positives to check out."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding RNA structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNA structure 4.6 is a Windows implementation of the Zuker algorithm",
            "b) It includes additional options for other folding algorithms and incorporation of experimental data",
            "c) The authors of RNA structure collaborate very closely with the Turner laboratory and keep the most up-to-date thermodynamic parameters",
            "d) The OligoWalk program cannot be used for siRNA design"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: One of the first methods used to find tRNA genes was to search for sequences that are self-complementary and can fold into a hairpin like the three found in tRNAs (Staden 1980). Through the regions of self-complimentarity it was first possible to find the tRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Vienna RNA Websuite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It introduced the Wuchty algorithm, developed applications of the McCaskill algorithm",
            "b) It also offers a wide variety of algorithms and functions",
            "c) The Wuchty algorithm generates a small but complete set of suboptimal structures",
            "d) The Wuchty algorithm computes some possible tertiary structures within a narrow free-energy range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A method for finding the RNA polymerase III transcriptional control regions of tRNA genes using a scoring matrix derived from known control regions, was derived. That is also very accurate. Finally, Lowe and Eddy (1997) have devised a search algorithm tRNAscan-SE that uses a combination of three methods to find tRNA genes in genomic sequences—tRNAscan, the Pavesi algorithm, and the COVELS program based on sequence covariance analysis (Eddy and Durbin 1994). This method is reportedly 99–100% accurate with an extremely low rate of false positives."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about the Sfold algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It uses a unique algorithm to aid in the design of siRNA",
            "b) The algorithm combines thermodynamic stabilities, calculations of target accessibility, and empirical rules",
            "c) The website offers specialized programs for the design of siRNA, antisense RNA, trans-cleaving RNA, and mRNA-microRNA interactions",
            "d) The website doesn’t offer programs for the design of a general program for statistically sampling suboptimal RNA structures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The model is not used to search genomic sequences directly. Instead, a list of candidate sequences is first found by searching for patterns that match the sequences in the model (Lowe and Eddy 1999)."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about the genome mapping?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It doesn’t lead to the understanding of a genome structure",
            "b) It involves identifying relative locations of genes",
            "c) It involves identifying traits",
            "d) It involves identifying mutations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first step to understanding a genome structure is through genome mapping, which is a process of identifying relative locations of genes, mutations or traits on a chromosome. A low-resolution approach to mapping genomes is to describe the order and relative distances of genetic markers on a chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "Genetic markers are ______ portions of a _______ whose inheritance patterns can be followed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) unidentifiable, genes",
            "b) unidentifiable, chromosome",
            "c) identifiable, chromosome",
            "d) identifiable, genes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For many eukaryotes, genetic markers represent morphologic phenotypes. In addition to genetic linkage maps, there are also other types of genome maps such as physical maps and cytologic maps, which describe genomes at different levels of resolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "One centiMorgan is defined as _________ percentage of the total recombination events.",
        "Options": [
            "a) one",
            "b) ten",
            "c) 0.1",
            "d) 0.01"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rationale behind genetic mapping is that the closer the two genetic markers are, the more likely it is that they are inherited together and are not separated in a genetic crossing event. The distance between the two genetic markers is measured in centiMorgans (cM), which is the frequency of recombination of genetic markers."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "Physical maps are maps of locations of identifiable landmarks on a genomic DNA _______ inheritance patterns.",
        "Options": [
            "a) remotely related to",
            "b) related to",
            "c) regardless of",
            "d) associated with"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: One centiMorgan is one percentage of the total recombination events when separation of the two genetic markers is observed in a genetic crossing experiment. One centiMorgan is approximately 1 Mb in humans and 0.5 Mb in Drosophila."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about cytologic maps?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They cannot be directly observed under microscope",
            "b) They refer to banding patterns",
            "c) They can be viewed on stained chromosomes",
            "d) They can be directly observed under microscope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The distance between genetic markers is measured directly as kilobases (Kb) or megabases (Mb). Because the distance is expressed in physical units, it is more accurate and reliable than centiMorgans used in genetic maps."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "Cytologic maps can be considered to be of _____ resolution and hence somewhat ______ physical maps.",
        "Options": [
            "a) very high, inaccurate",
            "b) very low, accurate",
            "c) very high, accurate",
            "d) very low, inaccurate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It uses a number of radio labeled probes to hybridize to a library of DNA clone fragments. By identifying overlapping clones probed by common probes, a relative order of the cloned fragments can be established."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "The _____ resolution genome map is the genomic DNA sequence that can be considered as a type of ______ map describing a genome at the single base-pair level.",
        "Options": [
            "a) highest, physical",
            "b) lowest, physical",
            "c) highest, cytological",
            "d) lowest, cytological"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cytological maps have quite low resolution, when compared to physical maps. They can be viewed under microscopes as well. "
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about DNA sequencing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is now routinely carried out using the Sanger method",
            "b) This doesn’t make use of DNA polymerases",
            "c) This involves the synthesis of DNA chains of varying length",
            "d) The DNA synthesis is stopped by adding dideoxynucleotides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: DNA polymerases are used to synthesize DNA chains. The dideoxynucleotides are labeled with fluorescent dyes, which terminate the DNA synthesis at positions containing all four bases, resulting in nested fragments that vary in length by a single base. When the labeled DNA is subjected to electrophoresis, the banding patterns in the gel reveal the DNA sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "The shotgun approach _______ sequences clones from _____ of cloned DNA.",
        "Options": [
            "a) randomly, one end",
            "b) randomly, both ends",
            "c) specifically, both ends",
            "d) specifically, one end"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This process is called base calling. Automated base calling may generate errors and human intervention is often required to correct the sequence calls."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "The hierarchical genome sequencing approach is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) entirely dissimilar to the shotgun approach",
            "b) dissimilar to the shotgun approach",
            "c) similar to the shotgun approach, but on a larger scale",
            "d) similar to the shotgun approach, but on a smaller scale"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are two major strategies for whole genome sequencing: the shotgun approach and the hierarchical approach. The shotgun approach generates a large number of sequenced DNA fragments. The number of random fragments has to be very large, so large that the DNA fragments overlap sufficiently to cover the entire genome."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "In hierarchical genome sequencing approach, based on the results of _______ mapping _______of the BAC clones on a chromosome can be determined.",
        "Options": [
            "a) physical, the locations and orders",
            "b) physical, only the locations",
            "c) cytological, only the locations",
            "d) physical, only the orders"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally, the genome has to be redundantly sequenced in such a way that the overall length of the fragments covers the entire genome multiple times. This is designed to minimize sequencing errors and ensure correct assembly of a contiguous sequence. Overlapping sequences with an overall length of six to ten times the genome size are normally obtained for this purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "The hierarchical approach is ____ and _____ than the shotgun approach because it involves an initial clone-based physical mapping step.",
        "Options": [
            "a) slower, less costly",
            "b) faster, more costly",
            "c) faster, less costly",
            "d) slower, more costly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In such mentioned cases, the remainder gap sequences can be obtained through extending sequences from regions of known genomic sequences using a more traditional PCR technique. That which requires the use of custom primers and performs genome walking in a stepwise fashion. This step of genome sequencing is also known as finishing, which is followed by computational assembly of all the sequence data into a final complete genome."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "When a sequence is generated from ____ ends of a single clone, the distance between the two opposing fragments of a clone is fixed to ________ meaning that they are always separated by a distance defined by a _____ length (normally 1,000 to 9,000 bases).",
        "Options": [
            "a) both, an uncertain range, clone",
            "b) one, an uncertain range, clone",
            "c) both, a certain range, clone",
            "d) both, a certain range, gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sequence errors can often be corrected by drawing a consensus from an alignment of multiple overlapped sequences. Bacterial vector sequences can be removed using filtering programs prior to assembly. To overcome the problem of sequence repeats, programs such as RepeatMasker can be used to detect and mask repeats. Additional constraints on the sequence reads can be applied to avoid miss-assembly caused by repeat sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about base calling and assembly programs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The first step toward genome assembly includes derive base calls",
            "b) The first step toward genome assembly includes assigning associated quality scores",
            "c) One of the steps is to assemble the sequence reads into contiguous sequences",
            "d) There is no identifying overlap between sequence fragments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A commonly used constraint to avoid errors caused by sequence repeats is the so called forward–reverse constraint. When the constraint is applied, even when one of the fragments has a perfect match with a repetitive element outside the range, it is not able to be moved to that location to cause miss-assembly."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Initial DNA sequencing reactions generate short sequence reads from DNA clones",
            "b) To assemble a whole genome sequence, these short fragments are joined to form larger fragments",
            "c) The average length of the reads is about 50 bases",
            "d) A number of overlapping contigs can be further merged to form scaffolds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: One of the steps includes identifying overlaps between sequence fragments, assigning the order of the fragments and deriving a consensus of an overall sequence. Assembling all shotgun fragments into a full genome is a computationally very challenging step. There are a variety of programs available for processing the raw sequence data."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about Phred?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a UNIX program",
            "b) It doesn’t give a probability score in output",
            "c) It is used for base calling",
            "d) It uses a Fourier analysis to resolve fluorescence traces and predict actual peak locations of bases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The average length of the reads is about 500 bases. To assemble a whole genome sequence, these short fragments are joined to form larger fragments after removing overlaps. These longer, merged sequences are termed contigs, which are usually 5,000 to 10,000 bases long. A number of overlapping contigs can be further merged to form scaffolds (30,000–50,000 bases, also called supercontigs), which are unidirectionally oriented along a physical map of a chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about Phrap?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It aligns individual fragments in a pairwise fashion using the Smith–Waterman algorithm",
            "b) It doesn’t take input from Phred",
            "c) It is used for sequence assembly",
            "d) It is a UNIX program"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It also gives a probability score for each base call that may be attributable to error. The commonly accepted score threshold is twenty, which corresponds to a 1% chance of error. The higher the score, the better the quality of the sequence reads. If the score value falls below the threshold, human intervention is required."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about EULER?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is an assembly algorithm",
            "b) It uses a Eulerian Superpath approach, which is a polynomial algorithm",
            "c) In this approach, a sequence fragment is broken down to tuples of five nucleotides",
            "d) The tuples are distributed in a diagram with numerous nodes that are all interconnected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It takes Phred base-call files with quality scores as input and aligns individual fragments in a pairwise fashion using the Smith–Waterman algorithm. The base quality information is taken into account during the pairwise alignment. After all the pair wise sequence similarity is identified, the program performs assembly by progressively merging sequence pairs with decreasing similarity scores while removing overlapped regions. Consensus contigs are derived after joining all possible overlapped reads."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about ARACHNE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It accepts base calls with associated quality scores assigned by Phred as input",
            "b) It is a free UNIX program",
            "c) It is for the assembly of whole-genome shotgun reads",
            "d) It doesn’t involve heuristic approach"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is a web-based Program that helps detect contaminating bacterial vector sequences. It scans an input nucleotide sequence and compares it with a database of known vector sequences by using the BLAST program."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding gene annotation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The gene annotation of the human genome employs a combination of theoretical prediction and experimental verification",
            "b) Gene structures are first predicted by ab initio exon prediction programs",
            "c) The predicted genes are compared with experimentally determined cDNA and EST sequences",
            "d) The pairwise alignment programs are not involved"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Before the assembled sequence is deposited into a database, it has to be analyzed for useful biological features. The genome annotation process provides comments for the features."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding gene ontology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It exists because there is a need to standardize protein functional descriptions",
            "b) It uses a limited vocabulary to describe molecular functions",
            "c) Biological processes are not described though",
            "d) The cellular components are described using limited vocabulary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The predictions are verified by BLAST searches against a sequence database. The predicted genes are further compared with experimentally determined cDNA and EST sequences using the pairwise alignment programs such as GeneWise, Spidey, SIM4, and EST2 Genome.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding gene ontology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) There is standardization of the names and activities",
            "b) There is no standardization of associated pathways",
            "c) It provides consistency in describing overall protein functions",
            "d) It facilitates grouping of proteins of related functions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The controlled vocabulary is organized such that a protein function is linked to the cellular function through a hierarchy of descriptions with increasing specificity. The top of the hierarchy provides an overall picture of the functional class, whereas the lower level in the hierarchy specifies more precisely the functional role. This way, protein functionality can be defined in a standardized and unambiguous way."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding Automated Genome Annotation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It exists because of the need to develop fast and automated methods to annotate the genomic sequences",
            "b) The automated approach relies on homology detection",
            "c) The automated approach doesn’t rely on heuristic sequence similarity searching",
            "d) Automation brings speed in gene annotation process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A GO description of a protein provides three sets of information: biological process, cellular component, and molecular function, each of which uses a unique set of non-overlapping vocabularies. The standardization of the names, activities, and associated pathways provides consistency in describing overall protein functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding genome economy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a phenomenon of synthesizing more proteins from fewer genes",
            "b) This is a major strategy that eukaryotic organisms use to achieve a myriad of genotypic diversities only",
            "c) This is a major strategy that eukaryotic organisms use to achieve a myriad of phenotypic diversities",
            "d) There are numerous underlying genetic mechanisms to help account for genome economy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If a newly sequenced gene or its gene product has significant matches with a database sequence beyond a certain threshold, a transfer of functional assignment is taking place. In addition to sequence matching at the full length, detection of conserved motifs often offers additional functional clues."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding GeneQuiz?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web server for protein DNA annotation",
            "b) It is a web server for protein sequence annotation",
            "c) It compares a query sequence against databases using BLAST and FASTA to identify homologs with high similarities",
            "d) It performs domain analysis using the PROSITE and Blocks databases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Detecting remote homologs typically involves combined searches of protein motifs and domains and prediction for secondary and tertiary structures. The prediction can also be performed using structure-based approaches such as threading and fold recognition."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about comparative genomics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is comparison of whole genomes from different organisms",
            "b) It includes comparison of gene number, gene location, and gene content from these genomes",
            "c) It provides insights into the mechanism of genome evolution and gene transfer among genomes",
            "d) It doesn’t help to reveal the extent of conservation among genomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It helps to understand the pattern of acquisition of foreign genes through lateral gene transfer. It also helps to reveal the core set of genes common among different genomes, which should correspond to the genes that are crucial for survival. This knowledge can be potentially useful in future metabolic pathway engineering."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Whole Genome Alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This helps to reveal the presence of conserved functional elements",
            "b) It doesn’t help to understand sequence conservation between genomes",
            "c) It be accomplished through direct genome comparison or genome alignment",
            "d) The alignment at the genome level is fundamentally no different from the basic sequence alignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Regular alignment programs tend to be error prone and inefficient when dealing with long stretches of DNA containing hundreds or thousands of genes. Another challenge of genome alignment is effective visualization of alignment results. Because it is obviously difficult to sift through and make sense of the extremely large alignments, a graphical representation is a must for interpretation of the result."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about LAGAN?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for Limited Area Global Alignment of Nucleotides",
            "b) It is a web-based program designed for pairwise alignment of small fragments of genomes only",
            "c) It first finds anchors between two genomic sequences using an algorithm that identifies short, exactly matching words",
            "d) Regions that have high density of words are selected as anchors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is a web-based program designed for pairwise alignment of large genomes. The unique feature of this program is that it is able to take into account degeneracy of the genetic codes and is therefore able to handle more distantly related genomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "A minimal constitutes genome, which is a _____ set of genes required for maintaining a free living cellular organism.",
        "Options": [
            "a) maximum",
            "b) maximal",
            "c) highest number of set of",
            "d) minimal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Finding minimal genomes helps provide an understanding of genes constituting key metabolic pathways, which are critical for a cell’s survival. This analysis involves identification of orthologous genes shared between a number of divergent genomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Coregenes is a web-based program that determines a ________ set of genes based on comparison of ________ small genomes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) vast, four",
            "b) core, fifteen",
            "c) core, four",
            "d) vast, fifteen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The user supplies NCBI accession numbers for the genomes of interest. The program performs an iterative BLAST comparison to find orthologous genes by using one genome as a reference and another as a query. This pairwise comparison is performed for all four genomes. As a result, the common genes are compiled as a core set of genes from the genomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Lateral gene transfer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is also known as vertical gene transfer",
            "b) There is exchange of genetic materials between species",
            "c) It mainly occurs among prokaryotic organisms when foreign genes are acquired through mechanisms",
            "d) It is one of the examples is transformation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is defined as the exchange of genetic materials between species in a way that is incongruent with commonly accepted vertical evolutionary pathway. Examples are transformation (direct uptake of foreign DNA from environment), conjugation (gene uptake through mating behavior), and transduction (gene uptake mediated by infecting viruses). The transmission of genes between organisms can occur relatively recently or as a more ancient event."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "A way to discern lateral gene transfer is through phylogenetic analysis, referred to as an ‘among-genome’ approach, which can be used to discover __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) recent lateral gene transfer events but almost negligible ancient events",
            "b) recent lateral gene transfer events",
            "c) ancient lateral gene transfer events",
            "d) both recent and ancient lateral gene transfer events"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Abnormal groupings in phylogenetic trees are often interpreted as the possibility of lateral gene transfer events. There are some basic tools for identifying genomic regions that may be a result of lateral gene transfer events using the within-genome approach, namely, ACT, Swaap."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Gene Order Comparison?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When the order of a number of linked genes is conserved between genomes, it is called synteny",
            "b) Generally, gene order is much more conserved compared with gene sequences",
            "c) Generally, gene order is much less conserved compared with gene sequences",
            "d) It is in fact rarely observed among divergent species"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Single or oligonucleotide statistics, such as G–C composition, codon bias, and oligonucleotide frequencies are used. Unusual nucleotide statistics in certain genomic regions versus the rest of the genome may help to identify “foreign” genes in a genome. A commonly used parameter is GC skew ((G − C)/(G + C)), which is compositional bias for G in a DNA sequence and is a commonly used indicator for newly acquired genetic elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding expressed sequence tags (ESTs)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One of the high throughput approaches to genome-wide profiling of gene expression is sequencing ESTs",
            "b) They are short sequences obtained from cDNA clones",
            "c) They serve as short identifiers of full-length genes",
            "d) They are typically in the range of 800 to 900 nucleotides in length"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ESTs are typically in the range of 200 to 400 nucleotides in length obtained from either the 5’end or 3’end of cDNA inserts. Libraries of cDNA clones are prepared through reverse transcription of isolated mRNA populations by using oligo (dT) primers that hybridize with the poly (A) tail of mRNAs and ligation of the cDNAs to cloning vectors."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the drawbacks of expressed sequence tags (ESTs)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are often of lowquality because they are automatically generated without verification",
            "b) Many bases are ambiguously determined, represented by N’s",
            "c) Frame shift errors and artifactual stop codons are some common errors",
            "d) Despite of all the failures, the translation the sequences is smooth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The EST data are able to provide a rough estimate of genes that are actively expressed in a genome under a particular physiological condition. This is because the frequencies for particular ESTs reflect the abundance of the corresponding mRNA in a cell, which corresponds to the levels of gene expression at that condition. Another potential benefit of EST sampling is that, by randomly sequencing cDNA clones, it is possible to discover new genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding expressed sequence tags (ESTs)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) EST libraries can be easily generated from various cell lines, tissues, organs, and at various developmental stages",
            "b) Although individual ESTs are prone to error, an entire collection of ESTs contains valuable information",
            "c) Identification of cDNA clone is difficult",
            "d) ESTs can also facilitate the unique identification of a gene from a cDNA library"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Common errors also include frameshift errors and artifactual stop codons, resulting in failures of translating the sequences. In addition, there is often contamination by vector sequence, introns (fromunspliced RNAs), ribosomal RNA (rRNA), mitochondrial RNA, among others. ESTs represent only partial sequences of genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding EST Index Construction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The goal of the EST databases is to organize and consolidate the largely redundant EST data",
            "b) The process includes a preprocessing step that removes masks repeats",
            "c) There is no screening of vector contaminants",
            "d) The goal of the EST databases is to improve the quality of the sequence information so the data can be used to extract full-length cDNAs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A problem of ESTs is the presence of chimeric clones owing to cloning artifacts in library construction, in which more than one transcript is ligated in a clone resulting in the 5_ end of a sequence representing one gene and the 3’ end another gene. Another fundamental problem with EST profiling is that it predominantly represents highly expressed, abundant transcripts. Weakly expressed genes are hardly found in a EST sequencing survey."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding UniGene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is an NCBI EST cluster database",
            "b) Overlapping EST sequences are computationally processed to represent a single expressed gene",
            "c) Each cluster is a set of overlapping EST sequences",
            "d) The overlapping EST sequences are computationally processed to represent a set of expressed genes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A short tag can lead to a cDNA clone. Often, after consolidation of multiple EST sequences, a full-length cDNA can be derived. By searching a non-redundant EST collection, one can identify potential genes of interest."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding TIGR Gene Indices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is an EST database that the similar type of clustering method from UniGene",
            "b) It is an EST database that uses a different clustering method from UniGene",
            "c) It compiles data from dbEST, GenBank mRNA and genomic DNA data, and TIGR’s own sequence databased Sequences are only clustered if they are more than 95% identical for over a fortynucleotide region in pairwise comparisons",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rapid accumulation of EST sequences has prompted the establishment of public and private databases to archive the data. The mentioned database is regularly updated to reflect the progress of various EST sequencing projects. Each newly submitted EST sequence is subject to a database search. If a strong similarity to a known gene is found, it is annotated accordingly."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding SAGE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for Serial analysis of gene expression",
            "b) It is another high throughput, sequence-based approach for global gene expression profile analysis",
            "c) It stands for Squared analysis of gene expression",
            "d) Unlike EST sampling, SAGE is more quantitative in determining mRNA expression in a cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The process includes a preprocessing step that removes vector contaminants and masks repeats. Vecscreen, can be used to screen out bacterial vector sequences. This is followed by a clustering step that associates EST sequences with unique genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about a microarray?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a slide attached with a high-density array of immobilized DNA oligomers representing the entire genome of the species under study",
            "b) Array of immobilized DNA oligomers cannot be cDNAs",
            "c) Each oligomer is spotted on the slide and serves as a probe for binding to a unique complementary cDNA",
            "d) It is the most commonly used global gene expression profiling method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The entire cDNA population, labeled with fluorescent dyes or radioisotopes, is allowed to hybridize with the oligo probes on the chip. The amount of fluorescent or radiolabels at each spot position reflects the amount of corresponding mRNA in the cell. Using this analysis, patterns of global gene expression in a cell can be examined."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "which of the following is incorrect about Oligonucleotide Design in A microarray?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA microarrays are generated by fixing oligonucleotides onto a solid support",
            "b) The oligonucleotide array slide represents thousands of preselected genes from an organism",
            "c) The length of oligonucleotides is typically in the range of twenty-five to seventy bases long",
            "d) The oligonucleotides don’t react with cDNA samples"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The oligonucleotides are called probes that hybridize to labeled cDNA samples. Shorter oligo probes tend to be more specific in hybridization because they are better at discriminating perfect complementary sequences fromsequences containing mismatches. However, longer oligos can be more sensitive in binding cDNAs."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about Data Collection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The two-color microarray uses multiple dyes at times",
            "b) The most common type of microarray protocol is the two-color microarray",
            "c) The cDNAs are obtained by extracting total RNA or mRNA from tissues or cells and incorporating fluorescent dyes in the DNA strands during the cDNA biosynthesis",
            "d) The expression of genes is measured via the signals from cDNAs hybridizing with the specific oligonucleotide probes on the microarray"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The most common type of microarray protocol is the two-color microarray, which involves labeling one set of cDNA from an experimental condition with one dye (Cy5, red fluorescence) and another set of cDNA from a reference condition (the controls) with another dye (Cy3, green fluorescence). When the two differently labeled cDNA samples are mixed in equal quantity and allowed to hybridize with the DNA probes on the chips, gene expression patterns of both samples can be measured simultaneously."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about Classification of microarray data?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For microarray data, clustering analysis identifies coexpressed and coregulated genes",
            "b) For microarray data, clustering analysis identifies coexpressed but not coregulated genes",
            "c) For microarray data, clustering analysis identifies and coregulated but not coexpressed genes",
            "d) Genes within a category have more similarity in expression than genes from different categories."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For such tests, it is common to use a P-value cutoff of .05, which means a confidence level of 95% to distinguish the data groups. This level also corresponds to a gene expression level with two standard deviations from the mean of distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about Hierarchical Clustering?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The tree-branching pattern illustrates a higher degree of relationship between related gene groups",
            "b) It is not similar to the distance phylogenetic tree-building method",
            "c) It produces a treelike structure that represents a hierarchy or relative relatedness of data groups",
            "d) In the tree leaves, similar gene expression profiles are placed more closely together than dissimilar gene expression profiles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When genes are co-regulated, they normally reflect related functionality. Through gene clustering, functions of previously uncharacterized genes may be discovered. Clustering methods include hierarchical clustering and partitioning clustering (e.g., k-means, self-organizing maps [SOMs])."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about k-Means Clustering?",
        "Options": [
            "a) k-means clustering produces a dendrogram",
            "b) It classifies data through a single step partition",
            "c) It is a divisive approach",
            "d) In this method, data are partitioned into k-clusters, which are prespecified at the outset"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Similarly, an unsupervised analysis does not assume predefined categories, but identifies data categories according to actual similarity patterns. The unsupervised analysis is also called clustering, which is to group patterns into clusters of genes with correlated profiles."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about Self-Organizing Maps?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clustering by SOMs is in principle similar to the k-means method",
            "b) It doesn’t involve neural networks",
            "c) The data points are initially assigned to the nodes at random",
            "d) It starts by defining a number of nodes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A hierarchical clustering method is in principle similar to the distance phylogenetic tree-building method. When genes with similar expression profiles are grouped in such a way, functions for unknown genes can often be inferred. Hierarchical clustering uses the agglomerative approach that works in much the same way as the UPGMA method, in which the most similar data pairs are joined first to form a cluster."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about SAGE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This approach is much more efficient than the EST analysis",
            "b) This approach is quite less efficient than the EST analysis",
            "c) It uses a short nucleotide tag to define a gene transcript",
            "d) It allows sequencing of multiple tags in a single clone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If an average clone has a size of 700 bp, it can contain up to 50 sequence tags (15 bp each), which means that the SAGE method can be at least fifty times more efficient than the brute force EST sequencing and counting. Therefore, the SAGE analysis has a better chance of detecting weakly expressed genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about SAGE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sequencing is the most costly and time-consuming step",
            "b) Here, sequencing is economical but time-consuming step",
            "c) Sequencing is economical but time-reducing step",
            "d) It is difficult to know how many tags need to be sequenced to get a good coverage of the entire transcriptome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is generally determined on a case-by-case basis. As a rule of thumb, 10,000 clones representing approximately 500,000 tags from each sample are sequenced. The scale and cost of the sequencing required for SAGE analysis are prohibitive for most laboratories. Only large sequencing centers can afford to carry out SAGE analysis routinely."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about the drawbacks of SAGE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One or two sequencing errors in the tag sequence can lead to ambiguous or erroneous tag identification",
            "b) Correctly sequenced SAGE tag sometimes may correspond to several genes or no gene at all",
            "c) Correctly sequenced SAGE tag always corresponds to several genes",
            "d) The drawback with this approach is the sensitivity to sequencing errors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To improve the sensitivity and specificity of SAGE detection, the lengths of the tags need to be increased for the technique. There are some comprehensive software tools for SAGE analysis viz. SAGEmap, SAGExProfiler."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about SAGE Genie?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is an NCBI web-based program",
            "b) It allows matching of experimentally obtained SAGE tags to known genes",
            "c) It provides an interface for visualizing human gene expression",
            "d) It doesn’t filter out linker sequences from experimentally obtained SAGE tags"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Given a cDNA sequence, one can search SAGE libraries for possible SAGE tags and perform “virtual” Northern blots that indicate the relative abundance of a tag in a SAGE library. Each output is hyperlinked to a particular UniGene entry with sequence annotation."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an incorrect statement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SAGE and DNA microarrays are both high throughput techniques that determine global mRNA expression levels",
            "b) Studies have indicated that the gene expression measurements from these methods are highly inconsistent with each other",
            "c) SAGE does not require prior knowledge of the transcript sequence",
            "d) DNA microarray experiments can only detect the genes spotted on the microarray"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is a web-based program that allows a “virtual subtraction” of an expression profile of one library (e.g., normal tissue) from another (e.g., diseased tissue). Comparison of the two libraries can provide information about overexpressed or silenced genes in normal versus diseased tissues."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an incorrect statement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collecting a SAGE library is very labor intensive and expensive",
            "b) Collecting a SAGE library is quite economical",
            "c) SAGE is not suitable for rapid screening of cells",
            "d) Gene identification from SAGE data is also more cumbersome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It has a filtering function that filters out linker sequences from experimentally obtained SAGE tags and allows expression pattern comparison between normal and diseased human tissues. The data output can be presented using subprograms such as the Anatomic Viewer, Digital Northern, and Digital Gene Expression Display."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding 2D-Page?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for Two-dimensional polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis",
            "b) It separates proteins by charge only",
            "c) The gel is run in one direction in a pH gradient under a non-denaturing condition",
            "d) It works to separate proteins by isoelectric points (pI)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Further characterization involves determination of amino acid composition, peptide mass fingerprints, and sequences using mass spectrometry (MS). Finally, database searching is needed for protein identification."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding 2D-Page?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Not all proteins can be separated by this method or stained properly",
            "b) The stained gel can be scanned and digitized for image analysis",
            "c) Membrane proteins are largely hydrophilic and readily solubilized",
            "d) One of the challenges of this technique is the separation of membrane proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is a high-resolution technique that separates proteins by charge and mass. It works to separate proteins by isoelectric points (pI) and then in an orthogonal dimension under a denaturing condition to separate proteins by molecular weights (MW). This is followed by staining, usually silver staining, which is very sensitive, to reveal the position of all proteins. The result is a two-dimensional gel map; each spot on the map corresponds to a single protein being expressed."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding Mass Spectrometry Protein Identification?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The proteolysis doesn’t generate a pattern according to molecular weight",
            "b) Proteins can be identified and characterized using MS",
            "c) The proteins from a two dimensional gel system are first digested in situ with a protease",
            "d) Protein spots of interest are excised from the two-dimensional gel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Membrane proteins are largely hydrophobic and not readily solublized. They tend to aggregate in the aqueous medium of a two-dimensional gel. To overcome this problem, membrane proteins can be fractionated using specialized protocols and then electrophoresed using optimized buffers containing zwitterionic detergents. Subfractionation can be carried out to separate nuclear, cytosol, cytoskeletal, and other subcellular fractions to boost the concentrations of rare proteins and to reveal subcellular localizations of the proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding the Protein Identification through Database Searching?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MS characterization of proteins is highly dependent on bioinformatic analysis",
            "b) Bioinformatics programs can be used to search for the identity of a protein in a database of theoretically digested proteins",
            "c) Even in reality, the protease digestion is always perfect in MS",
            "d) The purpose of the database search is to find exact or nearly exact matches"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This requires the software programs to be able to stretch or maneuver one of the gels relative to the other to find a common geometry. When the reference spots are aligned properly, the rest of the spots can be subsequently compared automatically."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding Mascot and ProFound?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ProFound is a web server with a set of interconnected programs",
            "b) ProFound searches a protein sequence database using MS fingerprinting information",
            "c) Bayesian algorithm is not involved in ProFound",
            "d) Mascot is a web server that identifies proteins based on peptide mass fingerprints, sequence entries, or raw MS/MS data from one or more peptides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The proteolysis generates a unique pattern of peptide fragments of various MWs, which is termed a peptide fingerprint. The fragments can be analyzed with MS, a high-resolution technique for determining molecular masses. Currently, electro-spray ionization MS and matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization (MALDI) MS are commonly used."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding Differential In-Gel Electrophoresis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proteins are mixed together before electrophoresis on a two-dimensional gel",
            "b) Differentially expressed proteins in both conditions can’t be visualized in the same gel",
            "c) In this, Differences in protein expression patterns can be detected in a similar way as in fluorescent-labeled DNA microarrays",
            "d) Proteins from experimental and control samples are labeled with differently colored fluorescent dyes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In MALDI-MS, for example, the peptides are charged with positive ions and forced through an analyzing tube with a magnetic field. Peptides are analyzed in the gas phase. Because smaller peptides are deflected more than larger ones in a magnetic field, the peptide fragments can be separated according to molecular mass and charges. A detector generates a spectrum that displays ion intensity as a function of the mass-to-charge ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a wrong statement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To assume biological activity, many nascent polypeptides have to be covalently modified before or after the folding process",
            "b) In eukaryotic cells most modifications take place in the endoplasmic reticulum and the Golgi apparatus",
            "c) The modifications in eukaryotic cells include proteolytic cleavage; formation of disulfide bonds; addition of phosphoryl, methyl, acetyl, or other groups onto certain amino acid residues",
            "d) The modifications in eukaryotic cells doesn’t include attachment of oligosaccharides or prosthetic groups to create mature proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Post translational modifications have a great impact on protein function by altering the size, hydrophobicity and overall conformation of the proteins. The modifications can directly influence protein–protein interactions and distribution of proteins to different subcellular locations."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a wrong about AutoMotif?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web server predicting protein sequence motifs",
            "b) It doesn’t use SVM approach",
            "c) In this process, the query sequence is chopped up into a number of overlapping fragments",
            "d) The overlapping fragments from are query sequence are fed into different kernels (similar to nodes)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hyperplane, which has been trained to recognize known protein sequence motifs, separates the kernels into different classes. Each separation is compared with known motif classes, most of which are related to posttranslational modification. The best match with a known class defines the functional motif."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "In a statistical learning process called support vector machine (SVM), a hyperplane is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) a linear or nonlinear mathematical function",
            "b) nonlinear mathematical function",
            "c) linear mathematical function",
            "d) exponential mathematical function"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This often leads to many false-positive identifications. One such example is the known consensus motif for protein phosphorylation, [ST]-x-[RK]. Such a short motif can be found multiple times in almost every protein sequence. Most of the predictions based on this sequence motif alone are likely to be wrong, producing very high rates of false-positives."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "A disulfide bridge is a unique type of _____ modification in which _____ bonds are formed between cysteine residues.",
        "Options": [
            "a) posttranslational, covalent",
            "b) translational, covalent",
            "c) translational, ionic",
            "d) posttranslational, ionic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is a data classification method similar to the linear or quadratic discriminant analysis. In this method, the data are projected in a three-dimensional space or even a multidimensional space."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Accurate prediction of _____ bonds may also help to predict the _____ dimensional structure of the protein of interest.",
        "Options": [
            "a) nitrogen, two",
            "b) nitrogen, three",
            "c) disulfide, three",
            "d) oxygen, three"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is used to best separate true signals from noise. The algorithm has more environmental variables included that may be required for the enzyme modification. After training the algorithm with sufficient structural features, it is able to correctly recognize many posttranslational modification patterns."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an incorrect statement about the terminologies related to protein sorting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Subcellular localization is an integral part of protein functionality",
            "b) Many proteins exhibit functions only after being transported to certain compartments of the cell",
            "c) All the proteins exhibit functions after being transported to certain compartments of the cell",
            "d) Protein sorting is also known as protein targeting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The study of the mechanism of protein trafficking and subcellular localization is the field of protein sorting, which has become one of the central themes in modern cell biology. Identifying protein subcellular localization is an important aspect of functional annotation, because knowing the cellular localization of a protein often helps to narrow down its putative functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "The signal sequences have a _________ consensus but contain some specific features. They all have a ______ core region preceded by one or more positively charged residues.",
        "Options": [
            "a) weak, hydrophilic",
            "b) weak, hydrophobic",
            "c) strong, hydrophilic",
            "d) strong, hydrophilic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: These compartments include chloroplasts, mitochondria, the nucleus, and peroxisomes. To carry out protein translocation, unique peptide signals have to be present in the nascent proteins, which function as “zip codes” that direct the proteins to each of these compartments."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "The signal sequences are typically _______ residues long, rich in _____ charged residues such as arginines as well as hydroxyl residues such as serines and threonines, but devoid of ______ charged residues.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 28 to 80, positively, negatively",
            "b) 300 to 800, negatively, positively",
            "c) 28 to 80, negatively, positively",
            "d) 300 to 500, positively, negatively"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is an example of posttranslational modification. Even in prokaryotes, proteins can be targeted to the inner or outer membranes, the periplasmic space between these membranes, or the extracellular space. The sorting of these proteins is similar to that in eukaryotes and relies on the presence of signal peptides."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "Chloroplast localization signals are also located in the __________ terminus and are about 25 to 100 residues in length, containing very few _______ charged residues but many hydroxylated residues such as serine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) N, negatively",
            "b) C, negatively",
            "c) C, positively",
            "d) N, positively"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: However, the length and sequence of the signal sequences vary tremendously. Peptides targeting mitochondria, for example, are located in the N-terminal region."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an incorrect statement about SignalP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It only uses neural networks",
            "b) It only uses HMMs",
            "c) It is a web-based program that predicts subcellular localization signals",
            "d) It uses both neural networks and HMMs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: They have the tendency to form amphiphilic α-helices. These targeting sequences are cleaved once the precursor proteins are inside the mitochondria."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not one of the training sets in SignalP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prokaryotes",
            "b) Eukaryotes",
            "c) Gram-positive bacteria",
            "d) Gram-negative bacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chloroplast localization signals are also called transit Peptides. An interesting feature of the proteins targeted for the chloroplasts is that the transit signals are bipartite."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the classic yeast two-hybrid method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is used for the detection of Protein interactions",
            "b) Method that relies on the interaction of “bait” and “prey” proteins in molecular constructs in yeast",
            "c) DNA-binding domain and a trans-activation domain don’t necessarily interact",
            "d) In this strategy, a two-domain transcriptional activator is employed as a helper for determining protein–protein interactions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The two domains which are a DNA-binding domain and a trans-activation domain normally interact to activate transcription. However, molecular constructs are made such that each of the two domains is covalently attached to each of the two candidate proteins (bait and prey)."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "If the bait and prey proteins _______ they bring the DNA-binding and trans-activation domains in such close proximity that they reconstitute the function of the transcription activator, turning ____ the expression of a reporter gene as a result. Which of the following is not the correct pair of blanks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) physically interact, on",
            "b) do not interact, on",
            "c) do not interact, off",
            "d) stop interacting, off"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Molecular constructs are made such that each of the two domains is covalently attached to each of the two candidate proteins. If the two candidate proteins do not interact, the reporter gene expression remains switched off."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the classic yeast two-hybrid method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protein–protein interaction networks of yeast and a small number of other species have been subsequently determined using this method",
            "b) This technique is a high throughput approach",
            "c) Each bait and prey construct has to be prepared individually to map interactions between all proteins",
            "d) It has been systematically applied to study interactions at the whole proteome level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This technique is essentially a low throughput approach. A major flaw in this method is that it is an indirect approach to probe protein–protein interaction and has a tendency to generate false positives (spurious interactions) and false negatives (undetected interactions). It has been estimated from proteome-wide characterizations that the rate of false positives can be as high as 50%."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the Predicting Interactions Based on Domain Fusion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is based on gene fusion events",
            "b) Predicting protein–protein interactions is called the “Rosetta stone” method",
            "c) A fused protein often reveals relationships between its domain components",
            "d) A fused protein doesn’t necessarily reveal about the relationships between its domain components"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The purified proteins are then analyzed by gel electrophoresis followed by MS for identification of the interacting components. The protein microarray systems mentioned above also provide a high throughput alternative for studying protein–protein interactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "The justification behind Rosetta stone method is that when two domains are fused in a single protein, they have to be in _______ proximity to perform a common function.",
        "Options": [
            "a) distant",
            "b) close",
            "c) extremely distant",
            "d) extremely close"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The rationale goes like this: if A and B exist as interacting domains in a fusion protein in one proteome, the gene encoding the protein is a fusion gene. Their homologous gene sequences A and B existing separately in another genome most likely encode proteins interacting to perform a common function. Conversely, if ancestral genes A and B encode interacting proteins, they may have a tendency to be fused together in other genomes during evolution to enhance their effectiveness."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the predicting Interactions Based on Phylogenetic Information?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proteins do not operate as a complex",
            "b) This method detects the co-presence or co-absence of orthologs across a number of genomes",
            "c) Protein interactions can be predicted using phylogenetic profiles",
            "d) Phylogenetic profile are defined as patterns of gene pairs that are concurrently present or absent across genomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this method, by studying gene/protein fusion events, protein–protein interactions can be predicted. This prediction rule has been proven to be rather reliable and since successfully applied to a large number of proteins from both prokaryote and eukaryotes."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the STRING?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Search Tool for the Retrieval of Interacting Genes/Proteins",
            "b) Functional associations include only the direct protein-protein interactions",
            "c) It is based on combined evidence of gene linkage, gene fusion and phylogenetic profiles",
            "d) It is a web server that predicts gene and protein functional associations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the two domains are located in two different proteins, to preserve the same functionality, their close proximity and interaction have to be preserved as well. Therefore, by studying gene/protein fusion events, protein–protein interactions can be predicted."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "The descriptions of morphological traits are often _____ which are due to _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) ambiguous, multiple genetic factors",
            "b) lucid, more than one genetic factors",
            "c) clear, multiple genetic factors",
            "d) ambiguous, one or two genetic factors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tree branching patterns representing the evolutionary divergence are referred to as phylogeny. Phylogenetics can be studied in various ways. It is often studied using fossil records, which contain morphological information about ancestors of current species and the timeline of divergence."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding the advantages of Molecular data for phylogenetics study?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are more numerous than fossil records",
            "b) They are easier to obtain as compared to fossil records",
            "c) Sampling bias is involved",
            "d) More clear-cut and robust phylogenetic trees can be constructed with the molecular data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thus, using fossil records to determine phylogenetic relationships can often be biased. For microorganisms, fossils are essentially nonexistent, which makes it impossible to study phylogeny with this approach."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "To use molecular data to reconstruct evolutionary history requires making a number of reasonable assumptions. Which of the following is incorrect about it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The molecular sequences used in phylogenetic construction are homologous",
            "b) The molecular sequences used in phylogenetic construction share a common origin",
            "c) Phylogenetic divergence cannot be bifurcating",
            "d) Parent branch splits into two daughter branches at any given point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There is no sampling bias involved, which helps to mend the gaps in real fossil records. Therefore, they have become favorite and sometimes the only information available for researchers to reconstruct evolutionary history. The advent of the genomic era with tremendous amounts of molecular sequence data has led to the rapid development of molecular phylogenetics."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding the terminologies of phylogenetics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The connecting point where two adjacent branches join is called a node",
            "b) Node represents an inferred ancestor of extant taxa",
            "c) At the tips of the branches are long lost species or sequences",
            "d) The lines in the tree are called branches"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Here, option “Phylogenetic divergence cannot be bifurcating” and “Parent branch splits into two daughter branches at any given point” contradict. Another assumption in phylogenetics is that each position in a sequence evolved independently. The variability among sequences is sufficiently informative for constructing unambiguous phylogenetic trees."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding the terminologies of phylogenetics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A group of taxa descended from a single common ancestor is defined as a clade or monophyletic group",
            "b) In a monophyletic group, two taxa share a unique common ancestor shared by other taxa as well",
            "c) Lineage is often synonymous with a tree branch leading to a defined monophyletic group",
            "d) When a number of taxa share more than one closest common ancestors, they do not fit the definition of a clade. In this case, they are referred to as paraphyletic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Multifurcation is normally a result of insufficient evidence to fully resolve the tree or a result of an evolutionary process known as radiation. Sometimes, a branch point on a phylogenetic tree may have more than two descendents, resulting in a multifurcating node."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding the terminologies of phylogenetics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The branching pattern in a tree is called tree topology",
            "b) When all branches bifurcate on a phylogenetic tree, it is referred to as dichotomy",
            "c) In case of dichotomy, each ancestor divides and gives rise to multiple descendants",
            "d) An unrooted phylogenetic tree does not assume knowledge of a common ancestor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: At the tips of the branches are present-day species or sequences known as taxa (the singular form is taxon) or operational taxonomic units. The bifurcating point at the very bottom of the tree is the root node, which represents the common ancestor of all members of the tree."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Evolution of a particular sequence _______ correlate with the evolutionary path of the species.",
        "Options": [
            "a) does not",
            "b) always",
            "c) does not necessarily",
            "d) invariably"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: One of the objectives of building phylogenetic trees based on molecular sequences is to reconstruct the evolutionary history of the species involved. However, strictly speaking, a gene phylogeny (phylogeny inferred from a gene or protein sequence) only describes the evolution of that particular gene or encoded protein."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "The species evolution is the ______ of evolution by _____ in a genome.",
        "Options": [
            "a) combined result, multiple genes",
            "b) result, single genes",
            "c) result, sole genes",
            "d) distinct results, single gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sequence may evolve more or less rapidly than other genes in the genome or may have a different evolutionary history from the rest of the genome owing to horizontal gene transfer events. Thus, the evolution of a particular sequence does not necessarily correlate with the evolutionary path of the species."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "It is often desirable to define the root of a tree. There are two ways to define the root of a tree. One is to use an outgroup, which ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) is a sequence that is homologous to the sequences under consideration",
            "b) is separated from those sequences at an early evolutionary time",
            "c) is generally determined from independent sources of information",
            "d) is generally determined from similar or related sources of information"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a species tree, the branching point at an internal node represents the speciation event whereas, in a gene tree, the internal node indicates a gene duplication event. The two events may or may not coincide. "
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect statement about the Kimura model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a model to correct evolutionary distances and  is a more sophisticated model",
            "b) In this, the mutation rates for transitions and transversion are assumed to be different",
            "c) According to this model, occur more frequently than transversions",
            "d) According to this model, transversions occur more frequently than transitions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To obtain a species phylogeny, phylogenetic trees from a variety of gene families need to be constructed to give an overall assessment of the species evolution. Phylogenetic trees drawn as cladograms (top) and phylograms (bottom)."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect statement about Choosing Substitution Models?",
        "Options": [
            "a) There is one substitution at a particular position, in divergent sequences",
            "b) The evolutionary divergence is beyond the ability of the statistical models to correct",
            "c) The statistical models used to correct homoplasy are called substitution models or evolutionary models",
            "d) For constructing DNA phylogenies, there are nucleotide substitution models available"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Here, the option “is generally determined from independent sources of information” and contradict and it can be explained as follows. For example, a bird sequence can be used as a root for the phylogenetic analysis of mammals based on multiple lines of evidence that indicate that birds branched off prior to all mammalian taxa in the in group. Outgroups are required to be distinct from the in group sequences, but not too distant from the in group."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an incorrect statement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In a phylogram, the branch lengths represent the amount of evolutionary divergence",
            "b) Trees like cladogram are said to be scaled",
            "c) The scaled trees have the advantage of showing both the evolutionary relationships and information about the relative divergence time of the branches",
            "d) In a cladogram, the external taxa line up neatly in a row or column"
        ],
        "Answer": "nswer: b\nExplanation: In a cladogram, the external taxa line up neatly in a row or column. Their branch lengths are not proportional to the number of evolutionary changes and thus have no phylogenetic meaning. In such an unscaled tree, only the topology of the tree matters, which shows the relative ordering of the taxa."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an incorrect statement about Newick Format?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It was designed to provide information of tree topology to computer programs without having to draw the tree itself",
            "b) In this format, trees are represented by taxa excluded in nested parentheses",
            "c) In this linear representation, each internal node is represented by a pair of parentheses",
            "d) For a tree with scaled branch lengths, the branch lengths in arbitrary units are placed immediately after the name of the taxon separated by a colon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Trees are represented by taxa included in nested parentheses. In this linear representation, each internal node is represented by a pair of parentheses that enclose all member of a monophyletic group separated by a comma."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "The number of rooted trees (NR) for n taxa is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) NR = (2n− 3)!/2n+2 (n− 2)!",
            "b) NR = (2n− 3)!/2n (n− 2)!",
            "c) NR = (2n− 3)!/2n−2 (n− 5)!",
            "d) NR = (2n− 3)!/2n−2 (n− 2)!"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Combining the nodes can be done either by strict consensus or by majority rule.\nIn a strict consensus tree, all conflicting nodes are collapsed into polytomies. In a consensus tree based on a majority rule, among the conflicting nodes, those that agree by more than 50% of the nodes are retained whereas the remaining nodes are collapsed into multifurcation."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "For unrooted trees, the number of unrooted tree topologies (NU) is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) NU = (2n− 5)!/2n−3(n− 5)!",
            "b) NU = (2n− 5)!/2n−3(n− 3)!",
            "c) NU = (2n− 5)!/2−2(n− 3)!",
            "d) NU = (2n− 5)!/2n(n− 3)!"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The number of potential tree topologies can be enormously large even with a moderate number of taxa. The increase of possible tree topologies follows an exponential function. In this formula, (2n−3)! Is a mathematical expression of factorial, which is the product of positive integers from 1 to 2n − 3. For example, 5! = 1 × 2 × 3 × 4 × 5 = 120."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect statement about Molecular Markers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For studying very closely related organisms, protein sequences are preferred",
            "b) The decision to use nucleotide or protein sequences depends on the purposes of the study",
            "c) For constructing molecular phylogenetic trees, one can use either nucleotide or protein sequence data",
            "d) The decision to use nucleotide or protein sequences depends on the properties of the sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The number of possible topologies increases extremely rapidly with the number of taxa. For six taxa, there are 105 unrooted trees and 945 rooted trees. If there are ten taxa, there can be 2,027,025 unrooted trees and 34,459,425 rooted ones."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "For studying the evolution of ________ divergent groups of organisms, one may choose either ______ nucleotide sequences, such as ribosomal RNA or protein sequences.",
        "Options": [
            "a) less widely, slowly evolving",
            "b) more widely, slowly evolving",
            "c) more widely, rapidly evolving",
            "d) less widely, rapidly evolving"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Because the number of rooted topologies is much larger than that for unrooted ones, the search for a true phylogenetic tree can be simplified by calculating the unrooted trees first. Once an optimal tree is found, rooting the tree can be performed by designating a number of taxa in the data set as an outgroup based on external information to produce a rooted tree."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "In many cases ______ sequences are preferable to ______ sequences because they are relatively ____ conserved.",
        "Options": [
            "a) protein, nucleotide, less",
            "b) nucleotide, protein, less",
            "c) protein, nucleotide, more",
            "d) nucleotide, protein, more"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The choice of molecular markers is an important matter because it can make a major difference in obtaining a correct tree. For studying very closely related organisms, nucleotide sequences, which evolve more rapidly than proteins, can be used. For example, for evolutionary analysis of different individuals within a population, noncoding regions of mitochondrial DNA are often used."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "In Jukes–Cantor Model to correct evolutionary distances, A formula for deriving evolutionary distances that include hidden changes is introduced by using a logarithmic function. It is ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) dAB = −(3/4) log[1 − (4/7)pAB] ",
            "b) dAB = −(3/4) ln[1 − (5/3)pAB] ",
            "c) dAB = −(3/4) log[1 − (4/3)pAB] ",
            "d) dAB = −(3/4) ln[1 − (4/3)pAB]"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the phylogenetic relationships to be delineated are at the deepest level, such as between bacteria and eukaryotes, using conserved protein sequences makes more sense than using nucleotide sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about distance based methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The computed evolutionary distances can be used to construct a matrix of distances between all individual pairs of taxa",
            "b) Clustering is the only method among the algorithms for the distance-based tree-building method",
            "c) The clustering-type algorithms compute a tree based on a distance matrix starting from the most similar sequence pairs",
            "d) Based on the pairwise distance scores in the matrix, a phylogenetic tree can be constructed for all the taxa involved"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The algorithms for the distance-based tree-building method can be subdivided into either clustering based or optimality based. These algorithms include an unweighted pair group method using arithmetic average (UPGMA) and neighbor joining. The optimality-based algorithms compare many alternative tree topologies and select one that has the best fit between estimated distances in the tree and the actual evolutionary distances."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about the Unweighted Pair Group Method Using Arithmetic Average?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The simplest clustering method is UPGMA, which builds a tree by a sequential clustering method",
            "b) Given a distance matrix, it starts by grouping two taxa with the largest pairwise distance in the distance matrix",
            "c) The distances between this new composite taxon and all remaining taxa are calculated to create a reduced matrix",
            "d) The grouping process is repeated and another newly reduced matrix is created"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It starts by grouping two taxa with the smallest pairwise distance in the distance matrix. A node is placed at the midpoint or half distance between them. It then creates a reduced matrix by treating the new cluster as a single taxon."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Corrects for unequal evolutionary rates between sequences by using a conversion step. This conversion requires the calculations of “r-values” and “transformed r-values” using the following formula ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) dAB’ = dAB − 1/4 × (rA + rB)",
            "b) dAB’ = dAB − 1/2 × (rA + rB)",
            "c) dAB’ = dAB − 1/3 × (rA + rB)",
            "d) dAB’ = (dAB/3) − 1/2 × (rA + rB)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: However, real data rarely meet this assumption. Thus, UPGMA often produces erroneous tree topologies. However, owing to its fast speed of calculation, it has found extensive usage in clustering analysis of DNA microarray data."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "A generalized expression of the r-value is ri calculated based on the following formula _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) ri = ∑dij + dj2",
            "b) ri = ∑dij",
            "c) ri = ∑dij + di",
            "d) ri = ∑dij + dj"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since this molecular clock assumption is often not met in biological sequences, to build a more accurate phylogenetic trees, the neighbor joining (NJ) method can be used, which is somewhat similar to UPGMA in that it builds a tree by using stepwise reduced distance matrices. However, the NJ method does not assume the taxa to be equidistant from the root."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about the Optimality-Based Methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The clustering-based methods produce multiple trees as output",
            "b) Optimality-based methods select a tree that best fits the actual evolutionary distance matrix",
            "c) There is no criterion in judging how this tree is compared to other alternative trees",
            "d) Optimality-based methods have a well-defined algorithm to compare all possible tree topologies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: AB is the converted distance between A and B and dAB is the actual evolutionary distance between A and B. The value of rsub>A (or rB) is the sum of distances of A (or B) to all other taxa."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about the Fitch–Margoliash?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Method selects a best tree among all possible trees based on minimal deviation between the distances calculated in the overall branches in the tree and the distances in the original dataset",
            "b) It starts by randomly clustering two taxa in a node",
            "c) It starts by creating three equations to describe the distances",
            "d) The method searches for some specific tree topologies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: i and j are two different taxa. The r-values are needed to create a modified distance matrix. The transformed r-values (r ‘) are used to determine the distances of an individual taxon to the nearest node: r i2 = ri/ (n−2)."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect statement about Character-based methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are also called discrete methods",
            "b) They are based directly on the sequence characters rather than on pairwise distances",
            "c) They doesn’t count mutational events accumulated on the sequences",
            "d) They may avoid the loss of information when characters are converted to distances"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: They count mutational events accumulated on the sequences. This preservation of character information means that evolutionary dynamics of each character can be studied. Ancestral sequences can also be inferred. The two most popular character-based approaches are the maximum parsimony (MP) and maximum likelihood (ML) methods."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect statement about Maximum Parsimony Method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By cutting off the unnecessary variables, model development may become difficult, and there may be more chances of introducing inconsistencies, ambiguities, and redundancies, hence, the name Occam’s razor",
            "b) In dealing with problems that may have an infinite number of possible solutions, choosing the simplest model may help to ‘cut off’ those variables that are not really necessary to explain the phenomenon",
            "c) This method chooses a tree that has the fewest evolutionary changes or shortest overall branch lengths",
            "d) It is based on a principle related to a medieval philosophy called Occam’s razor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: The theory was formulated by William of Occam in the thirteenth century and states that the simplest explanation is probably the correct one. This is because the simplest explanation requires the fewest assumptions and the fewest leaps of logic."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect statement about Building Work of MP tree?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It works by searching for all possible tree topologies and reconstructing ancestral sequences that require the minimum number of changes to evolve to the current sequences",
            "b) Other than informative sites are non-informative, which are constant sites or sites that have changes occurring only once",
            "c) Informative sites are the ones that can often be explained by a unique tree topology",
            "d) Constant sites have the same state in all taxa and are quite useful in evaluating the various topologies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Constant sites have the same state in all taxa and are obviously useless in evaluating the various topologies. The sites that have changes occurring only once are not very useful either for constructing parsimony trees because they can be explained by multiple tree topologies. The non-informative sites are thus discarded in parsimony tree construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect statement about Tree-Searching Methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The choice of the first three taxa can be random",
            "b) Parsimony method examines all possible tree topologies to find the maximally parsimonious tree",
            "c) It starts by building a three taxa unrooted tree, for which only one topology is available",
            "d) This is different than exhaustive search method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The inference of an ancestral sequence is made by first going from the leaves to internal nodes and to the common root to determine all possible ancestral character states. Then it goes back from the common root to the leaves to assign ancestral sequences that require the minimum number of substitutions."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect statement about branch-and-bound?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It uses a shortcut to find an MP tree",
            "b) It establishes an upper limit (or upper bound) for the number of allowed sequence variations",
            "c) It solely uses UPGMA method",
            "d) It starts by building a distance tree for all taxa involved"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This may be an oversimplification; mutations of some sites are known to occur less frequently than others, for example, transversions versus transitions, functionally important sites versus neutral sites. Therefore, a weighting scheme that takes into account the different kinds of mutations helps to select tree topologies more accurately. The MP method that incorporates a weighting scheme is called weighted parsimony."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about Bootstrapping?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a statistical technique that tests the sampling errors of a phylogenetic tree",
            "b) It does the tests by repeatedly sampling trees through slightly perturbed datasets",
            "c) A newly constructed tree is not biased at all",
            "d) The robustness of the original tree can be assessed here"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The rationale for bootstrapping is that a newly constructed tree is possibly biased owing to incorrect alignment or chance fluctuations of distance measurements. To determine the robustness or reproducibility of the current tree, trees are repeatedly constructed with slightly perturbed alignments that have some random fluctuations introduced."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about nonparametric bootstrapping?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A new multiple sequence alignment of the same length is generated with random duplication of some of the sites",
            "b) A new multiple sequence alignment of the distinct lengths is generated with random duplication of some of the sites",
            "c) Certain sites are randomly replaced by other existing sites",
            "d) Certain sites may appear multiple times, and other sites may not appear at all in the new alignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Otherwise, the noise introduced in the resampling process is sufficient to generate different trees, indicating that the original topology may be derived from weak phylogenetic signals. Thus, this type of analysis gives an idea of the statistical confidence of the tree topology."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about nonparametric bootstrapping?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All the bootstrapped trees are summarized into a consensus tree based on a majority rule",
            "b) The most supported branching patterns shown at each node are labeled with bootstrap values",
            "c) The most supported branching patterns are the percentage of appearance of a particular clade",
            "d) This test doesn’t provide a measure for evaluating the confidence levels of the tree topology"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In nonparametric bootstrapping, a new multiple sequence alignment of the same length is generated with random duplication of some of the sites (i.e., the columns in an alignment) at the expense of some other sites. This process is repeated 100 to 1,000 times to create 100 to 1,000 new alignments that are used to reconstruct phylogenetic trees using the same method as the originally inferred tree.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about Caveats?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unusually high GC content in the original dataset is the potential cause for generating biased trees",
            "b) Unusually accelerated evolutionary rates is the potential cause for generating biased trees",
            "c) Unusually accelerated evolutionary rates is the potential cause for generating biased bootstrap estimates",
            "d) Not a large number of bootstrap re-sampling steps are needed to achieve yielding results"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The bootstrap test provides a measure for evaluating the confidence levels of the tree topology. Analysis has shown that a bootstrap value of 70% approximately corresponds to 95% statistical confidence, although the issue is still a subject of debate."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect statement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In this method one half of the sites in a dataset are randomly deleted",
            "b) It creates datasets half as long as the original",
            "c) Each new dataset is subjected to phylogenetic tree construction using the different methods as the original",
            "d) One criticism of this approach is that the size of datasets has been changed into one half and that the datasets are no longer considered replicates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In addition, from a statistical point of view, a large number of bootstrap resampling steps are needed to achieve meaningful results. It is generally recommended that a phylogenetic tree should be bootstrapped 500 to 1,000 times. However, this presents a practical dilemma."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about Bayesian Simulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It does not require bootstrapping",
            "b) It requires bootstrapping",
            "c) The MCMC procedure itself involves thousands or millions of steps of resampling",
            "d) Posterior probabilities are assigned at each node of a best Bayesian tree as statistical support"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Each new dataset is subjected to phylogenetic tree construction using the same method as the original. The advantage of jackknifing is that sites are not duplicated relative to the original dataset and that computing time is much shortened because of shorter sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding TREE-PUZZLE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a program performing quartet puzzling",
            "b) It allows various substitution models for likelihood score estimation",
            "c) It doesn’t incorporate a discrete γ model",
            "d) Because of the heuristic nature of the program, it allows ML analyses of large datasets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It stands for Phylogenetic analysis using parsimony. It is a commercial phylogenetic package. It is probably one of the most widely used phylogenetic programs available from Sinauer Publishers. PAUP was originally developed as parsimony program, but expanded to a comprehensive package that is capable of performing distance, parsimony, and likelihood analyses. "
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding TREE-PUZZLE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The resulting puzzle trees are automatically assigned puzzle support values to internal branches",
            "b) The support values are percentages of consistent quartet trees",
            "c) The support values do not have the same meaning as bootstrap values",
            "d) The support values have the same meaning as bootstrap values"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For distance or ML analyses, PAUP has the option for detailed specifications of substitution models, base frequencies, and among site rate heterogeneity (γ -shape parameters, proportion of invariant sites). PAUP is also able to perform nonparametric bootstrapping, jackknifing, KH testing, and SH testing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "PHYML is a web-based _______ program using the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) phylogenetic, GA (Genetic Algorithm)",
            "b) sequence based alignment, GA (Genetic Algorithm)",
            "c) phylogenetic, dynamic programming",
            "d) sequence based alignment, dynamic programming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Is a free multiplatform comprehensive package containing thirty-five subprograms for performing distance, parsimony, and likelihood analysis, as well as bootstrapping for both nucleotide and amino acid sequences. "
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "In PHYML, The tree searching _____ when the total ML score no longer ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) ceases, increases",
            "b) stops, decreases",
            "c) terminates, decreases",
            "d) stops, increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The only problem is that to complete an analysis the user is required to move between different subprograms while keeping modifying names of the intermediate output files. It is command-line based, but relatively easy to use for each single program. "
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the maximum parsimony method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This method predicts the evolutionary tree",
            "b) It minimizes the number of steps required to generate the observed variation in the sequences",
            "c) The method is also sometimes referred to as the minimum evolution method",
            "d) Only a pairwise sequence alignment is required to predict which sequence positions are likely to correspond"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A multiple sequence alignment is required to predict which sequence positions are likely to correspond. These positions will appear in vertical columns in the multiple sequence alignment. For each aligned position, phylogenetic trees that require the smallest number of evolutionary changes to produce the observed sequence changes are identified."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the maximum parsimony method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The analysis steps are continued for every position in the sequence alignment",
            "b) This method is used for large numbers of sequences",
            "c) Those trees that produce the smallest number of changes overall for all sequence positions are identified",
            "d) This method is used for sequences that are quite similar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The algorithm followed is not particularly complicated, but it is guaranteed to find the best tree, because all possible trees relating a group of sequences are examined. For this reason, the method is quite time-consuming and is not useful for data that include a large number of sequences or sequences with a large amount of variation."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the programs for analysis of nucleic acid sequences?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNAPARS treats gaps as a fifth nucleotide state",
            "b) DNAPENNY performs parsimonious phylogenies by branch-and-bound search",
            "c) DNAPENNY can analyze sequences up to 11 or 12",
            "d) Compatibility criterion is not involved in DNACOMP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DNACOMP performs phylogenetic analysis using the compatibility criterion.\nRather than searching for overall parsimony at all sites in the multiple sequence alignment, this method finds the tree that supports the largest number of sites. This method is recommended when the rate of evolution varies among sites."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "Parsimony can give ________ information when rates of sequence change _______ in the different branches of a tree that are represented by the sequence data.",
        "Options": [
            "a) misleading, vary",
            "b) useful, change",
            "c) misleading, are constant",
            "d) sometimes contradicting, are constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PROTPARS is used For analysis of protein sequences. As mentioned, Silent mutations that do not change the amino acid are not scored on the grounds that they have little evolutionary significance."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the distance methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The sequence pairs that have the largest number of sequence changes between them are termed ‘neighbors’",
            "b) On a tree, these sequences share a node or common ancestor position and are each joined to that node by a branch",
            "c) It produces a phylogenetic tree of the group",
            "d) It employs the number of changes between each pair in a group of sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: These variations produce a range of branch lengths, long ones representing more extended periods of time and short ones representing shorter times. Although other columns in the sequence alignment that show less variation may provide the correct tree, the columns representing greater variation dominate the analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the distance methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The distance method was pioneered by Feng and Doolittle",
            "b) A collection of programs by authors Feng and Doolittle will produce both an alignment and tree of a set of protein sequences",
            "c) The program CLUSTALW uses the neighbor-joining distance method as a guide to multiple sequence alignments",
            "d) Among the Programs of the PHYLIP package, DNADIST is not one of them"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The goal of distance methods is to identify a tree that positions the neighbors correctly and that also has branch lengths which reproduce the original data as closely as possible. Finding the closest neighbors among a group of sequences by the distance method is often the first step in producing a multiple sequence alignment."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the Distance analysis programs in PHYLIP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FITCH estimates a phylogenetic tree assuming additivity of branch lengths",
            "b) FITCH uses the Fitch-Margoliash method",
            "c) FITCH assumes a molecular clock but KITSCH does not",
            "d) NEIGHBOR estimates phylogenies using the neighbor-joining or unweighted pair group method with arithmetic mean (UPGMA)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DNADIST and PROTDIST are the Programs of the PHYLIP package that perform a distance analysis. They automatically read in a sequence in the PHYLIP in file format and automatically produce a file called outfile with a distance table."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the neighbor-joining method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is very much like the Fitch-Margoliash method",
            "b) It is totally dissimilar than the Fitch-Margoliash method",
            "c) It is especially suitable when the rate of evolution of the separate lineages under consideration varies",
            "d) When the branch lengths of trees of known topology are allowed to vary in a manner that simulates varying levels of evolutionary change, it is the most reliable method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: KITSCH assumes a molecular clock but FITCH does not. Also, in NEIGHBOR the neighbor-joining method does not assume a molecular clock and produces an unrooted tree. The UPGMA method assumes a molecular clock and produces a rooted tree."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong statement about the maximum likelihood approach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This method doesn’t always involve probability calculations",
            "b) It finds a tree that best accounts for the variation in a set of sequences",
            "c) The method is similar to the maximum parsimony method",
            "d) The analysis is performed on each column of a multiple sequence alignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This method involve probability calculations to find a tree that best accounts for the variation in a set of sequences. All possible trees are considered. Hence, the method is only feasible for a small number of sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "The main disadvantage of maximum likelihood methods is that they are _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) mathematically less folded",
            "b) mathematically less complex",
            "c) computationally lucid",
            "d) computationally intense"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Because the rate of appearance of new mutations is very small, the more mutations needed to fit a tree to the data, the less likely that tree (Felsenstein 1981). The maximum likelihood method resembles the maximum parsimony method in that trees with the least number of changes will be the most likely."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong statement about DNAML and DNAMLK?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PHYLIP includes mentioned two programs for this maximum likelihood analysis",
            "b) DNAML estimates phylogenies from nucleotide sequences by the maximum likelihood method",
            "c) DNAMLK estimates phylogenies in the same manner as DNAML",
            "d) DNAMLK estimates phylogenies without molecular clock"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum likelihood method presents an additional opportunity to evaluate trees with variations in mutation rates in different lineages. Also it provides opportunity to use explicit evolutionary models such as the Jukes-Cantor and Kimura models with allowances for variations in base composition."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong statement about the maximum likelihood method’s steps?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It starts with an evolutionary model of sequence change that provides estimates of rates of substitution of one base for another",
            "b) In the beginning there is an evolutionary model of sequence change that provides estimates of transitions and transversions in a set of nucleic acid sequences",
            "c) The rates of all possible substitutions are chosen so that the base composition differs",
            "d) The set of sequences is then aligned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The main disadvantage of maximum likelihood methods is that they are computationally intense. However, with faster computers, the maximum likelihood method is seeing wider use and is being used for more complex models of evolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "Once all positions in the sequence alignment have been examined, the likelihoods given by each column in the alignment for each tree are _____ to give the likelihood of the tree.",
        "Options": [
            "a) multiplied",
            "b) added",
            "c) divided",
            "d) squared"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PAUP version 4 can be used to perform a maximum likelihood analysis on DNA sequences. The method has also been applied for changes from one amino acid to another in protein sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "A method of sequence alignment based on a Model (Bishop and Thompson 1986) was introduced that predicts the manner in which DNA sequences change during evolution. Which of the following is wrong about it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The basis of this method is to devise a scheme for introducing substitutions, insertions, and gaps into sequences",
            "b) The basis of this method is to provide a probability that each of these changes occurs over certain periods of evolutionary time",
            "c) Given each of these predicted changes, the method examines all the possible combinations of mutations to change one sequence into another",
            "d) Multiple combinations are selected that will be the most likely over time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DNAMLK estimates phylogenies from nucleotide sequences by the maximum likelihood method in the same manner as DNAML, but assumes a molecular clock. DNAML allows for variable frequencies of the four nucleotides, for unequal rates of transitions and transversions, and for different rates of change in different categories of sites, as specified by the program."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "A method of sequence alignment based on a Model (Bishop and Thompson 1986) was introduced that predicts the manner in which DNA sequences change during evolution. Which of the following is wrong about it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This method is different from the Smith-Waterman local alignment algorithm",
            "b) This method is quite similar to the Smith-Waterman local alignment algorithm",
            "c) The underlying mutational theory is like those used to produce the PAM matrices for predicting changes in DNA and protein sequences",
            "d) Sequences are predicted to change by a Markov process such that each mutation in the sequence is independent of previous mutations at that site or at other sites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The rates of all possible substitutions are chosen so that the base composition remains the same. The set of sequences is then aligned, and the substitutions in each column are examined for their fit to a set of trees that describe possible phylogenetic relationships among the sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Phylogenetic analysis of a set of sequences that aligns ______ is straightforward because the positions that correspond in the sequences can be readily identified in a ______ of the sequences.",
        "Options": [
            "a) very well, multiple sequence alignment",
            "b) in a haphazard manner, multiple sequence alignment",
            "c) in a distorted way, multiple sequence alignment",
            "d) very well, self alignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Option “very well, self alignment” here, becomes irrelevant as there is phylogenetic analysis involved. The types of changes in the aligned positions or the numbers of changes in the alignments between pairs of sequences then provide a basis for a determination of phylogenetic relationships among the sequences by the above methods of phylogenetic analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "For sequences that have ________ a phylogenetic analysis is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) diverged considerably, more challenging",
            "b) not diverged, more challenging",
            "c) diverged considerably, less challenging",
            "d) diverged considerably, a less work to do"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For diverged sequences, the analysis steps increase as well. A determination of the sequence changes that have occurred is more difficult because the multiple sequence alignment may not be optimal and because multiple changes may have occurred in the aligned sequence positions."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "In the bootstrap method, the data are resampled by _____ choosing _____ columns from the aligned sequences to produce, in effect, a new sequence alignment of the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) randomly, horizontal, same length",
            "b) specifically, vertical, different lengths",
            "c) randomly, vertical, same length",
            "d) randomly, vertical, different lengths"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The degree of variation also sometimes affecs the efficiency and nature of output. Once a suitable alignment has been found, one may also ask how well the predicted phylogenetic relationships are supported by the data in the multiple sequence alignment."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "In the final steps of the bootstrap method, the _____ the decay value, the _______ significant the original branches.",
        "Options": [
            "a) greater, less",
            "b) greater, more",
            "c) lesser, more",
            "d) more, less"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Each column of data may be used more than once and some columns may not be used at all in the new alignment. Trees are then predicted from many of these alignments of resampled sequences (Felsenstein 1988)."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "Two more recent uses of phylogenetic analysis are to analyze ______ and to trace the evolutionary history of specific genes. Which of the following could not be the correct blank?",
        "Options": [
            "a) gene families",
            "b) genomes",
            "c) proteomes",
            "d) physical separation methods"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bootstrap analysis is supported by most of the commonly used phylogenetic inference software packages and is commonly used to test tree branch reliability. Another method of testing the reliability of one part of the tree is to collapse two branches into a common node (Maddison and Maddison 1992)."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true regarding the methods of gene prediction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They solely consist of a type called ab initio–based methods",
            "b) The ab initio–based approach predicts genes based on the given sequence alone",
            "c) The ab initio–based approach predicts genes based on the given sequence and relative homology data",
            "d) They solely consist of a type called homology-based approaches"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The current gene prediction methods can be classified into two major categories, ab initio–based and homology-based approaches. The ab initio–based approach predicts genes based on the given sequence alone."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about GeneMark?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a suite of gene prediction programs based on the fifth-order HMMs",
            "b) The main program is trained on a number of complete microbial genomes",
            "c) A GeneMark heuristic program can be used to improve accuracy",
            "d) If the sequence to be predicted is from a non-listed organism, the most closely related organism can be chosen as the basis for computation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: They also include ribosomal binding sites, and polyadenylation (poly-A) sites. In addition, the triplet codon structure limits the coding frame length to multiples of three, which can be used as a condition for gene prediction."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Glimmer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for Gene Locator and Interpolated Markov Modeler",
            "b) It is a UNIX program from TIGR",
            "c) It does not necessarily use   the IMM algorithm",
            "d) It is used to  predict potential coding regions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It has been observed that nucleotide composition and statistical patterns of the coding regions tend to vary significantly from those of the non-coding regions. The unique features can be detected by employing probabilistic models such as Markov models or hidden Markov models to help distinguish coding from non-coding regions."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a wrong statement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prokaryotes include bacteria and Archaea",
            "b) Prokaryotes have relatively large genomes",
            "c) Prokaryotes have relatively small genomes",
            "d) In Prokaryotes, The gene density in the genomes is high, with more than 90% of a genome sequence containing coding sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Prokaryotes have relatively small genomes with sizes ranging from0.5 to 10Mbp (1Mbp=106 bp). Each prokaryotic gene is composed of a single contiguous stretch of ORF coding for a single protein or RNA with no interruptions within a gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "The presence of these codons at The beginning of the frame _____ give a clear indication of the translation initiation site.",
        "Options": [
            "a) always",
            "b) does not necessarily",
            "c) does not",
            "d) never"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Occasionally, GTG and TTG are used as alternative start codons. But methionine is still the actual amino acid inserted at the first position."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "There are ____ possible stop codons, identification of which is straightforward.",
        "Options": [
            "a) five",
            "b) two",
            "c) ten",
            "d) three"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Because there may be multiple ATG, GTG, or TGT codons in a frame, the presence of these codons at the beginning of the frame does not necessarily give a clear indication of the translation initiation site. Instead, to help identify this initiation codon, other features associated with translation are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a wrong statement regarding the conventional determination of open reading frames?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Without the use of specialized programs, prokaryotic gene identification can rely on manual determination of ORFs and major signals related to prokaryotic genes",
            "b) Prokaryotic DNA is first subject to conceptual translation in all six possible frames, two frames forward and four frames reverse",
            "c) A stop codon occurs in about every twenty codons by chance in a noncoding region",
            "d) Prokaryotic DNA is first subject to conceptual translation in all six possible frames, three frames forward and three frames reverse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is located immediately downstream of the transcription initiation site and slightly upstream of the translation start codon. In many bacteria, it has a consensus motif of AGGAGGT. Identification of the ribosome binding site can help locate the start codon."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a wrong statement regarding TESTCODE method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This is based on the nucleotide composition of the third position of a codon",
            "b) In practice, because genes can be in any of the six frames, the statistical patterns are computed for all possible frames",
            "c) It is implemented in the commercial GCG package",
            "d) It exploits the fact that the third codon nucleotides in a coding region fails to repeat themselves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: At the end of the protein coding region is a stop codon that causes translation to stop. There are three possible stop codons, identification of which is straightforward. Many prokaryotic genes are transcribed together as one operon."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a wrong statement regarding Gene Prediction Using Markov Models and Hidden Markov Models?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Markov models and HMMs can be very helpful in providing finer statistical description of a gene",
            "b) A Markov model describes the probability of the distribution of nucleotides in a DNA sequence",
            "c) In a Markov model the conditional probability of a particular sequence position depends on k alternate positions",
            "d) A zero-order Markov model assumes each base occurs independently with a given probability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Prokaryotic DNA is first subject to conceptual translation in all six possible frames, three frames forward and three frames reverse. Because a stop codon occurs in about every twenty codons by chance in a noncoding region, a frame longer than thirty codons without interruption by stop codons is suggestive of a gene coding region, although the threshold for an ORF is normally set even higher at fifty or sixty codons."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eukaryotic nuclear genomes are much larger than prokaryotic ones",
            "b) They tend to have a very high gene density",
            "c) Eukaryotic nuclear genomes’ sizes range from 10 Mbp to 670 Gbp (1 Gbp = 109 bp)",
            "d) They tend to have a very high gene density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In humans, for instance, only 3% of the genome codes for genes, with about 1 gene per 100 kbp on average. The space between genes is often very large and rich in repetitive sequences and transposable elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about translation and transcription?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The first is capping is at the 5’ end of the transcript which involves methylation at the initial residue of the RNA",
            "b) The splicing process involves a large RNA-protein complex called spliceosome",
            "c) The second event is splicing, which is the process of removing exons and joining introns",
            "d) The second event is splicing, which is the process of removing introns and joining exons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reaction requires intermolecular interactions between a pair of nucleotides at each end of an intron and the RNA component of the spliceosome. To make the matter even more complex, some eukaryotic genes can have their transcripts spliced and joined in different ways to generate more than one transcript per gene. This is the phenomenon of alternative splicing."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Most vertebrate genes use __________ as the translation start codon and have a uniquely conserved flanking sequence call a Kozak sequence (CCGCCATGG).",
        "Options": [
            "a) AAG",
            "b) ATG",
            "c) AUG",
            "d) AGG"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From a computational point of view, it is a very complex and challenging problem. Because of the presence of split gene structures, alternative splicing, and very low gene densities, the difficulty of finding genes in such an environment is likened to finding a needle in a haystack."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Ab Initio–Based Programs for Gene Prediction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The goal of the ab initio gene prediction programs is to discriminate exons from noncoding sequences",
            "b) The goal is joining exons together in the correct order",
            "c) The main difficulty is correct identification of exons",
            "d) To predict exons, the algorithms rely solely on gene signals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In addition, most of these genes have a high density of CG dinucleotides near the transcription start site. This region is referred to as a CpG island (p refers to the phosphodiester bond connecting the two nucleotides), which helps to identify the transcription initiation site of a eukaryotic gene. The poly-A signal can also help locate the final coding sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about PredictionUsing NeuralNetworks for Gene Prediction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A neural network   is a statistical model with a special architecture for pattern recognition and classification",
            "b) It is composed of a network of mathematical variables",
            "c) They resembles ab initio approaches",
            "d) The variables in NeuralNetworks resemble the biological nervous system, with variables or nodes connected by weighted functions that are analogous to synapses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: To predict exons, the algorithms rely on two features, gene signals and gene content. Signals include gene start and stop sites and putative splice sites, recognizable consensus sequences such as poly-A sites."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Prediction Using Neural Networks for Gene Prediction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A neural network is constructed with multiple layers; the input, output, and hidden layers",
            "b) The input is the gene sequence with intron and exon signals",
            "c) The model is not fed with a sequence of known gene structure",
            "d) The output is the probability of an exon structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Among these features, the hexamer frequencies appear to be most discriminative for coding potentials. To derive an assessment for this feature, HMMscan be used, which require proper training. In addition to HMMs, neural network-based algorithms are also common in the gene prediction field."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Prediction Using Discriminant Analysis for Gene Prediction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) QDA draws a curved line based on a quadratic function",
            "b) LDA works by drawing a diagonal line that best separates coding signals from noncoding signals based on knowledge learned from training data sets of known gene structures",
            "c) Some gene prediction algorithms rely on discriminant analysis, either LDA or quadratic discriminant analysis (QDA), to improve accuracy",
            "d) LDA works by plotting a three-dimensional graph of coding signals versus all potential 3’ splice site positions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Aspect of the model that makes it look like a biological neural network is its ability to “learn” and then make predictions after being trained. The network is able to process information and modify parameters of the weight functions between variables during the training stage. Once it is trained, it is able to make automatic predictions about the unknown. This is quite different than the ab initio methods."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about FGENES?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for FindGenes",
            "b) It is a web-based program that uses LDA",
            "c) It is used to determine whether a signal is an exon",
            "d) It does not make a use of HMMs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In addition to FGENES, there are many variants of the program. Some programs, such as FGENESH, make use of HMMs. There are others, such as FGENESH C, that are similarity based. Some programs, such as FGENESH+, combine both ab initio and similarity-based approaches."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "Which of the following wrong about HMM GENE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is also an HMM-based web program",
            "b) It uses a criterion called the conditional maximum likelihood to discriminate coding from non-coding features",
            "c) HMM prediction is unbiased toward the locked region",
            "d) If a sequence already has a sub-region identified as coding region, which may be based on similarity with cDNAs or proteins in a database, these regions are locked as coding regions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It combines hexamer frequencies with coding signals (initiation codons, TATA box, cap site, poly-A, etc.) in prediction. Putative exons are assigned a probability score (P) of being a true exon. Only predictions with P > 0.5 are deemed reliable. This program is trained for sequences from vertebrates, Arabidopsis, and maize. It has been used extensively in annotating the human genome."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Homology-Based Programs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are based on the fact that exon structures and exon sequences of related species are less conserved",
            "b) This approach assumes that the database sequences are correct",
            "c) It is a reasonable assumption in light of the fact that many homologous sequences to be compared with are derived from cDNA or expressed sequence tags (ESTs) of the same species",
            "d) Potential coding frames in a query sequence are translated and used to align with closest protein homologs found in databases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An HMM prediction is subsequently made with a bias toward the locked region and is extended from the locked region to predict the rest of the gene coding regions and even neighboring genes. The program is in a way a hybrid algorithm that uses both ab initio-based and homology-based criteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about EST2Genome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web-based program purely based on the sequence alignment approach to define intron–exon boundaries",
            "b) It compares an EST (or cDNA) sequence with a genomic DNA sequence containing the corresponding gene",
            "c) The alignment is rarely done using a dynamic programming–based algorithm",
            "d) Advantage of the approach is the ability to find very small exons and alternatively spliced exons that are very difficult to predict by any ab initio–type algorithms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Homology-based programs are based on the fact that exon structures and exon sequences of related species are highly conserved. When potential coding frames in a query sequence are translated and used to align with closest protein homologs found in databases, near perfectly matched regions can be used to reveal the exon boundaries in the query."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about SGP-1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The program translates all potential exons in each sequence and does pair wise alignment for the translated protein sequences using a dynamic programming approach",
            "b) The near-perfect matches at the protein level define coding regions",
            "c) It is a similarity-based web program that aligns two genomic DNA sequences from distinctly related organisms",
            "d) It stands for Syntenic Gene Prediction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the homologs are not available in the database, the method cannot be used. Novel genes in a new species cannot be discovered without matches in the database. A number of publicly available programs use this approach."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "The specific DNA sequences to which the transcription factors bind are referred to as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) replication elements",
            "b) blocking factors",
            "c) transcription factors",
            "d) regulatory elements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In bacteria, transcription is initiated by RNA polymerase, which is a multi-subunit enzyme. The σ subunit (e.g., σ70) of the RNA polymerase is the protein that recognizes specific sequences upstream of a gene and allows the rest of the enzyme complex to bind. "
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNA polymerases I is responsible for the transcription of ribosomal RNA",
            "b) RNA polymerases III is responsible for the transcription of tRNA",
            "c) RNA polymerase II is exclusively responsible for transcribing protein-encoding genes",
            "d) Synthesis of mRNAs is carried out by RNA polymerase I"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This includes the sequence segments located 35 and 10 base pairs (bp) upstream from the transcription start site. They are also referred to as the −35 and −10 boxes. For the σ70 subunit in Escherichia coli, for example, the −35 box has a consensus sequence of TTGACA. The –10 box has a consensus of TATAAT."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding the ab initio approaches?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The conventional approach to detecting a promoter or regulatory site is through matching a consensus sequence pattern represented by regular expressions",
            "b) The conventional approach to detecting a promoter or regulatory site is through matching a position-specific scoring matrix constructed from well-characterized binding sites",
            "c) The consensus sequences or the matrices are relatively short, covering 6 to 10 bases",
            "d) The consensus sequences or the matrices are relatively large, covering 700 to 1000 bases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Some ab initio programs are signal based, relying on characteristic promoter sequences such as the TATA box. Other programs rely on content information such as hexamer frequencies."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "To improve the specificity of prediction, some algorithms selectively ______ coding regions and focus on the upstream regions________ which are most likely to contain promoters. In that sense, promoter prediction and gene prediction are coupled.",
        "Options": [
            "a) include, (0.5 to 2.0 kb) only",
            "b) include, (0.5 to 2.0 Mb) only",
            "c) exclude, (0.5 to 2.0 Mb) only",
            "d) exclude, (0.5 to 2.0 kb) only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The limitation is the need for training, which makes the prediction programs species specific. In addition, this type of method has a difficulty in discovering new, unknown motifs."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "Once an operon structure is known ______ for the presence of a promoter and regulatory elements _____ in the operon do not possess such DNA elements.",
        "Options": [
            "a) only the first gene is predicted, whereas other genes",
            "b) only the first hundred genes are predicted, whereas next few genes",
            "c) only first two genes are predicted, whereas next few genes",
            "d) only first ten genes are predicted, whereas next few genes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: To determine whether a query sequence matches a weight matrix, the sequence is scanned through the matrix. Scores of matches and mismatches at all matrix positions are summed up to give a log odds score, which is then evaluated for statistical significance. This simple approach, however, often has difficulty differentiating true promoters from random sequence matches and generates high rates of false positives as a result."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct regarding the method for prokaryotic operon prediction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It relies on two kinds of information: gene orientation and intergenic distances of a pair of genes of interest and conserved linkage of the genes based on comparative genomic analysis",
            "b) It relies only on the gene orientation and intergenic distances of a pair of genes of interest",
            "c) It relies only on the conserved linkage of the genes based on comparative genomic analysis",
            "d) The prediction cannot be done manually using the rules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: To better discriminate true motifs from background noise, a new generation of algorithms has been developed that take into account the higher order correlation of multiple subtle features by using discriminant functions, neural networks, or hidden Markov models (HMMs) that are capable of incorporating more neighboring sequence information."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding BPROM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web-based program for prediction of bacterial promoters",
            "b) It is a web-based program only for prediction of eukarotic promoters",
            "c) It uses a linear discriminant function",
            "d) The linear discriminant function is combined with signal and content information"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: One of the unique aspects in prokaryotic promoter prediction is the determination of operon structures because genes within an operon share a common promoter located upstream of the first gene of the operon. Hence, operon prediction is the key in prokaryotic promoter prediction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding FindTerm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a program for searching bacterial ρ-independent termination signals located at the end of operons",
            "b) It is a program for searching bacterial ρ-dependent termination signals located within the operons",
            "c) The predictions are made based on matching of known profiles of the termination signals combined with energy calculations",
            "d) It is available from the same site as FGENES and BPROM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only the first gene is predicted for the presence of a promoter and regulatory elements, whereas other genes in the operon do not possess such DNA elements. There are a number of methods available for prokaryotic operon prediction. The most accurate is a set of simple rules developed."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding the Prediction for Eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The consensus patterns are only derived from bioinformatics studies",
            "b) The experimentally determined DNA binding sites are compiled into profiles and stored in a database for scanning an unknown sequence to find similar conserved patterns",
            "c) The consensus patterns are derived from experimentally determined DNA binding sites",
            "d) The ab initio method for predicting eukaryotic promoters and regulatory elements relies on searching the input sequences for matching of consensus patterns of known promoters and regulatory elements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A scoring scheme is developed to assign operons with different levels of Confidence. This method is claimed to produce accurate identification of an operon structure, which in turn facilitates the promoter prediction. The prediction can be done manually using the rules. The few dedicated programs for prokaryotic promoter prediction do not apply the rule for historical reasons. The most frequently used program is BPROM."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "CpGProD is a web-based program that predicts promoters containing a high density of CpG islands _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) in archea genomic sequences",
            "b) in mammalian genomic sequences",
            "c) in eukaryotic and bacterial genomic sequences",
            "d) only in bacterial genomic sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The eukaryotic transcription initiation requires cooperation of a large number of transcription factors. Co-operativity means that the promoter regions tend to contain a high density of protein-binding sites. Thus, finding a cluster of transcription factor binding sites often enhances the probability of individual binding site prediction."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding Eponine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web-based program that predicts transcription start sites",
            "b) It is a web-based program that particularly predicts tranpososons and retropososons",
            "c) The regulatory sites include the TATA box, the CCAAT box, and CpG islands",
            "d) It is based on a series of pre-constructed PSSMs of several regulatory sites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It calculates moving averages of GC% and CpG ratios (observed/expected) over a window of a certain size (usually 200 bp). When the values are above a certain threshold, the region is identified as a CpG island."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding Cluster-Buster?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is an HMM-based web-based program",
            "b) A query sequence is scanned with a window size of 1 kb for putative regulatory motifs using motif HMMs",
            "c) It works by detecting a region of high concentration of unknown transcription factor binding sites and regulatory motifs at the initiation",
            "d) It is designed to find clusters of regulatory binding sites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The query sequence from a mammalian source is scanned through the PSSMs. The sequence stretches with high-score matching to all the PSSMs, as well as matching of the spacing between the elements, are declared transcription start sites. A Bayesian method is also used in decision making."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding First EF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a program that predicts promoters for bacterial DNA",
            "b) It is a web-based program that predicts promoters for human DNA",
            "c) It stands for First Exon Finder",
            "d) It integrates gene prediction with promoter prediction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It works by detecting a region of high concentration of known transcription factor binding sites and regulatory motifs. If multiple motifs are detected within a window, a positive score is assigned to each motif found. The total score of the window is the sum of each motif score subtracting a gap penalty, which is proportional to the distances between motifs. If the score of a certain region is above a certain threshold, it is predicted to contain a regulatory cluster."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "The input for the neural network includes parameters for sequence physical properties, such as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA bendability",
            "b) Signals such as the TATA box",
            "c) Signals such as initiator box",
            "d) Signals such as CpAA islands"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It uses quadratic discriminant functions (see Chapter 8) to calculate the probabilities of the first exon of a gene and its boundary sites. A segment of DNA (15 kb) upstream of the first exon is subsequently extracted for promoter prediction on the basis of scores for CpG islands."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding CONPRO?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web-based program that uses a consensus method",
            "b) It is used to identify promoter elements for human DNA",
            "c) cDNA does not play a role in prediction",
            "d) The program uses the information to search the human genome database for the position of the gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It has a unique promoter model containing six scoring segments. The program scans a window of 300 bases for the likelihoods of being in each of the coding, noncoding, and promoter regions."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect regarding Phylogenetic Footprinting–Based Method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is possible to obtain promoter sequences for a particular gene through comparative analysis",
            "b) The conservation from closely related organisms is both at the sequence level and at the level of organization of the elements",
            "c) The conservation from closely related organisms is most at the sequence level",
            "d) It has been observed that promoter and regulatory elements from closely related organisms such as human and mouse are highly conserved"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The identification of conserved noncoding DNA elements that serve crucial functional roles is referred to as phylogenetic footprinting; the elements are called phylogenetic footprints. This type of method can apply to both prokaryotic and eukaryotic sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about ConSite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web server that finds putative promoter elements",
            "b) It includes comparing two orthologous sequences",
            "c) The program does not accept pre-computed alignment",
            "d) The program accepts pre-computed alignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The predictive value of this method also depends on the quality of the subsequent sequence alignments. Advanced alignment programs can be used. Even more sophisticated expectation maximization (EM) and Gibbs sampling algorithms can be used in detecting weakly conserved motifs."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Bayes Aligner?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Posterior probability values, which are considered estimates of the true alignment, are calculated for each alignment",
            "b) The method generates a single best alignment",
            "c) It aligns two sequences using a Bayesian algorithm which is a unique sequence alignment method",
            "d) It is a web-based footprinting program"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The user provides two individual sequences which are aligned by ConSite using a global alignment algorithm. Conserved regions are identified by calculating identity scores, which are then used to compare against a motif database of regulatory sites (TRANSFAC). High-scoring sequence segments upstream of genes are returned as putative regulatory elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about FootPrinter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a web-based program for phylogenetic footprinting using multiple input sequences",
            "b) The motifs from organisms spanning over the widest evolutionary distances are identified as promoter or regulatory motifs",
            "c) The program performs multiple alignment of the input sequences to identify conserved motifs",
            "d) The user does not necessarily provides a phylogenetic tree that defines the evolutionary relationship of the input sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: rVISTA is a cross-species comparison tool for promoter recognition. It aligns the two sequences using a local alignment strategy. The motifs that have the highest percent identity in the pairwise comparison are presented graphically as regulatory elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MEME is the EM based program only for protein motif discovery",
            "b) AlignACE is a web-based program using the Gibbs sampling algorithm to find common motifs",
            "c) AlignACE is optimized for DNA sequence motif extraction",
            "d) Melina stands for Motif Elucidator In Nucleotide sequence Assembly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Instead of returning a single best alignment, the method generates a distribution of a large number of alignments using a full range of scoring matrices and gap penalties. By studying the distribution, the alignment that has the highest likelihood score, which is in the extreme margin of the distribution, is chosen. Based on this unique alignment searching algorithm, weakly conserved motifs can be identified with high probability scores."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Expression Profiling–Based Method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Genes with similar expression profiles are considered coexpressed, which can be identified through a clustering approach",
            "b) This approach appears to be less effective for finding transcription factor binding sites",
            "c) An advanced alignment-independent profile construction method such as EM and Gibbs motif sampling is often used in finding the subtle sequence motifs",
            "d) The basis for coexpression is thought to be due to common promoters and regulatory elements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The user also needs to provide a phylogenetic tree that defines the evolutionary relationship of the input sequences. One may obtain the tree information from the “Tree of Life” web site, which archives known phylogenetic trees using ribosomal RNAs as gene markers. It identifies unusually well-conserved motifs across a set of orthologous sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about PhyloCon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for Phylogenetic Consensus",
            "b) It is used to identify regulatory motifs",
            "c) It is a UNIX program that combines phylogenetic footprinting with gene expression profiling analysis",
            "d) No conservation among orthologous genes and conservation among coregulated genes is a disadvantage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The use of MEME is similar to that for protein sequences and DNA motif finding. AlignACE automatically determines the optimal number and lengths of motifs from the input sequences. Melina is a web-based program that runs four individual motif-finding algorithms – MEME, GIBBS sampling, CONSENSUS, and Core search – simultaneously. The user compares the results to determine the consensus of motifs predicted by all four prediction methods. "
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Amino acid conservation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It has been known for some time that conservation of residues at the surface of a protein family is often related to function",
            "b) Conservation of residues at the core of a protein family is often related to function",
            "c) This may be an enzyme active-site or binding site",
            "d) Unlike hydrophobicity or electrostatic potential, displaying residue conservation on the molecular surface has no physical or chemical basis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: However, the evolutionary information can sometimes delineate a functional epitope allowing residues to be identified that are important for binding. In order to infer structure-function relationships, the proteins must be structurally related, preferably a large family of proteins with related function."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Shape Complementarity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The complementarity between two proteins or a protein and ligand can be described by surface contact or overlap",
            "b) The complementarity between two proteins or a protein and ligand can be described by the overall buried surface area of two molecules in contact",
            "c) The complementarity between two proteins or a protein and ligand can be described by the number of adjacent surface points (atoms or residues)",
            "d) The hydrophobic effect barely has impact on protein folding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For example simple atom neighbor counting and the simple surface contact scores are of this type. Whilst these measures are easily calculated they also have some physical basis for being effective scoring functions. The principal driving force for protein folding and binding is the hydrophobic effect, which involves the free energy gain of removing non-polar surface area from water."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Grid Representation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To speed up the matching process the topology of the protein can be simplified from atomic level detail to a series of cubic elements",
            "b) To speed up the matching process discretizing the 3-dimensional space using a grid is done",
            "c) Discretizing allows very fast computer matching using search methods such as Fourier transform",
            "d) Fourier transform is hardly used in computer matching"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: However, since no distinction is generally made between polar and non-polar surface area this is an approximation. As burial of the former is unfavorable or neutral the sentence is held true."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "In Grid representation, in a translational scan the mobile molecule B moves through the grid representing the static molecule A and a signal describing shape complementarity, fc, is generated for each mapping. Mathematically the correlation function, fc, of fA and fB is given by ______ where N is the number of grid points along the cubic axes i, j, and k and α, β, and γ are the translational vectors of the mobile molecule B relative to the static one A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) fc = \\(\\sum_{i=1,j=1,k=1}^N\\) (fA,i,j,k * fBi+αj+βk+ɣ)",
            "b) fc = \\(\\sum_{i=0,j=0,k=0}^N\\) (fA,i,j,k * fBi+αj+βk+ɣ)",
            "c) fc = \\(\\sum_{i=1,j=1,k=1}^N\\) (fA,0,0,0 * fBi+αj+βk+ɣ)",
            "d) fc = \\(\\sum_{i=0,j=0,k=0}^N\\) (f0,i,j,k * fBi+αj+βk+ɣ)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The shape of a molecule is described by mapping it to a 3-D grid of uniformly spaced points. Clearly the level of detail is controlled by the grid spacing. The larger the grid spacing the cruder the representation with respect to the atomic level."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Hydrophobicity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The hydrophobic effect plays a dominant role in the folding of proteins",
            "b) Hydrophobic residues aggregate away from contact with water",
            "c) Hydrophobic residues aggregate to form hydrophobic cores with more polar residues",
            "d) Hydrophobic residues form the solvent accessible surface but restrict the solubility of the protein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The overlap between points representing the surface of the molecules is scored favorably, however, overlap with points representing the core of the static molecule are scored unfavorably. Zero correlation score is given to two molecules not in contact. Negative scores represent surface overlap with the core region of molecule A."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Electrostatic Complementarity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The electrostatic properties of biomolecules play an important role in determining interactions",
            "b) The burial of charged residues at protein-protein/DNA interfaces is thought to be generally net destabilizing with the hydrophobic effect being the primary driving force",
            "c) Charged groups involved in the biomolecular interface are often stabilized by other polar or oppositely charged groups on the interacting molecule",
            "d) Charged groups involved in the biomolecular interface are often stabilized by similar polar or same charged groups on the interacting molecule"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The highest score represents the best surface complementarity for a given translational scan. Note that the mobile molecule must be mapped differently to the grid for each rotational change applied to the molecule."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "Proteins are dynamic entities that undergo _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) only fluctuation of flexible loop regions about equilibrium positions when in solution",
            "b) only limited conformational change of amino acid side-chains when in solution",
            "c) both limited conformational change of amino acid side-chains and fluctuation of flexible loop regions about equilibrium positions when in solution",
            "d) illimitable or total conformational change of amino acid side-chains when in solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Such flexibility can often be adequately treated by ‘soft’ potentials or limited conformational flexibility and/or refinement of side-chains on docking. However, proteins often undergo more extensive conformational changes which may involve large-scale motions of domains relative to one another or possibly conformational change involving order-disorder transitions."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "In case of Protein-ligand docking, ______ ligands are often _____ in adapting their shape to fit the receptor binding pocket.",
        "Options": [
            "a) small molecule, highly flexible",
            "b) large molecule, highly flexible",
            "c) large molecule, more flexible",
            "d) small molecule, less flexible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: These types of motions will be poorly treated by a rigid body model for docking. Again distinction is often made between the general treatment of protein-protein docking and protein-ligand docking."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "In Multiple conformation rigid-body method, a ligand is assumed to be able to adopt a number (N) of different _______ that are computed _____ the ligand being docked into the receptor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) low-energy conformations, after",
            "b) low-energy conformations, prior to",
            "c) high-energy conformations, prior to",
            "d) high-energy conformations, after"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The degree of conformational flexibility of a small molecule ligand (substrate, cofactor or inhibitor) can be considerable particularly where there are multiple torsion angles. This presents a major challenge in protein-ligand docking and several different approaches have been used to solve this problem."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "The disadvantage of Multiple conformation rigid-body method is that the active conformation may be missed as the result of a minor structural difference not considered in the ______ ligand conformations. Where, the N is the number of low-energy conformations.",
        "Options": [
            "a) N +1",
            "b) N",
            "c) N2",
            "d) N/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: These, N, low-energy conformations are then docked individually into the receptor assuming a rigid conformation using a descriptor-based approach. The scoring function is used to determine which of the resulting solutions is optimal."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true regarding Protein flexibility?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Methods have been described for the introduction of side-chain flexibility to both protein-ligand and protein-protein docking",
            "b) Methods have been described for the introduction of side-chain flexibility to protein-ligand   docking only",
            "c) The Mean Field principle is rarely used in this",
            "d) Methods have been described for the introduction of side-chain flexibility to protein-protein docking only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The disadvantage is that the active conformation may be missed as the result of a minor structural difference not considered in the N ligand conformations and the advantage of this approach is that the search can be restricted to a smaller number of relevant ligand conformations."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "The ______ is an ongoing community-wide experiment on the comparative evaluation of protein-protein docking for structure prediction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chronological Assignment of Prediction of Interactions (CAPRI)",
            "b) Chronological Assessment of Prediction of Interactions (CAPRI)",
            "c) Critical Assignment of Prediction of Interactions (CAPRI)",
            "d) Critical Assessment of Prediction of Interactions (CAPRI)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is only the case if an experimental structure already exists. Several docking methods have been evaluated at ‘Critical Assessment of Structure Prediction 2’ (CASP2) for both protein-ligand and protein-protein interactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "An understanding of the importance of different factors in a particular interaction is important if confidence in the results is required. Which of the following are not those factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shape",
            "b) Hydrophobicity",
            "c) Electrostatics",
            "d) pH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the protein-protein docking evaluation several of the same docking methodologies were used in both docking challenges. In the first challenge involving a protein inhibitor all the groups successfully predicted the complex."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "There exist three types of interactions between domains. Which of the following is not one of them?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stable complex",
            "b) Transient interaction",
            "c) Multi-domain protein",
            "d) Unstable interaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Interactions between domains occur in multidomain proteins, in stable complexes and in transient interactions between proteins that also exist independently. Experimental approaches for the large-scale determination of protein interactions are emerging. Theoretical analyses based on protein structures have unraveled some of the overall principles and features of the way domains evolved to interact with each other."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "Stable complexes consist of proteins that are _____ associated with each other, like many ____ proteins for instance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) temporarily, oligomeric",
            "b) temporarily, monomeric",
            "c) permanently, oligomeric",
            "d) permanently, monomeric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Interactions between domains determine the structure of multidomain proteins, in which there are several domains on one polypeptide chain. Given that all proteins consist of domains, interactions between domains also occur between the proteins that are permanently associated in stable complexes and proteins that interact transiently, but also exist independently of each other."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "Sets of proteins that are part of stable complexes and sets of proteins involved in transient interactions ____ in terms of the similarity in gene expression among the set of proteins.",
        "Options": [
            "a) are similar",
            "b) differ",
            "c) are same",
            "d) show similar function"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Well-known stable complexes include the histone octamer, the ribosome and DNA and RNA polymerases. Transient interactions on the other hand are all those protein-protein interactions that occur between proteins that also exist independently."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "Correlation of gene expression for pairs of transiently interacting proteins is ______ compared to randomly chosen pairs of proteins.",
        "Options": [
            "a) not significant",
            "b) only marginally significant",
            "c) totally significant",
            "d) significant to much extent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Proteins permanently associated in a stable complex need to be present or absent in the cell at the same time. Analysis of microarray data by Gerstein and co-workers by methods along the lines, has shown that the members of stable complexes in the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae have highly correlated gene expression patterns."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about Yeast-two-hybrid screens?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The yeast-two-hybrid system uses the transcription of a reporter gene driven by the Gal4 transcription factor to monitor whether or not two proteins are interacting",
            "b) The DNA-binding domain chimeric protein will not bind upstream of the reporter gene",
            "c) If the activation domain chimeric protein interacts with the DNA-binding domain chimeric protein, the reporter gene will be transcribed",
            "d) Disadvantages of the method are that only pairwise interactions are tested, and not interactions that can only take place when multiple proteins come together, as well as a high false positive rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In prokaryotes, genes are co-regulated if they are a member of the same operon, and many proteins that are members of the same stable complex are part of the same operon. For instance, Ouzounis and Karp determined that over 90% of the enzymes that are in stable complexes in E. coli metabolic pathways are adjacent on the E. coli chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about Purification of protein complexes followed by mass spectrometry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isolating protein complexes from cells allows identification of interactions between ensembles of proteins instead of just pairs",
            "b) Systematic purification of complexes on a large scale is done by tagging hundreds of genes with an epitope",
            "c) UnLike in the yeast-two-hybrid assay, this does not involve chimeric genes",
            "d) Affinity purification based on the epitope will then extract all the proteins attached to the bait protein from cell lysates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thus the proteins in stable complexes are more similar across species, having higher sequence identity between orthologs, than the proteins in transient interactions. A calculation by Teichmann showed that there are significant differences between the average values for sequence identities between S. cerevisiae and S. pombe orthologs in stable complexes, transient interactions and monomers."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Many entries in the Protein DataBank (PDB) are three-dimensional structures of multiple domains",
            "b) The structures in PDB provide experimental information about interactions between domains at atomic detail",
            "c) There are comparatively few three-dimensional structures compared to the amount of data available from the lower resolution large-scale experiments",
            "d) Many entries in the Protein DataBank (PDB) are two-dimensional structures of multiple domains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Analysis of structures consisting of multiple domains has uncovered some of the principles of domain interactions in three dimensions. This information can therefore be complementary to the experimental data on protein interactions and to the predicted interactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "Almost ______ engage in interactions with domains from their own family when one includes oligomeric proteins.",
        "Options": [
            "a) one fifith of all known families",
            "b) one fourth of all known families",
            "c) all of all known families",
            "d) half of all known families"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Each node in this graph represents a protein domain family. There are a few families that are hubs in the network: these are large families that are functionally versatile, such as Rossmann domains indicated by an ‘R’ here. Most families engage in only one or two types of interactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "Across the different types of catalytic families, the position of the two domains with respect to one another varied, but only within a range of about ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20°",
            "b) 10°",
            "c) 90°",
            "d) 80°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To study the large-scale patterns and evolution of interactions between protein domains, the interactions in terms of the domain families can be summarized. Thus the interactions of one family represent the sum of all the interactions of domains in that family. Precise information about contacts between individual domains can be extracted by analysis of PDB entries."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "Interactions between proteins can be predicted computationally by looking for sets of genes that occur as a _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) single gene in at least one genome",
            "b) multiple genes in at least one genome",
            "c) multiple genes in various genomes",
            "d) single gene in various genomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Computational methods for predicting protein-protein interactions are desirable as experimental determination is time-consuming and expensive. Several prediction methods are based on the observation that if two proteins are part of the same complex, it is favorable for the two interaction partners to be co-expressed and co-regulated."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "Conservation of gene order due to operon structure is _______ so interactions of proteins specific to eukaryotes cannot be detected by method of Conservation of gene order.",
        "Options": [
            "a) not applicable to archea genomes",
            "b) not applicable to prokaryote genomes",
            "c) applicable to eukaryote genomes",
            "d) not applicable to eukaryote genomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Interactions between proteins can be predicted computationally by looking for sets of genes that occur as a single gene in at least one genome. Or it can be done by looking for prokaryotic genes that have conserved adjacent gene order across several genomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "An approach for predicting ______ to look for cases across a set of genomes where _____ are part of the same gene in one genome resulted in gene fusion method.",
        "Options": [
            "a) gene interactions, only three to four orthologs",
            "b) gene interactions, two orthologs",
            "c) protein interactions, two or more orthologs",
            "d) protein interactions, two orthologs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is because they have been selected to remain as a co-regulated unit throughout the extensive shuffling of gene order that takes place in prokaryote genomes. Thus conservation of gene order across different, distantly related genomes has been used as a method for predicting protein interactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "Domains that are part of a multidomain protein are ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) nethier co-regulated nor colocalized",
            "b) not co-regulated but colocalized",
            "c) co-regulated and but not colocalized",
            "d) co-regulated and colocalized"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When comparing pairs of genes or sets of genes in different genomes for this purpose, it is important to ensure that the genes are truly equivalent, in other words that they are orthologs, as opposed to merely similar genes. This is frequently done by only accepting a pair of proteins as orthologs if they are ‘bi-directional best hits’. This means that both proteins are the best match to each other when searching against the other proteome. The other extreme would be to consider proteins as equivalent if they share just one of many domains, for instance."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about DNA sequencing methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Purified fragments of DNA cut from plasmid/phage clones or amplified by polymerase chain reaction (PCR)",
            "b) Clones of DNA fragments are denatured to single strands, and one of the strands is hybridized to an oligonucleotide primer",
            "c) Taq polymerase is quite heat sensitive",
            "d) New strands of DNA are synthesized from the end of the primer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In an automated procedure, new strands of DNA are synthesized from the end of the primer by heat-resistant Taq polymerase from a pool of deoxyribonucleotide triphosphates (dNTPs) that includes a small amount of one of four chain-terminating nucleotides (ddNTPs)."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "The combined mixture of all labeled DNA fragments is electrophoresed to _____ the fragments by______ and the ladder of fragments is scanned for the presence of each of the four labels.",
        "Options": [
            "a) separate, size",
            "b) separate, pH",
            "c) assimilate, pH",
            "d) assimilate, size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A similar set of fragments is made for each of the other three bases. But each set is labeled with a different fluorescent ddNTP."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "To sequence larger molecules, individual chromosomes are purified and broken into _____ or larger random fragments, which are cloned into vectors designed for large molecules.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100-Mb",
            "b) 100-kb",
            "c) 5000-kb",
            "d) 600-kb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A computer program then determines the probable order of the bands and predicts the sequence. Depending on the actual procedure being used, one run may generate a reliable sequence of as many as 500 nucleotides."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Many levels of clone redundancy may be required to build a consensus map because individual clones can have _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) rearrangements",
            "b) deletions",
            "c) two separate fragments",
            "d) vectors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For accurate work, a printout of the scan is usually examined for abnormalities that decrease the quality of the sequence, and the sequence may then be edited manually. The first sequence can also be extended by making a second oligonucleotide matching the distal end of the readable sequence and using this primer to read more of the original template."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue about Shotgun Sequencing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When DNA fragments derived from different chromosomal regions have repeats of the same sequence, they will appear to overlap",
            "b) When DNA fragments derived from different chromosomal regions have repeats of the same sequence, they will appear to scrutinize",
            "c) In a new whole shotgun approach, Celera Genomics is sequencing both ends of DNA fragments of short (2 kb), medium (10 kb), and long (BAC or >100 kb) lengths",
            "d) A large number of reads are then assembled by computer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By repeating this procedure, both strands of a DNA fragment several kilobases in length can be sequenced. Sequential sequencing of a DNA molecule using oligonucleotide primers is done later."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "Using cDNA sequence with the __________ it is much simpler to locate protein-encoding sequences in these molecules.",
        "Options": [
            "a) exons taken out",
            "b) exons removed",
            "c) introns added",
            "d) introns removed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Genomic sequencing meets both goals. However, only a small percentage of the genomic sequence of many organisms actually encodes proteins because of the presence of introns within coding regions and other noncoding regions in the genome."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The simplest and newest way of submitting sequences is through the Web site on a Web form page called BankIt",
            "b) The sequence can also be annotated with information about the sequence, such as mRNA start and coding regions",
            "c) The submitted form is transformed into GenBank format and returned to the submitter for review before being added to GenBank",
            "d) Sequin does not run on UNIX"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There has been a great deal of progress in developing computational methods for analyzing genomic sequences and finding these protein-encoding regions. But these methods are not completely reliable and, furthermore, such genomic sequences are often not available."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is untrue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) There is no detailed check of sequence accuracy prior to submission to GenBank and other databases",
            "b) Often, a sequence is submitted at the time of publication of the sequence in a journal article, providing a certain level of checking by the editorial peer review process",
            "c) No sequence is submitted without being published or prior to publication",
            "d) In laboratories performing large sequencing projects, such as those engaged in the Human Genome Project or the genome projects of model organisms, the granting agency requires a certain level of accuracy of the order of 1 possible error per 10 kb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The only possible difficulty is that a gene of interest may be developmentally expressed or regulated in such a way that the mRNA is not present. This problem has been circumvented by pooling mRNA preparations from tissues that express a large proportion of the genome, from a variety of tissues and developing organs or from organisms subjected to several environmental influences."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "Granting agency requires a certain level of accuracy in case of errors. Which of the given statements is untrue regarding it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In other laboratories, such as those performing a single-attempt sequencing of ESTs, the error rate may be much higher, approximately 1 in 100, including incorrectly identified bases and inserted or deleted bases",
            "b) Incorrect bases always translate to the right amino acid",
            "c) Base insertions/deletions will cause frame-shifts in the sequence",
            "d) Making alignment with a protein sequence becomes difficult because of frameshifts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This was an important development from resolution point of view. This has just enough DNA sequence to give a good idea of the protein sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong about GenBank DNA Sequence Entry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The information is organized into fields, each with an identifier, shown as the first text on each line",
            "b) In some entries, these identifiers may be abbreviated to two letters, e.g., RF for reference",
            "c) Some identifiers may have additional subfields",
            "d) The CDS subfield in the field FEATURES does not offer the amino acid sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The CDS subfield in the field FEATURES gives the amino acid sequence obtained by translation of known and potential open reading frames. The format of a database entry in GenBank, the NCBI nucleic acid and protein sequence database, is as follows: Information describing each sequence entry is given, including literature references, information about the function of the sequence, locations of mRNAs and coding regions, and positions of important mutations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong about European Molecular Biology Laboratory Data Library Format?",
        "Options": [
            "a) EMBL maintains DNA and protein sequence databases",
            "b) As with GenBank entries, a large amount of information describing each sequence entry is given",
            "c) Sequence entry includes literature references and information about the function of the sequence, but not locations of mRNAs and coding regions",
            "d) Information is organized into fields, each with an identifier, shown as the first text on each line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sequence includes numbers on each line so that sequence positions can be located by eye. Because the sequence count or a sequence checksum value may be used by the computer program to verify the sequence composition, the sequence count should not be modified except by programs that also modify the count. The GenBank sequence format often has to be changed for use with sequence analysis software."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong about FASTA Sequence Format?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The FASTA sequence format includes a comment line identified by a “>” character in the first column followed by the name and origin of the sequence",
            "b) The FASTA sequence format includes the sequence in standard one-letter symbols",
            "c) This format provides a very convenient way to copy just the sequence part from one window to another because there are no numbers or other nonsequence characters within the sequence",
            "d) The presence of ‘*’ is not quite essential for reading the sequence correctly by some sequence analysis programs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When one sequence entry is retrieved, all of these fields will be displayed. Search for the term “SOS regulon and coli” in all fields will find two matching sequences. Finding these sequences is simple because indexes have been made listing all of the sequences that have any given term, one index for each field. Similarly, a search for transcriptional regulator will find three sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong about National Biomedical Research Foundation/Protein Information Resource Sequence Format?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sequences retrieved from the PIR database are not in this compact format, but in an expanded format with much more information about the sequence",
            "b) The NBRF format is similar to the FASTA sequence format but with significant differences",
            "c) This is different than PIR format",
            "d) The first line includes an initial “>” character followed by a two-letter code such as P for complete sequence or F for fragment, followed by a 1 or 2 to indicate type of sequence, then a semicolon, then a four- to six-character unique name for the entry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sequence entry includes literature references and information about the function of the sequence, locations of mRNAs and coding regions and positions of important mutations. The sequence count or a checksum value for the sequence may be used by computer programs to make sure that the sequence is complete and accurate. For this reason, the sequence part of the entry should usually not be modified except with programs that also modify this count."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong about Genetics Computer Group Sequence Format?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Earlier versions of the Genetics Computer Group (GCG) programs require a unique sequence format and include programs that convert other sequence formats into GCG format",
            "b) Information about the sequence in the GenBank entry is not included but the line information is carried out",
            "c) If one or more sequence characters become changed through error, a program reading the sequence will be able to determine that the change has occurred because the checksum value in the sequence entry will no longer be correct",
            "d) Lines of information are terminated by two periods, which mark the end of information and the start of the sequence on the next line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The format is quite similar to the EMBL format, except that considerably more information about the physical and biochemical properties of the protein is provided. Also, the output of a DDBJ DNA sequence entry is almost identical to that of GenBank."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong about Abstract Syntax Notation Sequence Format?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The information is much more difficult to read by eye than a GenBank formatted sequence",
            "b) Abstract Syntax Notation (ASN.1) is a formal data description language that has been developed by the computer industry",
            "c) All the information found in other forms of sequence storage, e.g., the GenBank format, is present. For example, sequences can be retrieved in this format by ENTREZ",
            "d) Taxonomic information and bibliographic information cannot be encoded with this format"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The FASTA sequence format includes an optional ‘*’ which indicates end of sequence and which may or may not be present and its presence maybe essential. The FASTA sequence format is similar to the protein information resource (NBRF) format except that the NBRF format includes a first line with a “>” character in the first column followed by information about the sequence, a second line containing an identification name for the sequence, and the third to last lines containing the sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Before using a sequence file in a sequence analysis program, it is important to ensure that computer sequence files contain only sequence characters and not special characters used by text editors",
            "b) Computer sequence files might contain special characters used by text editors",
            "c) Editing a sequence file with a word processor can introduce such changes if one is not careful to work only with text or so-called ASCII files",
            "d) Most text editors normally create text files that include control characters in addition to standard ASCII characters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This sequence format, which is sometimes also called the PIR format. It has been used by the National Biomedical Research Foundation/Protein Information Resource (NBRF) and also by other sequence analysis programs."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about ASCII and Hexadecimal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Computers store sequence information as simple rows of sequence characters called strings, which are similar to the sequences shown on the computer terminal",
            "b) Each character is stored in binary code in the smallest unit of memory, called a byte",
            "c) Each character is stored in binary code in the smallest unit of memory, called a bit",
            "d) By convention, many of these combinations have a specific definition, called their ASCII equivalent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is started by a molecular genetics group at Stanford University, and subsequently continued by a company, Intelligenetics, the IG format is similar to the PIR format, except that a semicolon is usually placed before the comment line. The identifier on the second line is also present."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is untrue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sequence and other data files that contain non-ASCII characters also may not be transferred correctly from one machine to another and may cause unpredictable behavior of the communications software",
            "b) The ASCII mode is useful for transferring text files, and the binary mode is useful for transferring compressed data files, which also contain non-ASCII characters",
            "c) ASCII and binary modes cannot be set by the user",
            "d) Most sequence analysis programs also require not only that a DNA or protein sequence file be a standard ASCII file, but also that the file be in a particular format such as the FASTA format"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Information about the sequence in the GenBank entry is first included, followed by a line of information about the sequence and a checksum value. This value (not shown) is provided as a check on the accuracy of the sequence by the addition of the ASCII values of the sequence. If the sequence has not been changed, this value should stay the same."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "According to standard amino acid code letters which of the given pair is not right?",
        "Options": [
            "a) K- lysine",
            "b) Y- tyrosine",
            "c) Q- glutamine",
            "d) R- serine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ASN.1 has been adopted by the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) to encode data such as sequences, maps, taxonomic information, molecular structures, and bibliographic information. These data sets may then be easily connected and accessed by computers. The ASN.1 sequence format is a highly structured and detailed format especially designed for computer access to the data."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "which of the given statements is incorrect about Block multiple sequence alignment format?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Identification starts contain a short identifier for the group of sequences from which the block was made and often is the original Prosite group ID",
            "b) The identifier is terminated by a comma, and “BLOCK” indicates the entry type",
            "c) AC contains the block number, a seven-character group number for sequences from which the block was made, followed by a letter (A–Z) indicating the order of the block in the sequences",
            "d) The block number is a 5-digit number preceded by BL (BLOCKS database) or PR (PRINTS database)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The identifier is terminated by a semicolon, and “BLOCK” indicates the entry type. Min, max is the minimum, maximum number of amino acids from the previous blocks or from the sequence starting. DE describes sequences from which the block was made."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about READSEQ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is an extremely useful sequence formatting program developed by D. G. Gilbert at Indiana University, Bloomington",
            "b) It was developed at Indiana University, Bloomington",
            "c) It can recognize a DNA or protein sequence file in any of the formats",
            "d) It can recognize a DNA or protein sequence file in some particular formats"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In addition to this, w is the width of the sequence segments (columns) in the block. s is the number of sequence segments (rows) in the block. Other values (n1, n2) describe statistical features of the block. Sequence id is a list of sequences. Each sequence line contains a sequence identifier, the offset from the beginning of the sequence to the block in parentheses, the sequence segment, and a weight for the segment."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "Each DNA or protein sequence database entry has much information, including ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) an assigned accession number(s)",
            "b) source organism",
            "c) name of locus",
            "d) reference number type(s)"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer:  d\nExplanation: It can identify the format, and write a new file with an alternative format. Some of these formats are used for special types of analyses such as multiple sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an incorrect statement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The last column contains the sequences themselves",
            "b) It is quite tough making an index of the information in each of these fields so that a search query can locate all the occurrences through the index",
            "c) If one imagines a large table with each sequence entry occupying one row, then each column will include one of the above types of information for each sequence, and each column is called a FIELD",
            "d) The DNA, protein, and reference databases have all been cross-referenced so that moving between them is readily accomplished"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: Data files with such multiple sequences as mentioned are converted in READSEQ. Options to reverse-complement and to remove gaps from sequences are included. SEQIO and another sequence conversion program for a UNIX machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about Database Types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relational databases are more useful in the development of biological databases",
            "b) The tables in relational database are carefully indexed and cross-referenced with each other, sometimes using additional tables, so that each item in the database has a unique set of identifying features",
            "c) The relational database orders data in tables made up of rows giving specific items in the database, and columns giving the features as attributes of those items",
            "d) The two principal types of DBs are the relational and object-oriented databases"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer:  a\nExplanation: In addition, the GCG programs include the following sequence formatting programs: (1) GETSEQ, which converts a simple ASCII file being received from a remote PC to GCG format; (2) REFORMAT, which will format a GCG file that has been edited, and will also perform other functions; and (3) SPEW, which sends a GCG sequence file as an ASCII file to a remote PC."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about ENTREZ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a resource prepared only by the staff of the National Center for Biotechnology Information",
            "b) It provides a series of forms that can be filled out to retrieve a Medline reference related to the molecular biology sequence databases",
            "c) One straightforward way to access the sequence databases is through ENTREZ",
            "d) It provides a series of forms that can be filled out to retrieve a DNA or protein sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is a resource prepared by the staff of the National Center for Biotechnology Information and National Library of Medicine, Bethesda, Maryland. After search for either a protein or a DNA sequence is chosen at the above address, another Web page is provided with a form to fill out for the search. "
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "Using boolean logic, the search looks for database entries that include the first term __________ the second, and subsequent terms repeated until the last term.",
        "Options": [
            "a) AND",
            "b) OR",
            "c) ExOR",
            "d) NAND"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mentioned database centers are updated daily and exchange new sequences daily, so that it is only necessary to access one of them. The EMBL stands for European Molecular Biology Laboratory and DDBJ for DNA DataBank of Japan."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "For a protein search, which of the following is the wrong choice for fields?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accession (number)",
            "b) E. C. number",
            "c) Issue",
            "d) Journal number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: On the ENTREZ form, make a selection in the data entry window after the term “Search,” then enter search terms in the longer data entry window after “for.” The database will be searched for sequence database entries that contain all of these terms or related ones. "
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "Knowing ________ should be enough to find the required entry quickly.",
        "Options": [
            "a) publication date, protein name, journal name",
            "b) accession number, protein name, or name of gene",
            "c) publication date, protein name, or volume",
            "d) properties, protein name, or title word"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When searching for terms in a particular field, some knowledge of the terms that are in the database can be helpful. The “Limits” link on the ENTREZ form page is used to limit the GenBank field to be searched, and various logical combinations of search terms may be designed by this method. These fields refer to the GenBank fields."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about ENTREZ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) There is no simple way to find the correct sequence without manually checking the information provided in each sequence, but this usually takes longer time",
            "b) Before leaving ENTREZ, it is often useful to check for sequence database entries that are similar to the one of interest, called “neighbors” by ENTREZ",
            "c) The expanded query searches other database entries of interest, such as the same protein in another organism, a large chromosomal sequence that includes the gene, or members of the same gene family",
            "d) While visiting the site, note that ENTREZ has been adapted to search through a number of other biological databases, and also through Medline, and these searches are available from the initial ENTREZ Web page"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Other fields being- author name, journal name, keyword, modification date. Also, it includes organism, page number, primary accession (number), properties, protein name, publication date (of reference), seqID string, sequence length, substance name, text word, title word, volume, and sequence ID. Similar fields are shown for the DNA database search."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about Retrieving a Specific Sequence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It can be difficult to retrieve the sequence of a specific gene or protein simply because of the sheer number of sequences in the Gen-Bank database and the complex problem of indexing them",
            "b) Other projects may benefit from the availability of better curated and annotated protein sequence databases, but not PIR and SwissProt",
            "c) For projects that require the most currently available sequences, the NR databases should be searched",
            "d) The genomic databases can also provide the sequence of a particular gene or protein. Protein sequences in the Genpro database are generated by automatic translation of DNA sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The number of terms to be searched for and the field to be searched is the main decisions to be made. In doing so, it is important to be as specific as possible, or else there may be a great many possibilities."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "The first bacterial genome to be sequenced was that of ________ a mild human pathogen.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hemophilus influenzae",
            "b) Lactobacillus",
            "c) Vibrio cholarae",
            "d) Clostridium botulinum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nuclei and chromosomes were not observed in bacteria (a prokaryotic cell), but when bacterial DNA was eventually detected, the molecule was usually circular and was also in a compacted form. The following sections outline the structure and composition of prokaryotic and eukaryotic genomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "While sequencing of the first bacterial genome–A large number of random overlapping fragments were sequenced and then a consensus sequence of the entire ______ chromosome of Hemophilus was assembled by computer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8.6 x 109 bp",
            "b) 1.8 x 106 bp",
            "c) 6.9 x 105 bp",
            "d) 1.8 x 104 bp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This project was carried out at the Institute of Genomics Research. It was carried out in part to prove a new genome sequencing method—the shotgun method."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "While sequencing of The first bacterial genome—Approximately ____ of the ____  predicted genes matched genes of another species, the bacterial species E. coli K-12 that had been the subject of many years of genetic and biochemical research.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 46%, 1500",
            "b) 58%, 1496",
            "c) 72%, 1743",
            "d) 58%, 1743"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It was done excepting several regions that had to be assembled manually. Once available, open reading frames were identified, and these were compared to the existing proteins by a database similarity search."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "After sequencing the Hemophilus genome and Organisms were selected for sequencing based on minimum criteria. Which of the following is not one of them?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They had been subjected to a good deal of biological analysis",
            "b) They were model eukaryotic organisms",
            "c) They were an important human pathogen, e.g., Mycobacterium tuberculosis (tuberculosis)",
            "d) They were of phylogenetic interest"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The function of the other 42% of the Hemophilus genes could not be identified, although some of them were similar to the 38% of E. coli genes that were also of unknown function. Other unique sequences that appeared to be associated with the ability of the organism to behave as a human pathogen were also found."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "Which of the given is wrongly matched?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Escherichia coli – Bacteria",
            "b) Methanococcus jannaschii – Archaea",
            "c) Synechocystis sp. – Archaea",
            "d) Aquifex aeolicus – Bacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There were model prokaryotic organisms. For e.g., E. coli and Bacillus subtilis. The success of sequencing the Hemophilus genome in a relatively short time and with a modest budget heralded the sequencing of a large number of additional prokaryotic organisms. "
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "The sequences of satellite DNA fall into different types, each with a different repeat unit of length _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5–400 Mbp",
            "b) 3–300 kbp",
            "c) 6–900 Mbp",
            "d) 5–200 bp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: GeneQuiz is an example of such a resource. There are Web sites that provide a complete annotation of the prokaryotic genomes that have been sequenced."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "Minisatellites are made up of repeat units of up to ____ and microsatellites compose of repeat units of ____ or less.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25 bp, 10 bp",
            "b) 70 bp, 6 bp",
            "c) 80 bp, 9 bp",
            "d) 25 bp, 4 bp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Centromeres hold newly replicated daughter chromosomes together. They serve as a point of attachment for pulling the chromosomes apart during cell division."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "Genes that are transcribed are located in the ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) euchromatin",
            "b) heterochromatin",
            "c) heterochromatin and euchromatin",
            "d) tightly bound DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Eukaryotic genomes commonly have tandem repeats of sequences. In addition to this, they having linear chromosomes within a nucleus, and differing from prokaryotic genomes in this respect."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "______ can comprise a large proportion of the eukaryotic genome as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) transposable elements, single copy sequences",
            "b) transposable elements, repetitive sequences",
            "c) macrosatellite DNA elements, single copy sequences",
            "d) satellite DNA elements, single copy sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Because of the skewed base composition of regions that have repeats, they may be purified by virtue of having different buoyant densities. The repeat unit of length is 5–200 bp and not in the scale if Mega."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "(Transposable Elements) TEs have the potential to _____ in number until they comprise a ____ proportion of the genome sequence.",
        "Options": [
            "a) decrease, large",
            "b) decrease, micro",
            "c) increase, micro",
            "d) increase, large"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Some of it is found near the open ends of chromosomes- telomeres but Most of this repetitive DNA is found near the centromere. It is because they serve as a point of attachment for pulling the chromosomes apart during cell division."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "More than _____ of the human genome consists of interspersed repetitive sequences derived from TEs (transposable elements).",
        "Options": [
            "a) one-third",
            "b) one-eighth",
            "c) one-fifth",
            "d) half"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The presence of these elements may be demonstrated using programs for detection of low-complexity regions in sequences. For e.g. in the fruit fly Drosophila has 15% of genome that is made up of transposable elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "The retroposons include short _________ interspersed nuclear elements (SINES).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 90–4000 bp long",
            "b) 80–500 Mbp long",
            "c) 80–300 bp long",
            "d) 100–3000 bp long"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There exists also (6–8 kbp long) interspersed nuclear elements (LINES). Different types of transposable elements are present in high copy numbers in mammalian genomes in varying manner."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "_____ of the human genome comprises one particular family of the SINE Element, designated Alu (1.2 million copies).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 20%",
            "c) 60%",
            "d) 40%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ten percent of the human genome comprises one particular family of the SINE Element. And 14.6% of one particular LINE designated LINE1 (593,000 copies) are present."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "The human genome contains about _________ of class II of elements that probably predate human evolution (Smit 1996).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2,000 copies",
            "b) 200,000 copies",
            "c) 2,00,00,000 copies",
            "d) 20,00,000 copies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Human and mouse chromosomal regions that have a low density of genes are AT-rich and have more Alu or B1/B2 (SINES) than LINE1 elements. Whereas the reverse is true for regions that have a high gene density, and those regions are more GC-rich."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "A third category of TEs has features of both class I and class II TEs. These miniature, inverted repeat TEs (MITES) are ________ in length.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400 bp",
            "b) 500 Mbp",
            "c) 300 kbp",
            "d) 600 kbp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The class of TEs, class II, is made up of elements that employ a DNA-based mechanism of transposition. Class II elements also include the Activation-Dissociation (Ac-Ds) family in maize and the P element in Drosophila."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "Which of the given features is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TEs are present in few particular chromosomes",
            "b) TEs are present in all of the chromosomes",
            "c) Abundance of TEs varies",
            "d) TEs can comprise a large portion of the genomes of higher eukaryotes, both plants and animals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: They were discovered in diverse flowering plants where they are frequently associated with regulatory regions of genes. Hence, they could be exerting an influence on regulation of gene expression."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "Eukaryotic genes that encode proteins are interrupted by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) exons of varying length and number",
            "b) introns of varying length and number",
            "c) exons of varying length and but same number",
            "d) introns of varying number but same length"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: TEs are present in all of the chromosomes, ranging from bacteria to humans, but their abundance varies. They can comprise a large portion of the genomes of higher eukaryotes, thus, only a small fraction of the genome of these organisms carries gene sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "Screening the predicted protein sequences against ______ library confirms the prediction and expression of the gene.",
        "Options": [
            "a) expressed sequence tag (EST)",
            "b) tags",
            "c) palindromes",
            "d) proteomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cost and efficiency of this process has been greatly improved by automatic methods of sequence assembly, first used for the sequencing of the bacterium H. influenza. This same method of assembly was also used, in part, to complete the sequencing of the Drosophila and human genomes in a timely manner."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "In case of genome sequence assembly which of the given statement is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Full chromosomal sequences are   assembled from the overlaps in a highly redundant set of fragments by an automatic computational method or from the fragment order on a physical map",
            "b) Chromosome cloning is carried out in   bacterial artifical chromosomes (BACs)",
            "c) Chromosomes of a target organism are purified, fragmented, and subcloned in fragments of size hundreds of bp",
            "d) Genome sequences are assembled from DNA sequence fragments of approximate length 500 bp obtained using DNA sequencing machines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a new genome, each predicted gene is translated into a protein sequence; the collection of protein sequences encoded by the genome is the proteome of the organism. every protein in the proteome is then used as a query sequence in a database similarity search. Matching database sequences are realigned with the query sequence to evaluate the extent and significance of the alignment."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "Gene identification in prokaryotic organisms is simplified by their lacking _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) exons",
            "b) introns",
            "c) coding segments",
            "d) useful nucleotide sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The collective information on proteome function can then be further analyzed by self-comparison to find duplicated genes (paralogs) and by a proteome-by-proteome comparison to identify orthologs, genes that have maintained the same function through speciation, and other sequence and evolutionary relationships that are important for metabolic, regulatory, and cellular functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "Which of the given statement is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The predicted set of proteins for the genome is referred to as the proteome",
            "b) The amino acid sequence of proteins encoded by the predicted genes is used as a query of the protein sequence databases in a database similarity search",
            "c) A match of a predicted protein sequence to one or more database sequences   serves only to identify the gene function but it doesn’t validate the gene prediction",
            "d) The genome sequence is annotated with the information on gene content and predicted structure, gene location, and functional predictions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chromosomes of a target organism are purified, fragmented, and subcloned in fragments of size hundreds of kbp and not bp.  The BAC fragments are then further subcloned as smaller fragments into plasmid vectors for DNA sequencing."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "Which of the following information is not directly obtained by microarray analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Which genes are expressed at a particular stage of the cell cycle",
            "b) Which genes are expressed at a particular stage of developmental cycle of an organism",
            "c) Which genes are depleted at what time",
            "d) Genes that respond to a given environmental signal to the same extent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: TEs (Transposable Elements) can comprise one-half or more of the genome sequence. Eukaryotic genomes comprise classes of repeated elements, including tandem repeats present in centromeres and telomeres, dispersed tandem repeats (minisatellites and macrosatellites), and interdispersed TEs."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "Which of the given statement is incorrect about Functional Genomics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Functional genomics involves the preparation of mutant or transgenic organisms with a mutant form of a particular gene usually designed to prevent expression of the gene",
            "b) An abnormal properties of the mutant organism does not reveal the gene function",
            "c) When two or more members of a gene family are found, rather than a single match to a known gene, the biological activity of these members may be analyzed by functional genomics to look for diversification of function in the family",
            "d) A more detailed analysis of the relative amount of sequence variability in a chromosomal region within populations of closely related species can reveal the presence of genes that are under selection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Once the sequence patterns that are characteristic of the genes in a particular prokaryotic organism (e.g, codon usage, codon neighbor preference) have been found, gene locations in the genome sequence can be predicted quite accurately. The presence of introns in eukaryotic genomes makes gene prediction more involved because, in addition to the above features, locations of intron–exon and exon–intron splice junctions must also be predicted."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "Which of the given statement is incorrect about the gene map?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene order in two related organisms reflects the order that was present in a common ancestor genome. Chromosomal breaks followed by reassembly of fragments in a different order can produce new gene maps",
            "b) Gene order is only revealed by the physical order of genes on the chromosome",
            "c) Sequence variations (polymorphisms) that are close to (tightly linked) a trait may be used to trace the trait by virtue of the fact that the polymorphism and the trait are seldom separated from one generation to the next",
            "d) These types of evolutionary changes in genomes have been modeled by computational methods"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A match of a predicted protein sequence to one or more database sequences not only serves to identify the gene function, but also validates the gene prediction. Pseudogenes, gene copies that have lost function, may also be found in this analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "WU-BLAST produces P scores and BLAST (NCBI) produces E scores where _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) E = ln (1 + P2)",
            "b) E = ln (1 – P2)",
            "c) E = ln (1 + P)",
            "d) E = ln (1 – P)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The database was made by performing an all-by-all genome comparison across a spectrum of prokaryotic organisms and a portion of the yeast proteome. Orthologous pairs of sequence were then merged with clusters or orthologous pairs (COGs) for multiple proteomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "In Protein 2D gel Electrophoresis, Individual proteins produced by the genome can be separated to _____ by this method and specific ones identified by various _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) smaller extent, biochemical and immunological tests",
            "b) a large extent, biochemical and immunological tests",
            "c) a large extent, biochemical tests only",
            "d) smaller extent, purely mechanical tests"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For values less than 0.05, E = P. The choice of a < 10-20 score is a conservative one for identification of orthologs that should have a similar domain structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "_______ of the Drosophila sequence is composed of TEs and _____ is heterochromatic regions that do not include genes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) one-fourth, one-third",
            "b) one-fifth, one-fourth",
            "c) one-sixth, one-eighth",
            "d) one-sixth, one-third"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Genome regions that encode these sequences can then be identified and the corresponding gene located. A similar method may be used to identify the gene that encodes a particular protein that has been purified and characterized in the laboratory."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "Yeast is about ______ compact than E. coli.",
        "Options": [
            "a) fivefold, less",
            "b) threefold, more",
            "c) twofold, less",
            "d) twofold, more"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Moreover, changes in levels of proteins in response to an environment signal can be monitored in much the same way as a microarray analysis is performed. Microarrays only detect untranslated mRNAs, whereas a two-dimensional gel protein analysis detects translation products, thus revealing an additional level of regulation."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "The ________ are _______ by genetic structure to retroviruses.",
        "Options": [
            "a) STR retrotransposons, related",
            "b) LTR retrotransposons, related",
            "c) STR transposons, related",
            "d) LTR retrotransposons, not related"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From this information, the metabolic pathways and metabolic activities of the organism will become apparent. In some cases, the apparent absence of a gene in a well-represented pathway may lead to a more detailed search for the gene. Clustering of genes in the pathway on the genome of a related organism can provide a further hint as to where the gene may be located."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "Which of the given statement is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) As in an all-by-all protein comparison within a proteome, a matrix of alignment scores with E values is made, and the most closely related sequences in the two organisms are identified",
            "b) To perform a between-proteome analysis, proteome databases are made for the known and predicted genes of two or more genomes",
            "c) Each protein of one proteome is selected in turn as a query of the proteome of another organism or the combined proteome of a group of organisms",
            "d) Each protein of one proteome is selected in turn as a query of the proteome of another single organism only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hence, in the euchromatic regions, the gene density in the Drosophila genome is one gene per 9 kb. Despite the fact that the lower number of predicted genes in Drosophila is smaller than that of the other genomes, the amount of functional diversity, as evidenced by protein family representation, is similar."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "Which of the given statement is incorrect about proteome analyses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For BLAST, setting an effective database size appropriate for each search and program is important",
            "b) Due to the large number of comparisons that must be made in these types of analyses and due to the volume of program output, the procedure must be automated on a local machine using Perl scripts or a similar method and a database system",
            "c) BLAST is used for obtaining a correct statistical evaluation of alignment scores",
            "d) BLAST does not give statistical evaluation of alignment scores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Each protein encoded by the genome is used as a query in database similarity searches to identify similar database proteins, some having a known structure or function. Additional searches of EST databases can be used to identify additional relatives of the query sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "An all-against-all analysis requires first making a database of the proteome. This database is then sequentially searched by each individual protein sequence of the proteome using a rapid database similarity search tool such as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) XPBLAST",
            "b) WU-BLAST",
            "c) BLAST",
            "d) FASTA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: P values of WU-BLAST are similar to E values of NCBI BLAST (Rubin et al. 2000) for values of P and E < 0.05. This analysis generates a matrix of alignment scores, each with an E value and corresponding alignment for each pair of proteins. Also, the E value of an alignment score is the probability that an alignment score as good as the one found would be observed between two random or unrelated sequences in a search of a database of the same size."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "Evolutionary modeling can include various types of analyses. Which is mostly not one of them?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The prediction of chromosomal rearrangements",
            "b) Eu/Hetero-chromatin structures",
            "c) Duplications at gene, chromosomal and full genome level",
            "d) Duplications at the protein domain level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Option Eu/Hetero-chromatin structures indicate structural studies. Also as mentioned, analysis of the prediction of chromosomal rearrangements that preceded the present arrangement is done (e.g., a comparison of mouse and human chromosomes)."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "Which of the given statement is incorrect about Clusters of functionally related genes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In microbial genomes, genes specifying a metabolic pathway may be contiguous on the genome where they are coregulated transcriptionally in an operon by a common promoter",
            "b) In related organisms, gene order on the chromosome is least likely to be conserved",
            "c) As the relationship between the organisms decreases, local groups of genes remain clustered together, but chromosomal rearrangements move the clusters to other locations",
            "d) The function of a particular gene can sometimes be predicted, given the known function of a neighboring, closely linked gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In related organisms, both gene content of the genome and gene order on the chromosome are likely to be conserved. "
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "Which of the given statement is incorrect about Orthologs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In comparing two proteomes, a common standard is to require that for each pair of orthologs, the first of the pair is the best hit when the second is used to query the proteome of the first",
            "b) To identify orthologs, each protein in the proteome of an organism is used as a query in a similarity search of a database comprising the proteomes of only one different organism",
            "c) The best hit in each proteome is likely to be with an ortholog of the query gene",
            "d) Orthologs are genes that are so highly conserved by sequence in different genomes that the proteins they encode are strongly predicted to have the same structure and function and to have arisen from a common ancestor through speciation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To identify orthologs, each protein in the proteome of an organism is used as a query in a similarity search of a database comprising the proteomes of one or more different organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "In protein/domain analysis, each protein in the predicted proteome is again used as a query of a curated protein sequence database such as ____ in order to locate similar domains and sequences. To find orthologs, very low E value scores (E<10<20) for the alignment score and an alignment that includes 60–80% of the query sequence are generally required in order to avoid matches to paralogs.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PubChem",
            "b) Genbank",
            "c) MeSH",
            "d) SwissProt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The domain composition of each protein is also determined by searching for matches in domain databases such as Interpro. The analysis reveals how many domains and domain combinations are present in the proteome, and reveals any unusual representation that might have biological significance. The number of expressed genes in each family can also be compared to the number in other organisms to determine whether or not there has been an expansion of the family in the genome."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "Which of the following information Sequence comparisons do not provide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene relationships",
            "b) Function history",
            "c) Evolutionary history",
            "d) Gene locations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The availability of complete genome sequences makes possible a comparison of all of the proteins encoded by one genome, the proteome of that organism, with those of another. Because the genome sequence provides both the sequence and the map location of each gene, both the sequence and location can be compared."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proteins may be clustered into families on the basis of either sequence or structural similarity",
            "b) Proteins often comprise separate domains",
            "c) The number of protein sequences that are available is insufficient to determine that domain shuffling occurs in evolution",
            "d) Proteins are modular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Map locations of orthologous genes may also be compared. If a set of genes is grouped together at a particular chromosomal location, and if a set of similar genes is also grouped together in the genome of another organism, these groups share an evolutionary history."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two tandem copies of a gene are produced while Proteins with new functions are produced",
            "b) Proteins with new functions are produced by a gene duplication event",
            "c) Assortment and reassortment of protein domains takes place in individual genomes",
            "d) In no case the two duplicated genes both undergo change"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The number of protein sequences is sufficient unlike mentioned in option c. The comparisons of proteomes of different organisms can identify the type of domain changes and also provide an indication as to what biological role they may have in a particular organism. "
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The processes of domain assortment and gene duplication produce families of proteins in organisms",
            "b) Following speciation, a newly derived genome will inherit the families of ancestor organisms, but will also develop new ones to meet evolutionary challenges",
            "c) Comparison of each of the proteins encoded by an organism with every protein, an all-against-all comparison, reveals which protein families have been amplified and what rearrangements have occurred as steps in the evolutionary process",
            "d) When two or more proteins in the proteome share a high degree of similarity they are least likely to be paralogs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a possibility, two duplicated genes both undergo change, but interactions between the proteins stabilize the original function and support the evolution of new ones. Through mutation and natural selection, one of the copies can develop a new function, leaving the other copy to cover for the original function. However, because most mutations are deleterious to function, often one of the copies becomes a pseudogene. Not all gene duplications are thought to have the above effects."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about All-against-all Self-comparison?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A comparison of each protein in the proteome with all other proteins distinguishes unique proteins from proteins that have arisen from gene duplication, and also reveals the number of protein families but the domain content of these proteins cannot be known",
            "b) In all-against-all proteome comparison, each protein is used as a query in a similarity search against the remaining proteome",
            "c) In all-against-all proteome comparison, the similar sequences are ranked by the quality and length of the alignments found",
            "d) In all-against-all proteome comparison, The search is conducted with each alignment score receiving a statistical evaluation (P or E value)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When two or more proteins in the proteome share a high degree of similarity because they share the same set of domains, they are likely to be paralogs, genes that arose by gene duplication events. Proteins that align over shorter regions share some domains, but also may not share others. Although gene duplication events could have created such variation, other rearrangements may have also occurred, blurring the evolutionary history."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about Cluster analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clustering organizes the proteins into groups by some objective criterion",
            "b) One criterion for a matching protein pair is the statistical significance of their alignment score",
            "c) The P or E value from BLAST searches cannot be the criterion for a matching protein pair",
            "d) A criterion for clustering proteins is the distance between each pair of sequences in a multiple sequence alignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The domain content of these proteins may also be analyzed. in all-against-all proteome comparison, a match between a query sequence and another proteome sequence with the same domain structure will produce a high-scoring, highly significant alignment. These proteins are designated paralogs because they have almost certainly originated from a gene duplication event."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about Clustering by making subgraphs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Each sequence is a vertex and each pair of sequences that is matched with a significant alignment score is joined by an edge that is weighted according to the statistical significance of the alignment score",
            "b) One way to identify the most strongly supported clusters is simply to add the most weakly supported edges in the graph",
            "c) One way to identify the most strongly supported clusters is simply to remove the most weakly supported edges in the graph",
            "d) An edge is weighted according to the statistical significance of the alignment score"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Option c and b mean the same yet are different by the negation in option c.The lower this value, the better the alignment. There will be a cutoff P or E value at which the matches in the BLAST search are no longer considered significant. A value of P or E = 0.01–0.05 is usually the point at which the alignment score is no longer considered to be significant in  order to focus on a more closely related group of proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about Clustering by single linkage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In First step, a group of related sequences found in the all-against-all proteome comparison is subjected to a multiple sequence alignment usually by CLUSTALW",
            "b) A neighbor-joining algorithm is rarely used in this method",
            "c) This procedure and the algorithms are the same as those used to make a phylogenetic tree by the distance methods",
            "d) A distance matrix that shows the number of amino acid changes between each pair of sequences is made"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As weaker and weaker links are removed, the remaining combinations of vertices and edges represent most strongly linked sequences. This type of analysis was performed on an initial collection of E. coli genes by Labedan and Riley (1995)."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about Grouping Sequences?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The problem of deciding which sequences to include in the same group or cluster and which to separate into different groups or clusters is a recurring one",
            "b) Divergence is necessary, but the sequences chosen should be clearly related based on inspection of each pair-wise alignment and a statistical analysis",
            "c) The conservative approach is to group distinct sequences",
            "d) The adventurous approach is to choose a set of marginally alignable sequences to pursue the difficult task of making a multiple sequence alignment and then to make profile models that may recognize divergence but will also give false predictions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The conservative approach is to group only very similar sequences together. However, in making a conservative multiple sequence alignment with only very alike sequences, it is not possible to analyze the evolutionary divergence that may have occurred in a family of proteins. Furthermore, if a matrix or profile model is made from this alignment, that model will not be useful for identifying more divergent members of a family."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about Clusters of orthologous groups?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Using the protein from one of the organisms to search the proteome of the other for high-scoring matches should identify the ortholog as the highest- scoring match, or best hit",
            "b) When entire proteomes of the two organisms are available, orthologs may be identified",
            "c) a pair of orthologous genes in two organisms share so much sequence similarity that they may be assumed to have arisen from a common ancestor gene",
            "d) each of the orthologs belongs to a family composed of  paralogous sequences but irrelevant or not related to each other"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In many cases, each of the orthologs belongs to a family composed of paralogous sequences related to each other by gene duplication events. Hence, in the above database search, the ortholog will not only match the orthologous sequence in the second proteome but also these other paralogous sequences. The objective of the clusters of orthologous groups (COG) approach is to identify all matching proteins in the organisms; defined as an orthologous group related by both speciation and gene duplication events."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about Clusters of orthologous groups?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Paralogs may include a best hit or a high-scoring match of one of the sequences by another, but the reciprocal match can have low similarity that does not have to be significant",
            "b) Paralogs defined by sets of three matching sequences in the selected organisms were kept separated from the clusters",
            "c) Orthologous pairs were first defined by the best hits in reciprocal searches",
            "d) To produce COGs, similarity searches were performed among the proteomes of phylogenetically distinct clades of prokaryotes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Paralogs defined by sets of three matching sequences in the selected organisms were also added to these clusters. Sixty percent of the original set of 720 COGs does not include paralogs, or includes paralogs from one lineage only, suggesting that there has not been extensive duplication of this group."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about Searching for orthologs to a protein family in an EST database?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Searches of EST databases for matches to a query sequence routinely produce minimal amounts of output that must be searched manually for significant hits",
            "b) ESTs with a high percent identity with the query sequence, a long alignment with the query sequence, and a very low E value of the alignment score represent groups of paralogous and orthologous genes",
            "c) To identify orthologs as the most closely related sequence, ESTs were aligned using the amino acid alignment as a guide",
            "d) To identify orthologs as the most closely related sequence, a phylogenetic tree was produced by the maximum likelihood method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Many sequences arise from near the 3’ end of the mRNA, although every effort is usually made to read as far 5’ as possible into the upstream portion of the cDNA. Because not all of the genes may be expressed in the tissues chosen for analysis, the library will often not be complete."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about Family and Domain Analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene identification of predicted proteins in the genome is designed to discover the metabolic features of an organism",
            "b) In a particular organism or group of organisms, one particular domain can be expanded to perform a particular function",
            "c) Comparison of the domain content of an entire proteome with that of another proteome cannot help in revealing the biological roles of diverse domains in different organisms",
            "d) Different proteins are mosaics of domains that occur in different combinations in a given protein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Searches of EST databases for matches to a query sequence routinely produce large amounts of output that must be searched manually for significant hits.  an automatic method was described in 1999 utilizing a computer script, FAST-PAN, that scans EST databases with multiple queries from a protein family, sorts the alignment scores, and produces charts and alignments of the matches found."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about Ancient Conserved Regions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The method involves database similarity searches of the SwissProt database with human, worm, yeast, or E. coli genes and identification of matches with sequences from a different phylum than the query sequence",
            "b) An analysis of ACRs that predate the radiation of the major animal phyla some 580–540 million years ago suggested that 50–60% of coding sequences are ACRs",
            "c) These ACRs may represent proteins present at the time of the prokaryotic–eukaryotic divergence",
            "d) Phylogenetically diverse groups of organisms have been analyzed for the presence of conserved proteins and protein domains that have been conserved over long periods of evolutionary time, called ancient conserved regions or ACRs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a particular organism or group of organisms, various domains can be expanded to perform a particular function. More than 2000 fly and worm proteins are multidomain proteins, compared to about one-third this number in yeast."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about Horizontal Gene Transfer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The genomes of most organisms are derived by vertical transmission, the inheritance of chromosomes from parents to offspring from one generation to the next",
            "b) It is the acquisition of genetic material from a different organism",
            "c) The transferred material   becomes a temporary addition to the recipient genome",
            "d) An extreme example is the proposed endosymbiont origin of mitochondria in eukaryotic cells and chloroplasts in plants"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The analysis of ACRs 580–540 million years ago suggested that 20–40% of coding sequences are ACRs. For example, a search with 1916 E. coli proteins detected 266 ACRs found in 439 sequences, roughly one-quarter of the SwissProt database."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about Horizontal Gene Transfer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a significant source of genome variation in bacteria, allowing them to exploit new environments",
            "b) Such transfer is rendered possible by a variety of natural mechanisms in bacteria for transferring DNA from one species to another",
            "c) Detection of HT is made possible by the fact that each genome of each bacterial species has a unique base composition",
            "d) The time of transfer of DNA cannot be estimated by the composition of the HT DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The transferred material becomes a permanent addition to the recipient genome. Although these exchanges do not occur very often on a generation-to-generation basis, a significant number can occur over a period of hundreds of millions of years."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "Which of the given statement is incorrect regarding MAGPIE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It analyzes the genome using a set of automated processes",
            "b) It is designed for high-throughput genome sequence analysis",
            "c) It is unable to locate potential promoters",
            "d) It automatically annotates genomic sequence data and maintains a daily up-to-date record in response to user queries about one or more genomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: GeneQuiz is an integrated system for large-scale biological sequence analysis that uses a variety of search and analysis methods using current sequence databases. By applying expert rules to the results of the different methods, GeneQuiz creates a compact summary of findings."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "Which of the given statement is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Paralogous sequences, frequently are found to have dissimilar functions",
            "b) An early classification scheme for eight related groups of E. coli genes included categories for enzymes, transport elements",
            "c) An early classification scheme for eight related groups of E. coli genes included categories for regulators, membranes, structural elements, protein factors, leader peptides, and carriers",
            "d) Ninety percent of E. coli genes related by significant sequence similarity fell into these same broad categories"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The system also uses a set of rules in logic programming to make decisions that may be used to interpret information from various sources. It has been used to locate potential promoters, terminators, start codons, Shine-Dalgarno sites, DNA motif sites, co-transcription units, and putative operons in microbial genomes. These sites are shown on a map display of the genome that may be edited."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "The designation ECa.b.c.d conveys information. Which of the following is not one of it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One of twelve main classes of biochemical reactions",
            "b) The group of substrate molecule",
            "c) The nature of chemical bond that is involved in the reaction",
            "d) Designation for acceptor molecules (cofactors)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Genes that are significantly similar in an organism, i.e., paralogous sequences, frequently are found to have a related biological function. This discovery follows the expected origin of paralogs by gene duplication events, leaving one copy to perform the original function and producing a second copy to develop a new function not too distant from the original one under evolutionary selection."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "Two species that have recently diverged from a common ancestor might be expected to have a ________ set of genes and ________ chromosomes with these genes positioned along the chromosomes in the same order.",
        "Options": [
            "a) distinct, similar",
            "b) similar, distinct",
            "c) similar, dissimilar",
            "d) similar, similar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Option “One of twelve main classes of biochemical reactions” should be ‘one of six main classes of biochemical reactions’. The Enzyme Commission numbers formulated by the Enzyme Commission of the International Union of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology provide a detailed way to classify enzymes based on the biochemical reactions they catalyze."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "Which of the given statement is incorrect about the observations made with regard to gene order?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Order is highly conserved in closely related species",
            "b) Order in closely related species becomes changed by rearrangements over evolutionary time",
            "c) As more and more rearrangements occur, there will no longer be any correspondence in the order of orthologous genes on the chromosome of one organism with that of a second organism",
            "d) Order is less conserved in closely related species"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Although catalyzing the same reaction, these enzymes showed variations in metabolic regulation of their activity. More than one-half of multiple enzymes in E. coli share significant sequence similarity; i.e., they are paralogs. However, the remainder do not share any sequence similarity."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "Which of the given statement is incorrect about the Chromosomal Rearrangements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Comparison of the number of rearrangements in a given period of evolutionary history may vary significantly from one organism to the next",
            "b) If gene A has a neighboring gene B, then if an ortholog of A occurs in another genome, there is an increased probability of an ortholog of B also occurring in the other organism",
            "c) If gene A has a neighboring gene B, then if an ortholog of A occurs in another genome, the B ortholog is more likely to be a neighbor of the A ortholog of the genome of the second species if the two species are more divergent",
            "d) In general, the order of orthologs is not well conserved in prokaryotes when the genomes have diverged sufficiently that the orthologs have < 50% identity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By this scheme, plants devote more than one-half of their genome to energy metabolism. Whereas, animals devote one-half of their genome to communication-related functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "Which of the given statement is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In a given organism or species, genes are found in a given order that is maintained on the chromosomes from one generation to the next",
            "b) Genes with a related function are frequently found to be distorted on a chromosome",
            "c) A possibility is that there is genetic variation (alleles) within each gene in a cluster of a given species and that only certain allelic combinations of different genes are compatible",
            "d) Clustering of related genes presumably provides an evolutionary advantage to a species"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Over evolutionary time, the sequence of each pair of genes will slowly diverge, as the species diverge and other changes such as gene duplication and gene loss change the gene content. In addition, the order of genes also changes over evolutionary time as a result of chromosomal rearrangements."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about global gene regulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One way to obtain useful information about a genome is to determine which genes are induced or repressed in response to a phase of the cell cycle",
            "b) Sets of a gene whose expression rises and falls under the same condition are likely to have a related function",
            "c) Sets of a gene whose expression rises and falls under the same condition are likely to have dissimilar functions",
            "d) Cell cycle is a developmental phase, or a response to the environment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In addition, a pattern of gene expression may also be an indicator of abnormal cellular regulation and is a useful tool in cancer diagnosis. Because genomes, especially eukaryotic genomes, are so large, a new technology has been developed for studying the regulation of thousands of genes on a microscope slide."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about Microarray (or microchip) analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a new technology in which all of the genes of an organism are represented by oligonucleotide sequences spread out in an 80 x 80 array on microscope slides",
            "b) The oligonucleotide sequences cannot be synthesized directly on the slide",
            "c) The oligonucleotides are collectively hybridized to a labeled cDNA library prepared by reverse-transcribing mRNA from cells",
            "d) The amount of label binding to each oligonucleotide spot reflects the amount of mRNA in the cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The oligonucleotide sequences can also be synthesized directly on the slide at densities of up to one million per square centimeter. Genes that are responding the same way to an environmental signal, in this case the addition of serum to serum-starved skin cells are clustered together in a display. From this analysis, a set of genes that responds in an identical manner may be identified."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "Which of the given statements is incorrect about Microarray Analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is designed to detect global changes in transcription in a genome",
            "b) It provides information about the levels of protein products of the genes",
            "c) The proteins are first separated in a column on the basis of size and then across a second dimension on a slab on the basis of charge",
            "d) Labeled protein samples may also be extracted from treated cells and separated by two-dimensional gel electrophoresis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Automatic methods for clustering related sets of genes have been devised. The first of these methods, hierarchical clustering, is commonly used, but the other two methods are better designed to detect differences in patterns over a set of time points or samples."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "In cluster analysis of microarray data– If Xi is the log odds value for gene X at time i, then for two genes X and Y and N observations, a similarity score is calculated. S(X,Y) is also known as the Pearson correlation coefficent. Xoffset and Yoffset can be the mean of the observations on X or Y, respectively, in which case is the standard deviation, or else Xoffset and Yoffset can be set to zero when a reference state is used. Which of the following best represents it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) S(X,Y) = \\(\\frac{1}{N-2}\\) ∑i=1,N . (Xi – Xoffset) (Yi + Yoffset)/ϕxQY",
            "b) S(X,Y) = \\(\\frac{1}{N}\\) ∑i=1,N . (Xi – Xoffset) (Yi – Yoffset)/ϕxQY",
            "c) S(X,Y) = \\(\\frac{1}{N-1}\\) ∑i=1,N . (Xi + Xoffset) (Yi + Yoffset)/ϕxQY",
            "d) S(X,Y) = \\(\\frac{1}{N}\\) ∑i=1,N+2 . (Xi + Xoffset) (Yi – Yoffset)/ϕxQY"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Microarray analysis is designed to detect global changes in transcription in a genome but does not provide information about the levels of protein products of the genes, which may also be subject to translational regulation. This method also can resolve thousands of proteins based on size and charge. There are databases of the patterns found in different organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "In cluster analysis of microarray data– A node is created between the _________ scoring pair, and the gene expressed profiles of these two genes are averaged and the joined elements are weighted by the _________ of elements they contain.",
        "Options": [
            "a) lowest, frequency",
            "b) average, sequence",
            "c) lowest, number",
            "d) highest, number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: After values of S(X,Y) have been calculated for all gene combinations, the most closely related pairs are identified in an above-diagonal scoring matrix. The object of clustering is to identify genes that respond the same way to the environmental treatment. Each gene is compared to every other gene and a gene similarity score (metric) is produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "In cluster analysis of microarray data– For n genes, the process is repeated ________ times until a single element remains.",
        "Options": [
            "a) n2",
            "b) n",
            "c) n-1",
            "d) n-4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The node is created as mentioned. The matrix is then updated replacing the two joined elements by the node."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "In SVMs (Support vector machines) Data points are log-transformed and normalized as in method A, where for N observations of a gene i, the log transform Xi of the expression level Ei and reference level Ri is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Xi = \\(\\frac{Log (E_i/R_i)}{\\sqrt{\\sum_{j=1,N} Log_{z-2} (E_j/R_j)}}\\) ",
            "b) Xj = \\(\\frac{Log (E_j/R_i)}{\\sqrt{\\sum_{j=1,N} Log_z (E_j/R_j)}}\\) ",
            "c) Xi = \\(\\frac{Log (E_i/R_i)}{\\sqrt{\\sum_{j=1,(N-1)} Log_z (E_j/R_j)}}\\) ",
            "d) Xi = \\(\\frac{Log (E_i/R_i)}{\\sqrt{\\sum_{j=1,N} Log_z (E_j/R_j)}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This number of iterations gives the best results. In the final dendrogram, the order of genes within a cluster is determined by simple weighting schemes, e.g., average dendrogram level. "
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "Other types of evidence for a relationship between two genes are also given that are not dependent in sequence similarity. Which of the following is a wrong statement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) genes are closely linked on the same chromosomes",
            "b) genes are transcribed from the same DNA strand",
            "c) gene fusions are observed between otherwise separate genes",
            "d) phylogenetic profiles show the genes are not that commonly present in organisms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the mentioned case they are more likely to share the same function. A considerable fraction of a genome may encode proteins whose function may not be identified in this manner because the proteins are not related to another of known function."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "Which of the given statement is untrue about functional genomics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Known functions are derived from experimental evidence in molecular biology and genetic studies with model organisms",
            "b) Non-Orthologous genes between biologically distinct species can be identified, and it is strong evidence for a related function",
            "c) Sequence-based methods of gene prediction can be augmented by the types of genome comparisons that are designed to identify related genes based on common patterns of expression, evolutionary profiles, chromosomal locations, and other features",
            "d) Genome analysis depends to a large extent on sequence analysis methods that identify gene function based on similarity between proteins of unknown function and proteins of known function"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Phylogenetic profiles reveal the genes are both commonly present in many organisms implying they have interdependent metabolic functions. Option a and b imply coordinated regulation in an operon-like structure. Option c suggests the encoded proteins are physically associated in a common complex. "
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "In Reverse-genetics analysis of gene function– Even though a particular gene may be _____ ortholog of a gene of known function in another organism, that gene may be acquired by a _____ function.",
        "Options": [
            "a) a highly predicted, similar",
            "b) a highly predicted, same",
            "c) a highly predicted, novel",
            "d) less predicted, novel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Branch lengths are shorter for closely related proteins and thicker when two or more prediction methods indicate a relationship. The links are based on experimental data, proteins whose homologs are known to operate sequentially in metabolic pathways, proteins that evolved in a correlated fashion as evidenced by presence in fully sequenced genomes, proteins whose homologs are fused into a single protein in another organism, and proteins whose mRNA expression profiles are similar under a range of cellular and environmental conditions. "
    }
]